This body is the biological expression
of the soul’s delusion;
it’s constructed
of exploiting tendencies.
[Facebook | Egocentric World]
So, as we abandon envisioning ourselves
as exploiting agents,
and become dedicating agents,
we start reconceiving that
I can achieve my potential,
my prospect, my identity
through service, through dedication,
not through exploitation.
tad viddhi praṇipātena
paripraśnena sevayā
[Bg: 4.34]
Saraswatī 􏰅Ṭhākur said this,
“When we are bowing
and approaching the lotus feet of guru,
and we are bowing,”
once he said, “It means
we are finished with this world.”
What does that mean?
The world, where we thought,
“I am the centre”,—
the egocentric world—
“I am the centre, and I have
so many friends on Facebook.”
[Laughing]
That’s one example.
But that idea, “I am the Lord
of all I survey, I am the centre.”
The narcissistic centre,
an egocentric conception
of ourselves and the world—
everything is meant to please me.
That which pleases me
is good,
that which does not please me
is bad.
To reconfigure ourselves
along the lines of theocentricity—
what is pleasing to Kṛṣṇa,
and by extension, His devotees—
ānukūlyasya saṅkalpaḥ
prātikūlyasya varjanam
[Hbv: 11.417]
A new standard for judging,
what is good and bad;
desirable, undesirable;
progressive, regressive;
evolving, devolving.
New criteria
for making those assessments.
So then, now withdrawing
from the plane of exploitation,
putting my energy
towards dedication,
then we are acquiring
dedicating tendencies.
As we acquire
dedicating tendencies—
the old self is dissolving,
and vanishing,
and a new self
is manifesting.
Once Guru Mahārāj
compared it to,
he said,
“As you go, say, East
you proceed East, automatically
you are withdrawing from West.
So we are going to think, “Well,
I want to withdraw from West.”
No, just go East.
Go in the Eastern direction,
and automatically
you’ll withdraw from West.
That’s what it’s like.
And you’ll see yourself
in a new light, with a new form
that’s constructed
of dedicating tendencies.
All other concepts of self
are misconceived identities,
false notions of the self.
Guru Mahārāj says,
“We learn from Einstein
that reality is a thing
plus its potential.”
Our potential is as servitors
in the spiritual domain.
Without that, to the degree
that is absent—
we are in an unreal,
unrealistic,
untenable state of self
or existence.
So reality is a thing
plus its potential.
The reality
of ‘who you are’,
so when your serving potential
is activated.
That’s sevā, seva-mayo yam loka—
the world of sevā.