If in this world
we’re constantly searching
for ideals in terms
of the most beautiful,
the most sweet,
the most charming,
the most affectionate,
the most loving …
[Absolute Soulmate]
the person who could be considered
my best counterpart;
an ideal representation of beauty,
charm, sweetness, love, and affection,
of what is to be seen, heard, felt,
tasted, touched and smelled.
What if that
is the ultimate reality?
Instead we’re being told
that the ultimate source of everything
is something impersonal
and maybe unconscious.
So that which is dead
and unconscious
is giving life
to so many conscious beings;
what cannot see
is gifting sight to so many;
what has no capacity to hear
is allowing everyone to hear;
what cannot taste is giving
everyone the tasting capacity.
We’ve swallowed
this type of …
What’s the scientific term?
—‘Bullshit’— I think that’s
the scientific term:
we’ve swallowed this wholesale,
and denied the Personality of Godhead,
and think that we’re very modern,
very advanced scientific thinkers.
Because we can’t accommodate
how the original source
of all sensual ability
and capacity
can also have
sensual ability and capacity—
we deny that: that’s just
that would be just too much.
I mean that would be
like God or something. [Laughing]
Right,
that would be inconceivable
that an absolute personality,
who is absolutely beautiful,
absolutely charming, absolutely funny,
absolutely tasteful,
who can reciprocate simultaneously
the ideal hankering of every being—
that would be
the Absolute, of course.
So, that the Ultimate Reality is beautiful,
loving, charming, and sweet:
science is not prepared
to deal with that.