Einstein says, “Reality is an illusion,
albeit a very persistent one.”
[Inconceivable Story of God]
He means what’s conventionally conceived,
the objective world, that reality.
He rightly said, “It’s an illusion”.
He’s right.
What we take to be reality here
is an illusion.
And what people think is fictitious
is reality.
Like the Life of Pi movie,
where the man says,
“I’m gonna tell you a story
that will make you believe in God.”
Then he tells, for the sake of this
conversation, an inconceivable story.
He tells this to a Japanese
insurance agent,
who’s saying, “That’s unbelievable.
You’ll never get any money for that.”
“What if I tell you a story
that’s believable?”
“Yes!”
Then he tells a believable story,
and they say,
“Oh, we could give something for that.”
But then the man says, “But of the two
stories I told you, which do you prefer?”
And they go,
“We prefer the unbelievable one.”
That’s what he meant.
The story of God
is inconceivable.
The story of science, of rational,
appears to be believable
to so-called ‘rational mind’.
But the story of God
is inconceivable.
Of the two, we prefer
the inconceivable story of God
to the so-called rational narrative
of secular humanist and atheistic science.
Mr. Nietzsche says, “There are no facts,
there are only interpretations.”
We prefer this interpretation.