Hare Krishna. Yes, Prabhu. Some questions?
Dandavat, Mahārāja! We have a question from Krishnapada Prabhu, Salt Lake City.
We hear Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
saying that the environment is not the problem,
that we ourselves are the problem and not
to quarrel with the environment. But say,
when you are in a hot atmosphere and you are
wearing too many layers, do you not take off
some layers, move to a cooler spot or make
an adjustment to that environment?
Could you speak about this according to the perspective of our spiritual life?
In the Bhagavad-gītā
Krishna tells Arjuna:
mātrā-sparśās tu kaunteya śītoṣṇa-sukha-duḥkha-dāḥ
āgamāpāyino ’nityās tāṁs titikṣasva bhārata
[Bhagavad-gītā 2.14]
He says that the environment, karmic circumstances
we are surrounded by, and literally, the world
we find ourselves in, He compares to seasonal changes.
And His advice is tolerance, tāṁs titikṣasva
to tolerate it. And as He says,
Krishnapada in the question. So,
if necessary you remove some layers, or open
an umbrella, or put on more, according to
the circumstance. But that is not to blame
the environment or the circumstances as the
sole cause of your suffering. It’s a superficial
cause of suffering. But what is at the heart
of the matter, the root of the matter is something
else, that has placed us in this circumstance.
Ichchhā-dveṣa-samutthena dvandva-mohena
bhārata [Bhagavad-gītā 7.27]. Again in
the Gītā. And in Manu Saṁhitā: tamasā
bahu rūpeṇa veśṭitāḥ karmahetunā.
Manu says, “All these different life forms
you see…” And as I’ve told, the body
is the biological expression of the soul’s
delusion. And what is it based on?
Veśṭitāḥ karmahetunā, we’re all dressed in our karma—which is more to the point.
We have generated the circumstances that we
find ourselves in. Even from a scientific
point of view, for every action there’s
an equal and opposite reaction. And when the
subject of karma comes up in the Gītā, Krishna
to Arjuna, it’s interesting to note that
the first thing Krishna says to Arjuna—and
I’m paraphrasing—is, “It’s complicated.”
All right, or as Prabhupād said, “The intricacies of karma are difficult to know.” It’s complicated.
What does it say? “Even the experts are
bewildered,” I forget the verse, but it’s
saying, “in trying to understand the intricacies
of karma. It’s very complicated.” Because
you’re in a situation as a human being,
where you’re making real-time choices, and
that will have a future outcome. But you also
have the results, the reactions of former
actions, in different stages of development
and expression.
Rūpa Goswāmī discusses this quoting the Padma-purāṇa in the Bhakti-rasāmṛta-sindhu,
and he said, “Some karmic reactions are
in seed form, some of them have sprouted,
some have flowered, and some are bearing fruit.”
So they’re in all different stages of expression
and in the midst of that you’re making real-time
choices. So, Krishna tells Arjuna, “It’s complicated,”
but nonetheless, it is…
If for every action there’s an equal and
opposite reaction, in that sense, it’s warranted.
We are responsible for the karmic circumstances
that we find ourselves in. So, the message
of the Gītā, as He alludes here, Śrīla
Guru Mahārāja is saying, “Not to quarrel
with the environment,” but, as the aphorism
is there, or the cliché: “Healer heal thyself.”
Make an inner adjustment.
But if we want to pursue this line of thought
deeper, then—the pages o f the Bhāgavatam,
there’re the Brahmā-stuti, the prayers
of Brahmā:
tat te ’nukampāṁ su-samīkṣamāṇo
bhuñjāna evātma-kṛtaṁ vipākam
[Śrīmad Bhāgavatam 10.14.8]
Su-samīkṣa is the word that he [Lord Brahmā]
used. Samīkṣa means ‘to analyze.’ But
su-samīkṣa means ‘to scrutinize’—to
analyze very acutely, to take it to another level.
Tat te ’nukampāṁ su-samīkṣamāṇo.
So, in Guru Mahārāja’s words, “These
karmic circumstances that you find yourself
in, (that, footnote, we’ve generated), they’re
not to your liking or we're suffering .”Is it
meant to take you down, to undo you? Or is
there some way to interpret this in a positive light?”
“Here,” Guru Mahārāja says, “the devotee,
one with more advanced spiritual vision, with
greater depth, seeing beyond the superficial
aspect of any circumstance or situation, able
will be able to see deeper, will see the friendly hand
of Krishna in the background.”
Like the test. We know teachers do a flash-quiz,
a pop-quiz—it goes by various names. Unannounced
they decide to test the students. Why? Because
the teacher may have the impression that they’re
only feigning comprehension. So to see where
they’re at, as a whole, in terms of imbibing
the teachings. An unannounced pop-quiz is
given. Let’s say, “Now close the books,”
and here comes this test. And it’s usually
met with groans, or some irritation, or annoyance.
But why is the teacher doing this? Someone
might think like, “Our teacher is very mean.
It’s not a nice teacher, not a good teacher.”
But really, is that the case, or is it that
the teacher is really doing a service to the
students by this test coming, being given,
will allow them to identify upon the things
that they do not comprehend properly? To give
that their focus, their attention. It’ll
be revealed through testing
where the flaws are, where one needs to develop.
So, the greater the depths of devotional vision, the more favourable the interpretation of the circumstances.
We hear of Queen Kunti:
vipadaḥ santu tāḥ śaśvat
tatra tatra jagad-guro
bhavato darśanaṁ yat syād
apunar bhava-darśanam
[Śrīmad Bhāgavatam 1.8.25]
She’s reflecting upon her pastimes with
Krishna and the Pāṇḍavas. And we know,
the Pāṇḍavas repeatedly were put into
very dangerous situations, life-threatening
situations. And the point of emphasis from
her is that upon reflection she realizes:
those were the times of the greatest intensity of her focus, remembrance, dependence, taking
shelter. And that other times, when things
were seemingly fine and going on normally,
that there was a tendency to be distracted
from that which is substantial. To become
forgetful or complacent. So, she’s so advanced that she comes to the conclusion, saying:
vipadaḥ santu tāḥ śaśvat
tatra tatra jagad-guro
bhavato darśanaṁ yat syād
apunar bhava-darśanam
[Śrīmad Bhāgavatam 1.8.25]
“By having darśana of You, through remembrance
of You…” Then—bhava-darśanam,
“you don’t have to see, experience this world
of suffering any more.” So, it would be
then, “If adverse circumstances compel me
to enter that level, that depth of focus,
concentration, remembrance, then adversity
would be good for me.” Now we know, no one
is inviting adversity other than Queen Kunti.
But she has achieved that level.
That’s her level of interpretation.
So, again in the Gītā:
bhoktāraṁ yajña-tapasāṁ
sarva-loka-maheśvaram
[Bhagavad-gītā 5.29]
[Krishna is saying,] bhoktāraṁ—everything
is meant for his enjoyment. Yajña-tapasāṁ,
all yajñas, tapasya. He is what? It’s said,
yajño vai viṣṇuḥ from the Vedas, and
Yajñeśvar. That’s why Brahmā was vimohan,
bewildered to see… He’s thinking, “Normally
the Lord is worshipped with yajña. There’s
a big sacrifice and then there’s the offering.
He eats only what is offered through yajña.
And here I am to believe that this five-year-old
boy sitting on the banks of the Yamunā with
His cowherd boyfriends and His calves, and
they’re frolicking about, and they’re
having a picnic—He can do that too? The One,
who, we’re told, only eats through yajña?”
And he learned about the aprākṛta-līlā
of Krishna, the human-like pastimes of the
central conception of the Infinite.
But: bhoktāraṁ yajña-tapasāṁ
sarva-loka-maheśvaram
[Bhagavad-gītā 5.29]
“He’s controlling everything.”
There’s that saying, “Not a blade of grass
moves without the will of God.” Guru Mahārāja
would extend it to dust. So, whatever you
conceive of the finest thing, not moving without
a will of God—the electron, the neutron,
the proton, the quark. Then one would have
to question, “If on that level the movement
is attributed to divinity, then what to speak
of things that are seemingly more significant
then that?— In the background: the divine, divinity”.
So, then we’ll have to think,
“Is this meant to take me down? It’s meant
to make me fail or pass to the next level?
Is He inimical to me or friendly to me? Who’s
controlling all circumstances is my enemy
or my friend?” [Who] has my self-interest
at heart, and not only myself—the whole
animation, in the words of Guru Mahārāja.
And throw in the inanimate as well.
Next line:
bhoktāraṁ yajña-tapasāṁ
sarva-loka-maheśvaram
suhṛdaṁ sarva-bhūtānāṁ
[Bhagavad-gītā 5.29]
Because what was said in the first two lines
might give one pause. “Supreme enjoyer controlling
everything.”—What about us? What about you—suhṛdaṁ
sarva-bhūtānāṁ, “and He’s the dearmost
friend of every living being.” So, like
in this world,
it’s not what you know, but who you know.
If the person you know—and
not just know, but is your dearmost friend—
is controlling everything, then it cannot be
against your self-interest. And this point,
to embrace this, to understand this, to have
faith and the truth of this…
Suhṛdaṁ sarva-bhūtānāṁ—what does Krishna say—jñātvā māṁ śāntim ṛchchhati, “knowing this
if you can know this, and believe this, [and]
embrace this understanding, then
"jñātvāmāṁ śāntim ṛchchhati, “then you’ll
be free from anxiety and peaceful,
knowing that Krishna’s friendly hand is in the background of all events.”
We’re living in a world of mortality. When
events transpire in such a way is to make
that inescapably obvious, we’re upset. Because
we prefer to—what’s the word, when you’re…
I guess ‘oblivious’ is one word—to be
oblivious to our mailing address, which is
the world of mortality. So we want it to be
kept as far away as possible, not to rain
on our little parade of exploitation.
And then the Latin phrase
memento mori—death reminders
which is supposed to be one of
the themes of art.
And by that, we don’t just mean paintings, but may mean literature. When, if it’s to be taken seriously, it
must deal with one of these subjects. Memento mori, death reminders.
We hear that Chekhov is arguably the greatest short-story writer of all time.
And so everyone should read a little Chekhov. [LAUGHING]
What’s the name? It’s called “Ionych” [aɪ’ənɪʧ]?
Okay, “Ionych” [iː’ɔənɪʧ], not
‘ion’ [‘aɪən]. “Ionych” [iː’ɔənɪʧ].
[LAUGHING] I still think he could have chosen
a better title for it, but I’m not Chekhov.
[LAUGHING] But in this story, just to give
an example, I thought, well, if he’s supposed
to be this great writer, and a short story
is supposed to be the hardest kind of story
to write, because they can have no…, nothing
unnecessary can be introduced there. Some,
So, “What is this story about?” And, if it’s
consistent with the themes of great literature,
then memento mori could definitely be one
of the themes. And in a nutshell, a man at
a party in Petersburg is obsessed with a girl
who’s like a musician, dancer, singer that type
She is much younger than [him],
he is enamoured. And she’s not unaware of that
So, before the party ends, she passes
a note to him saying, ‘Meet me in the cemetery
at midnight.’ So, when he goes home he still
has…, his intelligence is still operating
at this point, and he’s thinking, “I’m
not such a fool! This girl is just toying
with me. ‘Meet me in the graveyard, the
cemetery, at midnight.’ I’m not that kind
of foolish man.” But that’s how he was
thinking around 10:30. As the clock started
going more towards midnight, and he started
to think, “What if she actually goes and
I’m not there.” [LAUGHING] Like the praying
mantis she was eating his brain.
We saw a praying mantis today—if someone wonders where that came from. Anyway. So, he’s thinking
if I’m... on the odd chance that she’s serious,
I should go there. And he gets his driver
takes him to the cemetery. And midnight hour,
the bewitching hour comes. But no bewitcher,
she does not show. He is there alone, and
he decides to walk through the cemetery.
And as he’s walking through the cemetery he’s observing the names and dates, birth dates
and death dates, on the gravestones. And it
occurs to him that they were young men, women
like he and that girl. They also had hopes,
aspirations, loves, plans.
As John Lennon said in his song, “Life is
what happens to you while you’re busy making
other plans.” Three months ago people were
busy making other plans, then all their plans
came to an end. Just like everyone, who had
survived, they’re full of plans, hopes,
conventional aspirations. Not unlike anyone
else, not a particular class of people, not
unlike anyone else. And then all of those
plans finished because this is the world of mortality.
And I thought when… about Chekhov. So, he’s arguably the greatest story writer,
and I thought, this underscores how excellent
he is at storytelling. He’s telling you
a story, in essence, setting up something
that doesn’t happen. A lesser writer would
think about what happens. He’s so masterful.
He’s telling you something… What you anticipate
will happen, does not happen. The girl doesn’t
come. You think, “So what kind of a story is that?”
It’s a better story because
of her not showing. That leads him on this
tour of the cemetery, of the graveyard, and
he realizes… As the verse Guru Mahārāja
liked to quote from Gray’s Elegy (Gurudev
liked it so much as well):
The boast of heraldry, the pomp of pow'r,
And all that beauty, all that wealth e'er gave,
Awaits alike th' inevitable hour.
The paths of glory lead but to the grave.
[Thomas Gray, Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard]
So he dealt with that issue, that’s why
it’s considered to be art.
It’s not something we should run away from,
but we should confront.
Shakespeare, “Out, out, brief candle!”
What does that mean? The brief candle is life.
“Out, out, brief candle! Life’s but a
walking shadow…” Subjective evolution,
chaiābhās, chidābhās. “Life’s but
a walking shadow
a poor player / That struts and frets his hour upon the stage / And then is heard no more…”
We all have very limited time here.
Labdhvā su-durlabham idaṁ bahu-sambhavānte
mānuṣyam artha-dam [SB 11.9.29]
life is temporary, but you get an opportunity for liberation.
Not social liberation, national liberation,
economic liberation, women’s
liberation, or any other sort of liberation
in the crematorium, within the jurisdiction
of the crematorium. According to Google, they say
what is it, how many—ten billion people
have lived? We accept what Veda says according
to Bhakti Vinod. Let’s deal with them
because people are familiar with Google than Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur.
But they say, ten billion people. Oh, excuse me, a hundred billion people
have lived, I’m sorry. 100 billion people
have lived known. And what’s the present
population of the Earth—less than ten billion.
So let’s just deal in round numbers—ninety
billion have come and gone. No one is exempt.
“A poor player / Who struts and frets his
hour upon the stage.” Ninety billion players
strutted and fretted their hour upon the stage
and are heard no more. Unless you were infamous,
mainly.
The way to have your name and fame
exists for a long time in history is more
or less to be infamous, to do something really
horrible to the rest of all the other people.
That’ll be remembered.
“It is a tale / Told by an idiot, full of sound and fury, / Signifying nothing.”
[William Shakespeare, Macbeth, Act 5, Scene 5]
We know when… Who is it? Gandharvas, the
dancers and singers on Brahmaloka.
Brahmā has watched, and from a lower planet, someone
came to approach Brahmā for some relief
in their planetary system. And they were told,
“When he finishes, when the dancers and
singers finish, you know, 15 minutes, then
you can meet with Brahmā.” “Oh, OK, let’s
watch the show… Wonderful! Nice singing!
Beautiful singing! Beautiful dancing!”
They finished and Brahmā says, “How may I assist
you?” And the person says,
“Oh, it doesn’t matter now
because the people I wanted you to help,
they all passed away
hundreds of thousands of years ago.”
Why? Because, six months of the heavenly planets,
our six months, is a day there.
Keep extrapolating: Bhūr,
Bhuvar, Mahar, Jana, Tapa, Satya.
By the time you get to Satyaloka, four billion three hundred million (4,320,000,000) years a day.
The average lifespan there is fifteen trillion years.
Brahmā, at the end of three hundred and eleven trillion years, will also die.
ā-brahma-bhuvanāl lokāḥ
punar āvartino ’rjuna
mām upetya tu kaunteya
punar janma na vidyate
[Bhagavad-gītā 8.16]
“Not even the great Brahmā is exempt in
the world of mortality,
in the events in this world.”
Guru Mahārāja in the famous talk…
And I was saying I wanted to dedicate this talk to
Dhananjay Prabhu, Chaitanya Mayi,
Munindra Mohan, and Krishna Kanta DD, Shanti Moyi DD
and all the Italian bhakta-vṛnda—our
god-brothers and god-sisters there.
We’re thinking of them. And I spoke to Munindra
Mohan Prabhu and Krishna Kanta DD,
and I was recalling Guru Mahārāja’s response to
the proposition of World War III—and that’s
in the Search for Śrī Krishna—Reality
the Beautiful. And they mentioned, they had
been reading with other devotees that very
section of the book the evening before.
But the famous lines that, those who are familiar
with it, come away with that’s Guru Mahārāja
saying, “A point on a line, a line in a
plane, a plane in a solid.” And for those
not familiar with this type of thought, he
means, “What is the line but an infinite
number of points.” So, he is saying, “This
point in history, this event in time and space
and history, is a point on a line which is
an infinite number of points.”
And a plane is an infinite number
of lines. So, he’s saying, “From an overview
it’s insignificant.” It doesn’t mean
our hearts aren’t breaking, that people
are not suffering, that we’re not lamenting
the loss of loved ones. But from the overview…
People say, “What is the use of philosophy?
It has no practical value.”
Guru Mahārāja said, “When it comes to dealing with death, you’ll understand the value of philosophy.”
So, from a philosophical point of view, and
not only—if you say, “Oh, but that’s
religion and philosophy,”—no, from a scientific
point of view, there’s a book out
that had to be written well before this pandemic.
Because it was released around a month ago.
So, when you consider how long it takes to
publish a book—the research and writing
was [done] long before that. And it’s about
the end of the world or the end of the universe.
And it’s written by a credible scientist,
who’s saying something that scientists
have known for a long time, but is either relatively
unknown with the people in general
or not attributed much importance because it’s
so long from now, which means
the expiration date of the universe.
So, as we’ve said before.
[Do] you know what power is in mathematics?
Like, when you do 2 squared, 2 to the 3rd power
2 to the [4th, etc.] So, if you take
10 squared is 100, right, then 10 to the 3rd,
4th, [etc.] If you turn that into years, some
scientists will say, “Well, it could be
10 to the 10th power in years or 10 to the
12th, some may be to the 14th.” But they
might disagree on which power it will be,
but they’re all in the consensus that it
has an expiration date. So, all of what we
know now, all of human history, all human geography
everything we know—it will vanish.
That’s not a religious idea, a religious notion,
it’s a scientifically accepted one.
All of this will vanish. Then what will our
lives have been, is human life just meant
for conventional aspirations? And by that,
I mean an allusion to biological imperative,
meaning: reproduction.
Āhāra-nidrā-bhaya-maithunaṁ cha [Hitopadeśa 25], eating, sleeping, reproduction and defence, shelter
creating a situation where you can
become free from fear and anxiety.
We’re told, that we hold in common with animals.
What separates us—
dharmeṇa hīnāḥ paśubhiḥ samānāḥ—is this…
The word used here is dharma, but really what
it’s alluding to, is this inner purpose, inner necessity. We are the only species
who ask ‘why?’, who contemplates purpose,
fulfilment, value. Means, beyond base necessities.
We value the concepts in a book. A moth just
sees food. A dog doesn’t understand the
value of gold. There are many examples like
that. So, we’re talking about something
that is subjective. And remember, just because
something is subjective, does not mean that
it’s not true. Because it can’t be proven
by conventional means. You can’t prove that
something is funny. You can’t prove that
someone is beautiful.
That doesn’t mean that there is no such thing as humour, or beauty,
or other subjective things. And just
because one person
does not perceive that,
does not deny the possibility of its existence
to another. So, we’re talking, really, about
what is subjective in terms of value.
So, Guru Mahārāja says in that section,
“Learn to live in the plane of your faith.”
Śraddhā mayo ’yaṁ loka, that, which
does not vanish, when this world vanishes.
That’s our bet. That’s the theistic bet.
That’s the fight, the noble fight.
It’s not cowardice. As Guru Mahārāja said, “Come
and face the real fight!” What is it [about]?
About mortality—we’re in the mortal world.
But how is it framed by humanists? Even the
great atheist Christopher Hitchens, who died
from cancer a few years ago, he said, “Whenever
someone gets a terminal illness that’s always
framed in terms of a battle.
You know, they’ll say, ‘He’s a fighter, he’s gonna
fight this thing! He’s not going down without a fight!’”
And as I may have mentioned
before, there’s a place called Ladbrokes.
For those who don’t know it’s either in
England, Ireland, or both. And they take bets
on anything. You can bet on anything there,
not just a horse race or sports. You can place
a bet with them on just about anything. Probably
unlike when the universe will end. But if
they would take a bet on this cancer battle,
I’m betting with cancer. So, then Hitchens
concluded by saying, “And when the person
finally passes, it’s as if to say that he
finally succumbed and died after a long struggle
with mortality.” Mortality.
Oh, and interestingly in the Bhāgavatam—it
may seem harsh, or cruel, or too much, but—after
Śukadev Goswāmī has spoken the bulk of
the Bhāgavatam to Parikṣit Mahārāja,
and he is giving his final advice to him—and
this means, he’s described Krishna-līlā,
all the avatars, the dynasty, everything leading
up to Krishna and His madhura-rasa pastimes
with Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī and vrajagopīs—but
he turns them and says:
tvaṁ tu rājan mariṣyeti
paśu-buddhim imāṁ jahi
[Śrīmad Bhāgavatam 12.5.2]
I was shocked when I heard this. He says,
“Don’t believe it. To believe that you
will die that’s paśu-buddhi, that’s animal
intelligence.” So, this is Eastern philosophy,
Indian theism, Vedic understanding 101 [101
means ‘basics’ or ‘ABC’, —Ed.] that
you’re not the material body. Śrīla Prabhupād
spent 10 years hammering ātmā-jñāna of
the second chapter of Bhagavad-gītā. After
all of these instructions, Śukadev turns
to Parikṣit Mahārāja and says, “Don’t
be afraid to die. That’s animal consciousness.”
And we say, “Well that’s very easy to
say.” It is. It’s easy to say—to realize
is another thing. My responsibility is to
be a medium for what is said there. I don’t
mean to imply that I have no such fear. But
in the pages of the Bhāgavatam, it’s considered,
it’s called paśu-buddhi that fear. Remember:
janma-mṛtyu-jarā-vyādhi-duḥkha-doṣānudarśanam
[BG 13.9]. Krishna says, “You want to understand
the world? This is what it is. It’s a place
of suffering. What are the basic types of
suffering? Janma, birth, death, old age, disease.”
This happened a hundred years ago in 1918.
Somehow we think it won’t happen again or
it won’t happen to us. We won’t be in
those numbers, in the statistics.
When Yudhiṣṭhir Mahārāja is having his
conversation with Yamarāj… And I thought,
as a side point, that if you were talking
to the lord of death, you’d really want
to ask him things. But what surprising is,
he is asking Yudhiṣṭhir Mahārāja questions.
Because as much as we’re interested to know
about the world of death, we can understand
thematically, he’s interested to understand
about the world of the living. And says to
him, “What’s the most astonishing thing
about the world of the living?” And what
is Yudhiṣṭhir Mahārāja saying?
ahany ahani bhūtāni
gacchantīha yamālayam
śeṣāḥ sthāvaram icchanti
kim āścaryam ataḥ paraṁ
[Mahābhārata, Vana-parva 313.116]
Āścaryam means ‘incredible, astonishing.’
“I can’t think of anything that is more
astonishing than this,” that according to
Google 90 billion people have died. And that
are just human beings and all the other living
beings around them. We’re discovering fossils
every day. So, how much death there’s been
up to this point—of human beings and other
species, and everything imaginable or unimaginable?
And we know statistically, scientifically,
it’s not some wacky rigid religious idea
that we all must die. We’ll say, “No,
the Google guys say that they’re going to
download all the knowledge in robots, and
then the machine-learning will figure out
how we can scan copies of ourselves and then
make a backup, and download yourself into
a robot made out of diamonds, and then you
can live forever.” [LAUGHING]
Everyone has to… That’s why Guru Mahārāja
says, “Don’t be a coward and run away
from this. Is that, you have to deal with
mortality. It’s inescapable for everything
here because, even if you become one of those
diamond robots who can so-called ‘live forever,’
you’re going to be finished too at the end
of the trillion-trillion years or whatever
it is.” We put three hundred eleven trillion
on it with Brahmā. Even if you’re going
to be with Mārkaṇḍeya Ṛṣi floating
on a banyan leaf, which I don’t see any
description of that in the Bhāgavatam, there’s
not room for two on the banyan leaf. Sooner
or later you have to deal with this inevitable
problem.
So, that’s where Yudhiṣṭhir says: “Although
everyone before us has died, around us everyone
is dying.” Like now, so many people are
dying. It’s unavoidable. You cannot hide
your head in the sand about this. It’s everywhere.
A few months ago they said that, while this
was part of the news in the West, in China
they said, “It’s not just big news—it’s
the only news.” If you look at the current
news it’s the only news, and the economic
effects of this event—that’s the news.
This is the news. The news is at any moment
any one of us may have to go, may have to
withdraw from this plane. Then what is the
purpose of life?
We’re thinking what he says what is most
astonishing, “Still somehow, hope against
hope, we’re holding out it won’t be me.
I won’t be in those numbers. I won’t be
in those statistics. Somehow I’ll make it
through.” Then for what purpose? To cherish
conventional aspirations to the biological
imperative to reproduce? We’re not pandas.
You could understand why that could be a big
program for them. If we’re something more
than pandas then what is that purpose?
When we were leaving London with Śrīla Gurudev,
and he said, as his servitors were preparing
the luggage for the flight, and Gurudev turn
to me and said, “Mahārāja, you cannot
imagine how happy I was in my village life.”
And I thought that’s really unusual. Usually,
people who were in connection with Krishna
consciousness will tell you how miserable
they’d become and that led them to take
shelter of the Krishna consciousness movement.
But Śrīla Govinda Mahārāja was saying,
“Oh, [in my village] I was so happy. I loved
everyone, everyone loved me—all the people,
the birds, the animals, the trees, even the
rickshavalas.” [LAUGHING] With some sort
of gradation there. I don’t know if that’s
in the Padma-purāṇa or not. And he said,
“And then Guru Mahārāja’s representatives
came from Śrī Chaitanya Sāraswat Maṭh
preaching in his village, and the lead preacher
told them, ‘Your father will die, your mother
will die, this whole world will vanish. Then
what will you do? Your father is nothing,
your mother is nothing, this world is nothing—it
will all vanish. Then what?’” And Gurudev
introduced it by saying, “He came talking
this nonsense—mother is nothing, father
is nothing, world there’s nothing, it will
all vanish. But it struck a sympathetic chord
in my heart and I could not deny its truth,
the validity.”
Still, the one other thing I wanted to say
was, when we were told that during this period
the safest thing to do is self-isolation,
to go into isolation.
And for some, that’s very difficult to do, for some less, but it’s the advice
‘to stop all the social interaction.’
And as a side point, it’s interesting to
note that, due to the temporary suspension
of economic development and everything that
goes with it, blue skies have returned, clear
water in Venice due to no tourists or no manufacturing.
And before we go back to business as usual,
maybe some adjustments should be made. Look
at that blue sky and think about it if there’s
some adjustment you can make. Look at that
clear water. That’s a side point, but dealing
with the principle of isolation.
I was telling Krishna Kanta DD and Munindra
that one time when I was living in Europe,
there was some discrepancy with my international
driver’s licence, and I was going from Austria
to Germany, and—you know that German precision
[and] proficiency—they noted that. And somehow—I’m
giving the condensed version—I was incarcerated,
which for those who don’t know what’s
‘incarcerate,’ I was thrown in jail in
solitary confinement immediately. And I was
presented to a judge, and through a German
interpreter, the lady told me with a smile
on her face, “This matter should be resolved
in three weeks. Entschuldigen Sie bitte.”
I went to my cell wearing these woolen pants
and the woolen coat. I asked if I could have
two things—my japa-mālā and a volume [of]
Śrī Chaitanya-charitāmṛta, and they consented
to that. So, I was in the cell chanting and
thinking, “I need to keep my composure.”
If I allow this confinement to… If I lose
my composure in confinement, I’m going to
lose my mind, and be tormented mentally, psychically.
So I started having a dialogue with myself.
And it ran something like this—I was saying,
“Your whole life you spend in a room this
size, so now you’re in a room this size,
you’re always in a room this size, so don’t
be disturbed by that, it’s just a different
location, but you spend your whole life in
a room this size.” But then the other part
of the dialogue said, “But there’s a difference.”
At that time I was living in Vienna [and]
it’s true, this room and the room in Vienna
are a similar size. “The difference is,
you decide to be in that room in Vienna and
you did not make the choice to be in this
room.” So the difference between these two
rooms is freedom. It’s not the room that’s
the difficulty. Your freedom has been taken
from you. You don’t have a choice. The room
in Vienna—you can decide not to be in there,
to go for a walk, or do whatever is necessary.
In this room, you cannot decide not to be here.
You can only be here. And then I thought,
“This is a problem.” I thought, “Yeah,
that’s my freedom.” It’s the freedom.
It’s not the size of the room, it’s that
I’ve lost my freedom, my choice.
We’re told, it’s so innate to the existence
of the jīva, you cannot remove the free will.
Because in Jaiva-dharma at one point it’s
brought up that, “Well, if it’s by misuse
of the free will of the jīva that brings
them into the suffering condition—
take away the free will, make it so that they can only
be happy-happy-happy all the time…time…time…”
And Bhakti Vinod’s answered, he said, “No,
understand, it’s so innate; if you remove
free will from the jīva, jīva doesn’t
exist anymore.”
And somehow I see a connection between this and the poet [W.H.] Auden. You know who is, right?
Auden. He wrote a famous thing that was called "1947" [The Age of Anxiety: A Baroque Eclogue]…
Anyway, he has a line that… And I’m not saying Auden would agree with me,
but I’d told you chyron at the bottom of the screen saying,
“I reserve the right to appropriate anything I’ve ever heard anyone say to promote Krishna conception.”
The chyron at the bottom of the screen says…
So he said, “We are composed of Eros and dust.”
And then I thought, “Yes, but it’s
not the dust… Let go of the dust part—that’s
the part that can finish. The Eros part is
permanent. It will live on. There must be
a domain where that aspect can be expressed—that’s
only dealt with in Krishna conception.”
muktir hitvānyathā rūpaṁ
sva-rūpeṇa vyavasthitiḥ
[Śrīmad Bhāgavatam 2.10.6]
Shed… the shackle of the dust aspect. The
Eros part is permanent and has a plane of
expression in the domain of divine love of
Krishna. So, what did I say before?
Oh, back in the jail cell. So, then I thought… And
I had heard one devotee within the last year,
for something that, say, in the US would have been
considered a minor infraction, was serving
two years' internment. So I thought, “This
could be something like that. I need to take
this very seriously and I need to prepare
myself to be confined indefinitely.
That’s the only way I’ll be able to… If I’m
thinking this is going to end tomorrow, or
a week from now, that won’t be good for
[me] because if not then I’m going to be
devastated psycho-emotionally.” So I thought,
“I need to prepare myself that it could
be indefinite confinement and when I’m okay
with that then I can proceed. It should be
nothing less than that.” Then I thought,
“How to get to that point? Now I understand
what I need to do. How will I get there?”
So, I chanted as much as I could and then
I remembered, “Oh, I have my Chaitanya-charitāmṛta,”
and it turns out it was Sanātan-śikṣā,
Mahāprabhu’s instructions to Sanātan Goswāmī,
which you may remember begins with Sanātan
Goswāmī in jail, and while he’s in jail
he gets a letter from Rūpa Goswāmī.
So I’m reading this with great eagerness and
anticipation. I’ve read it before but now
it’s showing some new light to me because
of its relevance. That’s the point.
Āchinoti yaḥ śāstrārtham [Vāyu-purāṇa].
There’s so much in the scripture what is
relevant to us in our present situation and
circumstance—that we need to know. So, there
is the letter of Rūpa Goswāmī to Sanātan
Goswāmī where he’s quoting a śloka and
it says:
yadu-pateḥ kva gatā mathurā-purī
raghu-pateḥ kva gatottara-kośalā
iti vichintya kuruṣva manaḥ sthiraṁ
na sad idaṁ jagad ity avadhāraya
[Śrī Chaitanya-charitāmṛta, Madhya 20.3,
Purport]
It’s so beautiful. The only person I ever
heard quote it was Śrīla Gurudev. Once.
At the time I had not committed it to memory.
Then I thought, “Oh, he knows that,”
and he used it so beautifully. But what he’s
saying here and this is when the calm...—
"manaḥ sthiraṁ" means ‘mental composure,’ more
than mental. And it’s so perfect in context
and meaningful to devotees, aspiring devotees
as well. Yadu-pateḥ kva gatā mathurā-purī,
saying, “Where’s the Mathurā Purī of
Yadu-pati (that means Krishna)? There was
a time when Krishna world was here.” We
always read about Vrindāvan, and we say,
“5000 years ago.” And he said, “Where
has it gone?” Raghu-pateḥ kva gatottara-kośalā,
and the Raghu-vaṁśha, the dynasty of Rāmachandra and his kingdom—
long gone to the point considered by mode of mythology.
Vanished, withdrawn from this
plane. So he’s saying, “If the Krishna world
withdrew from this plane, the Raghu,
Rāmachandra's, withdrew from this plane, then
iti vichintya kuruṣva manaḥ sthiraṁ,
then make your mind steady by realizing—what?—
Na sad idaṁ.” Na sad means ‘it’s not
real, this world—it’s not real, it’s not permanent,
it’s temporary.’ Na sad
idaṁ jagad ity avadhāraya,
it’s only here from some time and then it vanishes.
As that scientist says in his book.
But don’t let the… They’ll say, “Oh,
but that’s going to happen a trillion years
from now.” That’s what Yudhiṣṭhir
Mahārāja is telling Yamarāj saying,
“That kind of thinking—that’s what’s astonishing,
when you know better:
everyone before you died, everyone around us is dying,
and now it’s been pushed in our face, and still
we think it won’t be us.” Kim āśchāryam
ataḥ param [Mahābhārata, Vana-parva 313.116],
what could be more astonishing than this.
But, if we appreciate the letter of Rūpa
Goswāmī then we understand that this is
the time when philosophy shows its value.
Deep thinking. Dive deep into Reality, beyond
the superficial aspects of temporal existence.
Hare Krishna. And as Guru Mahārāja says,
“Live in the world of our faith.”
I was discussing this with
Śrīla Madhusūdan Mahārāja earlier.
Our happiness lies in glorifying
Hari-guru and Vaiṣṇava.
When recently was the Appearance Day of Śrīvās
Ṭhākur… And when they were in the kīrtan
at śrīvās-aṅgaṁ—and that’s where
Mahāprabhu sang hari haraye namaḥ kṛṣṇa,
the beginning of that—during one kīrtan
one of his sons died. He came out of the room
saying what’s wrong. And [his] wife and
others said [that] his son died, they’re all
crying, lamenting, and he is saying, “That
may be, but don’t disturb Mahāprabhu.
Mahāprabhu is now in some deep ecstatic emotion.
We don’t want to disturb those divine emotions of His.”
And you can think, “Oh, how callous is Śrīvās!”
No, he’s loving…, but this is the depth
of his devotion that: that is real and this
is temporal. But then afterwards,
when it comes to Mahāprabhu’s attention,
and he’s saying, “Śrīvās, why didn’t you tell me?”
[Śrīvās] is saying, “I didn’t want to disturb You.”
And then Mahāprabhu is saying, like
“Can I ever leave such
a devotee as this? He’s totally purchased Me
with this type of love and affection.”
And because these are divine pastimes,
it’s like they say at the end of the movie:
‘no animals were actually harmed in the making
of this motion picture.’ So, no one actually
dies in these divine pastimes. No souls were
actually extinguished. Read the Bhagavad-gītā
Chapter 2: na jāyate mriyate vā kadāchin, etc.
But that child, who was actually, perhaps,
the child of Chitraketu in the Bhāgavatam.
So the child is revived by Mahāprabhu, and
he starts giving a philosophical talk to everyone
telling them that this world… This is a
child speaking now, who just died, left the world,
then he comes back and says, “This
world is temporary. Don’t put your faith
here and try to live permanently in this plane.
By the will of the Lord, I came here for some time
by His will I’m leaving here now going
on to another situation. Don’t lament for me.”
Bhakti Vichār Jājāvar Mahārāja was the
last person to take sannyās from
Śrīla Bhakti Siddhānta Saraswatī Ṭhākur, but being a simple-hearted pure devotee
and humble in every way. And we had the good fortune
to meet His divine grace and be bathed in
his Vaiṣṇava vision. He thought, “What
if I can’t keep up,” when the sannyāsi
is offered by Saraswatī Ṭhākur—“What if I can’t maintain my vows, I can’t keep the position.”
He was fearful, afraid.
Guru Mahārāja, when he heard…
And some devotees were saying,
“Yes, Prabhu, what you are thinking that
is the correct thing. Tell Prabhupād you’re
not qualified.” When Guru Mahārāja heard
this, he approached Śrīla Saraswatī Ṭhākur
and explained the situation about the hesitation.
I think his name was Sarvānanda—
something along those lines— Brahmachārī.
Saraswatī Ṭhākur called him to his side, and he said,
“When you take sannyāsi you are approaching the abhaya-pāda.” That means ‘the fearless world.’
Like, bhajahu̐ re mana śrī-nanda-nandana /
abhaya-charaṇāravinda re.
Kamala-dala-jala, jīvana ṭalamala—
we see this all the time,
because we have lotus flowers here.
When I first heard this song many years ago, I thought
it was saying, ‘water on the lotus petals.’
That’s not what it’s saying. Because there’s
the lotus flower—that’s another story.
So many things are said about the lotus.
This is talking about the leaf, the green leaf
beneath the lotus flower. And you’ll see
a bead of water pooling on there. And they
look like mirrors, actually, if you look at
them closely. But you can watch it and then
without any indication it just suddenly rolls
off the leaf. It’s not like you go,
“Oh, it’s gonna happen,” no, it just does it,
and that’s what he’s saying. Kamala-dala-jala,
jīvana ṭalamala, ‘this life is like that
water on the leaf of the lotus flower—
it can finish at any moment.’ So, Saraswatī
Ṭhākur told Jājāvar Mahārāja,
“This is the world you should be afraid of, not
the spiritual world, going that direction—
don’t be fearful of that.” This world, [in] which
there’s danger in every step—the ādhyātmic,
ādhidaivic and ādhibhautic miseries, as
this present situation reminds us—
it is inescapable. So, if anything, if this can
be used as a catalyst or, what’s the word
for like ‘compel’ but it’s another word…
‘push’… I can’t think of… in terms
of giving a push… Nityānanda Dās:—‘Accelerate.’
Goswāmī Mahārāja:—That’s a word.
There is another word I’m looking for. Prachoditāḥ.
Prachodayati… Yes, all of these things.
Can’t find a precise word but to nudge us,
to push us in the direction of internal culture.
Self-reflection, self-analysis—it’s a
good time to reflect upon our lives—
up to this point at present and how we shall proceed.
But it’s what is before us right now
that is most important.
As Guru Mahārāja liked to quote that poetry,
Trust no Future howe’er pleasant!
Let the dead Past bury its dead!
Act,—act, in the living Present!
Heart within, and God o’erhead!
[The snippet from Henry Wadsworth Longfellow’s
“A Psalm of Life”
quoted in “Loving search for
the lost servant” Śrīla Guru Mahārāja, p.3]
Compel, compulsion to dive deep into Reality.
Hare Krishna.