Roopa goes salami is warning about this
kinda stuffuu
so those are sentimental by nature and
the other group
acting stanislavsky method getting in
the character
so don't mistake it for something like
that I
we're going to read and pretense its
again
its although it appears to be it's not
it's not a mental exercise
it's not an intellectual exercise
it has to be a faith-based transaction
whether you're an intellectual or simple
hearted percent
3 a faith-based transaction so the Honda
tones from the other two funny ad-hoc
then something substantial can come to
one
not by force
not by sentiment
not by a imitation
but through service say bon located
sabado
shy on the other sports and arts I'll
means here
through service he may
consent to reveal Himself Association
art Mart we've been newt a
tender love yes line
condoms farm he may decide he may not
as I told before and what you
EXR this were not the same you taking
Kristen tom is not revealing himself why
he could
but he knows you're capable better night
so it has to be real still
notched up a celebration it come by the
lead to say lyle by the let you to miss
looking about the above it in a sticky
at a certain point
but he got the tipping point
the mend me right close to 100 percent
tipping point reaches so much have a
majority
tipping point but that's up to Krishna
what that said I will say
its my firm believe that
everyone who's ever substantially been
in connection with Krishna consciousness
has some on
level love revelation something's been
revealed to them
and not only once repeatedly
and we know that not in the sense of
self assertion
protest are arrogance but out of
gratitude to our groove Argo
we cannot deny that's something
as then give to do %uh something has
touched us
and that's like
a and the philosophical basis for this
is cover us both Tommy
self-deprecation but extreme
glorification
out the give the groove are God's II
might highway then we say bobbi Starr
we see Ricky Doyle they we say like the
star I'm lower than the worm in the
school store
a more simple than that I am i die.
a
and if you hear my name
you lose all your good qualities
if you check out by name you'll fall
down but
what I'm telling here what's passing
through me here on the former Chaitanya
chart on read some
there's nothing higher than us that he
says with
he after the a
confession all self a.m.
deprecation says with absolute certainty
assuredness there's nothing higher than
this
so thats the base to suffer a realistic
position for the vote e2
progress in Krishna consciousness the
right amount of self-deprecation
and acquired appreciation gifted by the
good
Varga for genuine spiritual substance
that's a viable progressive spiritual
life
and they can have some hope
some prospects when growers says dive
deep in the reality that it's possible
not a imploring us to do something
that's not possible
but I think but to do that if to be
serious
roots on this day I had diarrhea that
dot com above are denoted cetera
serious determined faithful
patient and as much as Krishna
once the reciprocate
your hearts enter true earnest anchoring
I'll be reciprocated and more
growers that whatever little faith we
have
casted toward the end that internet he
said and then prepare yourself
for what will come and return in
response to that
when Mahaprabhu serve the Passat on hit
his so generous it gives enough for four
prepare for that
he only knows that and
reciprocate infinitely a drop of the
Infineon Infineon
so when we have any by the grace have
grown by snov
sought to Shasta some touch with Krishna
consciousness
we feel ourselves very fortunate as
ballin as we are