That which is auspicious, you should
do immediately without hesitation,
and that which is inauspicious,
you should delay, delay, wait, wait and see.
He who acts hurriedly
will have to repent, this kind of thing.
[Rāvaṇ’s Good Advice]
When he told us this advice,
we were surprised—
who’s the source of this?
It’s great wisdom, everyone
will benefit from hearing it:
that which is auspicious,
do immediately without hesitation;
that which is inauspicious, delay it,
put it off, don’t rush into that.
‘Fools rush in where angels
fear to tread’—this whole idea.
So Guru Mahārāj said,
“Where does this come from? It’s from Rāvaṇa,
the demon,
the ten-headed demon, Rāvaṇa.”
How does it happen?
After all these pastimes take place,
and he’s lying and dying
on the battlefield.
Guru Mahārāj said,
Rāmachandra told Lakṣmaṇ,
“You go and get some advice from him;
he has some valuable knowledge
about the world, about life,
about experience. Go and approach him.”
And he said at first Lakṣmaṇ goes
to where his head is
because he’s lying on the battlefield
dying, and Rāma says,
“No, no, no.
If you’re to take instruction,
then you should sit at the feet.”
That’s the proper way to approach;
sit at the lotus feet of the instructor.
So, he’s sitting at the feet of Rāvaṇa
and inquiring from him,
“What have you learned in life?
What valuable wisdom
can you impart to me?”
And that’s when Rāvaṇa says,
śubhasya śīghram aśubhasya kāla-haraṇam
“Everyone told me,
‘Don’t go against Rāmachandra’.
Everyone told me,
‘Do not kidnap his wife, Sītā Devī’.
‘This is a bad idea.’
Every last person.
I ran it by different people,
nobody signed on to this.
They all said, ‘Bad idea, don’t do it,
please don’t do this,
it’s going to be the end of you,
it’s going to be your ruination.’”
He said,
“But I didn’t listen to them.
I had these other good programs.”
Like, he had The Stairway to Heaven,
The Mango Program—
mangoes come from Sri Lanka …
Different kinds … The city was very nice.
He said, “But those I stopped,
I stopped developing them.
But this bad program,
fight with Rāmachandra, steal his wife,
I just rushed into it, full blown,
with passion, didn’t listen to anybody,
against all good advice.”
And he said, “Look at me now.”
So, that which is auspicious,
do it immediately;
that which is inauspicious,
delay, delay, wait, don’t do that.