You need a little bit
of mercy to understand this.
It’s not an academic thing.
It’s not the transfer of data.
[Heart Transmission | Feeling Is Above Knowledge]
We are not data mining.
This isn’t,
“Oh, some knowledge, and then what?
—You transfer this information here—
Oh, now I know it, and
you know it, we discussed it.”
That’s not like that.
tene brahma hṛdā [SB: 1.1.1]
It’s a heart to heart,
it’s a heart transmission.
Not to transfer of data packets,
or information,
but of feeling, ānandam,
Ānanda Sundar.
Feeling, to transfer of the feeling.
This feeling is above knowledge.
He said, but
as Guru Mahārāj  told
when he was twenty three,
he had one teacher,
who was around eighty,
and he had, like
‘six black belts’.
I mean, anthological ‘black belts’.
Like, in the ṣaṭ‒darśane of
in all the different philosophies.
He is very learned, educated.
And so, Guru Mahārāj , at one point,
thinks very simple‒hearted, pure‒hearted—
the saral brahman.
He [Guru Mahārāj] said,
“Why don’t you use your
vast learning, and intellect,
in discovery of the glories
of Mahāprabhu?
And that man said,
“Oh, my boy,
it is not a question of learning.
But you’ve got to have
some mercy.”
That man knew it also.
“You’ve got to have some mercy.”
It’s not just a question of knowing.
We say,
jñāna‒śūnyā bhakti
is faint ignorance,
is not real ignorance.
It’s faint.
Means there …
pretending under the influence
of Yoga-māyā not to know.
Those who know the most are pretending
they not to know certain things.
And not pretending,
it’s heart felt.