Guru Mahārāj
will say,
“Bhāgavatam takes it
to another level,
whereas, in Bhagavad-gītā
you’re being told
don’t quarrel with the environment,
be tolerant.”
The Śrīmad Bhāgavatam
is saying,
[Krishna Consciousness | Not By Force]
tat te ’nukampāṁ su-samīkṣamāṇo
bhuñjāna evātma-kṛtaṁ vipākam
[SB: 10.14.8]
that su-samīkṣa—
if you scrutinize this,
if you look deeply beneath the surface
of karmic circumstance,
and as we said—
acquired prejudice and tendencies—
saṃskāra: one’s impressions lifetime
after lifetime, after lifetime …
Acquired mental impressions,
layering, covering the self.
If you look very deep
in your circumstances you’ll see,
not only is toleration prescribed,
good prescription … but,
in the background—
suhṛdaṁ sarva-bhūtānāṁ
[Bg: 5.29]
the friendly hand of
Kṛṣṇa is there.
Who owns and
controls everything
is not trying to crush you,
but, is your friend.
And wanting to bring you
out of karmic circumstance.
So, what I mean to say here really,
to address the initial question,
is that, that’s between God
and that individual.
We’re not to impose
our conceptions upon others.
If somebody sincerely inquires—
you try to answer as the best you can,
but to try and change somebody
against their will,
to try and impose, or enforce
some way of seeing on someone
that is against … without their consent,
that they’re resistant to,
that won’t be successful
and it also begs the position
of the person
who’s the enforcer.
But, in the case of,
you could say, devotees
or say some devotee wife—
she is concerned about her husband.
Then the best thing
is like we do for any new person
is just give them exposure
to Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
Same thing parents do
with their children,
you give them exposure
to Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
How far they will embrace
that is an individual thing.
As we mention again
in the Gītā,
manuṣyāṇāṁ sahasreṣu
kaścid yatati siddhaye
yatatām api siddhānāṁ
kaścin māṁ vetti tattvataḥ
[Bg: 7.3]
Kṛṣṇa Himself is saying
in the Gītā again,
and He should know—
He is situated in everyone’s heart.
He can do His own
demographic study,
statistical analysis
at any given point and time.
He is saying,
“It’s very rare for someone
to seriously express interest
in spiritual culture,
theistic culture, substantially.
That’s rare.
Out of thousands—one.”
And then what does He say?
—And out of those
who may become siddha
in the general
sense of the term—
perfect, spiritually realized.
He says,
kaścin māṁ vetti tattvataḥ
[Bg: 7.3]
—Hardly one knows Me.
Elsewhere,
in the Bhāgavatam we hear,
muktānām api siddhānāṁ
nārāyaṇa-parāyaṇaḥ
su-durlabhaḥ praśāntātmā
koṭiṣv api mahā-mune
[SB: 6.14.5]
—Out of ten million
liberated souls,
one might be
a devotee of Kṛṣṇa.
And once Guru Mahārāj said,
“Even that is too many.”
[Laughing]
So what do we hear?
koṭi-karma-niṣṭha-madhye eka ‘jñānī’ śreṣṭha
[Cc: 2.19.147]
Out of ten million karmis … one jñānī
is better than ten million karmīs
And then …
koṭi-mukta-madhye
‘durlabha’ eka kṛṣṇa-bhakta
[Cc: 2.19.148]
And out of millions
of liberated souls,
one may be a devotee
of Kṛṣṇa.
So it’s rare and generally
the outcome of accumulated sukriti,
from ajñāta-sukṛti
to jñāta-sukṛti, śraddhā,
sādhu-saṅga.
So, Guru Mahārāj
is telling us underground,
ajñāta-sukṛti,
which we define as
some unknowing contact
with nirguṇa agents.
So, if someone’s of a couple,
if one person is engaged
in the culture of
Kṛṣṇa consciousness,
then by dent
of connection with them,
the other person
is going to get
a certain amount
of exposure.
And if they remain together
in a mutually, how we say,
respectful relationship
of one another,
that person will accumulate
sukṛti, and in time it will …
the accumulative effect
of that sukṛti
will be expressed as śrāddha—
faith, which will lead them
to take the association
of devotees seriously.
But as Gurudev
would say in a phrase,
you want to make it
very simple, “Not to force.”
Not to force with children,
not to force with life partners.