We are all familiar
with the expression
‘No risk, no gain.’
If you’re going to gain something,
you have to take some risk.
[All Gain, No Risk]
At the time I was very sort of pleased
with myself about that.
And I thought, “Yeah,
I’ve risked everything to be with you,
to come in connection with your holy lotus feet,
and now I’ve gained everything.”
So, I was very proud
and happy, like,
“Yes, I know that very well—
‘no risk, no gain’,
and I myself am
such a sterling example of that.”
And then Guru Mahārāj knew,
he had me
like primed for what
he was about to say,
because I was sitting like that
[self-mocking]
And he said,
“But there is a higher stage,”
“There is? What?”
He said,
“All risk and no gain.”
And I had to think
for minute like,
“Did I just hear what he said?
‘All risk and no gain.’”
And he could see
a bewildered look on my face.
He said,
“Are you ready for that?
You’ll risk everything
and gain nothing.”
And then I thought …
I was trying to think of it all, but …
and I am unable
to process this entirely.
And then now I’m totally bewildered,
and Guru Mahārāj is smiling.
[Laughing]
And he said,
“That is the position of the Vraja-gopīs.
They risk everything
with no anticipation of gaining.
That’s the highest standard.
They’re not calculating self-interest,
they’re not calculating
what they will get from doing this.
bhajanīya-sarva-sad-guṇa viśiṣṭa
[Bs]
They’re irresistibly drawn to Kṛṣṇa
to offer themselves.”
Just like in the parallel,
a mundane parallel in this world,
when someone in romantic love
and they become enamoured
by another person
without thinking
about all these things—
automatically they’re giving themselves
to that person.
Even more so when one
in the consume someone or something,
we’re actually searching for someone
to offer ourselves to,
to give ourselves to.
But because we’ve been deceived
so many times,
and we have a strong tendency
ourselves toward self‒deception,
we’re reluctant.
So we are keeping the heart
sheltered, cloistered, covered,
and afraid to give ourselves,
to offer ourselves.
So, anyway, Śrīla Guru Mahārāj said,
“All risk and no gain.
Are you ready for that?”
And now I was just
totally bewildered.
I don’t know
what I’m agreeing to.
And then he began to explain.
He said,
“All risk and no gain because
you think that
this world is something substantial.
And you think that spiritual life
and spiritual reality is insubstantial.”
It’s just something abstract
people are talking about it.
Can you prove it?
This, that sort of thing.
We are very suspicious
of the spiritual reality.
But this world … because
you can knock on it,
you can walk on it,
you can manipulate it
in various ways,
we think, “This is the solid
substantial plane.”
Although even according to the science
it’s constantly in motion,
and also according to the science
there will come a time when all of this vanishes.
And enter some kind
of nebulous state.
And according to Veda
it’ll again express itself.
bhūtvā bhūtvā pralīyate
[Bg: 8.19]
It manifests for sometime,
it’s all disintegrated and withdrawn,
and then manifests again.
So, even though we know that
that’s really the nature of this world,
and everything we see here
has only appeared for a brief time,
and will vanish in time,
we’re still thinking,
“This is the solid world
with a strong foundation,
and the spiritual world
that we’re hearing about in spiritual conception
is very tentative, it’s abstract,
we are not sure,
we’ll have to examine it more,
look at the fine print, etc.”
So he said,
“That’s why it’s ‘all risk and no gain’—
all of this that
I’ve accumulated here,
in the world of exploitation,
the energy that I’ve accumulated,
I’m going to risk all of this
in service to Kṛṣṇa,
which seems
to be something abstract,
and not palpable, inaccessible, etc.
But just as when you go East,
automatically
you’re withdrawing from West.
As you engage in a process
of self-surrender,
gradually you’ll begin to perceive:
this world and everything in it
is insubstantial,
and actually what I’m coming in connection with
in the Kṛṣṇa‒conscious world
is real and substantial.”
So, then the transition
takes place.
So, Guru Mahārāj  said,
“What initially seemed to be a proposition
of ‘all risk and no gain’
in the end becomes
‘all gain and no risk.’”
Because whatever was gathered here
in the temporary world
is not substantial to begin with.
So, what did you really risk?
Nothing.
And you gained everything
in the process.
So, in the end
‘all risk and no gain’
turns into
‘all gain and no risk’.
But how to proceed
in that direction?
If this concept
awakens in the heart
a little sense of potential,
of possibility,
then under the guidance
of sādhu, sāstra, guru, Vaiṣṇava
we try to make some progress.