We know Gurudev’s being
super affectionate, and it’s true.
He’s love and affectionate personified,
really, truly, to the extreme.
[Extreme Tolerance]
And how he backs his devotees.
He goes through hell with them.
And all these things.
And being with people like myself
that’s a likelihood.
It’s not just like
a saying of flattery.
But anyway,
when he was younger …
Guru Mahārāj
could be super affectionate
and loving, and it’s really true;
totally charming and all that,
but He’s also very …
he could be very severe.
That was his word
about himself.
Because when they said
sometime like,
“He made some comments
about this or that.”
He once said,
“I’m a man, who if I was in Vaikuṇṭha,
I would be a troublemaker.
I would cause dissension.”
And like, if he was in Vaikuṇṭha,
people were going like …
he’s saying something higher
than we were actually …
Like, that would be trouble.
He said, again he said us about himself.
Another time something came up,
and we were trying,
‘Oh, no Mahārāj ,
you are this …’
And he goes, ‘No, I’m
a severe commentator.’” That he said.
Once some people
came to him and said,
what they’re trying
to find something to go,
“There’s some letter
at the Alabahat Gaudia Math,
it says you’re a troublemaker,
you did …”
And Guru Mahārāj
is like leaning on the wall,
and these persons
giving this report,
“There’s a letter somewhere, that says—
troublemaker and cause dissension.”
Guru Mahārāj , when it finally was clear,
what’s being said.
He went, “I accept the challenge.”
[Laughing]
He said, “Yes, whenever things
are not up to mark,
I say so, and boldly I say so.
Therefore I’m alone. ”
And we were going like, “But we’re happy
to be with you Mahārāj .”
[Laughing]
So, but also he could be severe.
Gurudev, one of the reasons
Gurudev was so tolerant
with everyone,
it’s only one reason,
there are many.
But he said,
and he meant this,
not as a statement
of humility, but like …
He said, “Guru Mahārāj
was so tolerant with me,
how can I turn around and
not be tolerant with you and others.”
That was a very beautiful
way of thinking.
He’s saying, “I know how much …”
And he’s saying that.
I mean you can adjust it
in anyway you want
according to your conception.
But he did say this.
So, that’s way to say, “Guru Mahārāj ’s
just unlimited tolerant and affectionate.
So I have to, I feel I should do that
with all of you and others, and like that.”