There’re many different ways
that people can measure wealth.
How does the original
Supreme Personality of Godhead,
the Supreme Reality,
measure value?
[Devotion is Measured in the Inverse]
So, if He gets the breeze
from the garment of Rādhārāṇī
upon Him,
His divine form,
He considers that to be
the most valuable treasure.
That Kṛṣṇa, who
yogīndra-durgama-gatir madhusūdano ’pi
tasyā namo ’stu vṛṣabhānu-bhuvo diśe ’pi
[Rādhā-rasa-sudha-nidhi: 2]
well, that’s Mahāprabhu,
same theme with
sureśānāṁ durgaṁ gatir atiśayenopaniṣadāṁ
[Cc: 2.4.51]
Who … the great yogis,
theу’re trying to get a glimpse of,
the Upanishads, the Gods …
When Kṛṣṇa as the baby and Trinаvarta,
He went in the sky,
part of the pastime,
they say, one of the reasons
He went in the sky
is to let the Goddesses, Gods
and Goddesses like, have a look.
[Laughing]
So, who’s durgaṁ—very difficult
to have a glimpse of …
Brahmā is trying to get
an audience with Kṛṣṇa.
muhyanti yat sūrayaḥ
[SB: 1.1.1]
That Kṛṣṇa considers
Himself so fortunate
to be blessed by the breeze from
the garment of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī.
So, the conclusion of Prabodhānanda Saraswatī Ṭhākur
is a special note.
He says, “Therefore, She is so great,
She is so exalted,
so extraordinary, so exceptional,
that I consider the direction
in which She appeared
to be worshipable.”
Well, those in a … Her …
the sādhakas, in the lowest position,
they are voyeuristically
envisioning themselves
as servitors in the Divine domain,
in the upper world,
in the most confidential region
of the spiritual existence.
They have …
those, who are newly recruited
and acquainted
with Kṛṣṇa consciousness
projecting themselves
into those situations.
Someone who is actually there:
ashta-sakhi Tuṅga-vidyā—
Prabodhānanda Saraswatī
in Gaura-līla—says,
“The direction in which She appeared
is worshipable to me!
That’s close enough for me.”
That’s what’s said by someone,
who’s actually there
and eyewitnessed to all
of these things.
And eyewitnessed to how Kṛṣṇa feels
when He’s blessed
with the breeze of the garment
of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī.
He says, “The direction in which
She appears is worshipable to me.”
So, the system
for measuring devotional magnitude
is always in the inverse.