It's a very broad subject,
'what is the happiness in Krishna consciousness?'
As Kaviraj Goswami tells us,
bāhye viṣa-jvālā haya,bhitare ānanda-maya,
kṛṣṇa-premāra adbhuta charita
the 'adbhuta charita', wonderful, wonderfully
astonishing characteristic of Krishna prema,
the highest type of Krishna consciousness,
is that, although externally one appears to be suffering,
internally, they're relishing some
extraordinary type of sweetness.
So we kinda have a stereotype
about what is happiness in Krishna consciousness.
In the Brhad Bhagavatamrtam of Sanatan Goswami,
when he's concluding, perhaps the first section,
he's saying, "The real rasik devotees of the Lord,
they alone understand the joy
and the superiority of Viraha,
of separation. That, if Krishna consciousness
is about depth of love,
'hladini shakti', the sār of Hladini
is prema, bhava, the sār of that -
the cream of that - bhava, maha bhava,
ultimately.
Maha bhava means in this sense,
the greatest heart,
who possesses the greatest heart,
full of Krishna consciousness to the greatest degree,
the greatest depth of heart?
Srimati Radharani,
'maha bhav swarupani, Radha thakurani'
Hladini shakti, personified.
We're told that, so, if this is about
achieving the greatest depths of heart
and magnitude of heart, intensity,
Guru Maharaj revealed - and,
we're back in Golden Volcano,
divine lava -
that in separation, a greater depth
and magnitude and intensity of heart
is achieved than in union.
So when Srila Gurudev
was dealing with this question once,
he said with some - almost disgust,
that someone was trying to put forth the idea
that union was higher than separation,
and Gurudev said, 'Even the animals know about union.'
and he said, 'Goats, they understand something about union.'
He said, 'But who understands the peculiar joy of separation?
Not the animals, certainly.'
Guru Maharaj liked to quote Shelley,
saying "Our sweetest tales
are those full of the saddest thoughts."
He said, what is the Krishna prema?
The real joy, happiness, in Krishna consciouness
appears like you've been bitten,
poisoned by a cobra, and you're haemorrhaging.
Well, bathing in a shower of nectar at the same time.
If you can hold these two things,
it's almost counter-intuitive
or, what's the sanskrit expression..
regarding two opposites being held
in the mind at the same time?
I can't remember the phrase now,
but, these two peculiar
polar opposites, in a sense, simultaneously,
saying, 'that's the actual position
of the higher devotees.'
But as indicated in the Bhagavad Gita
by Srila Guru Maharaj,
when the devotees are discussing
these pastimes, the wide variety of pastimes,
it's as if they're feasting,
that's 'tushanti', like when we have a big feast
and there's one tasteful thing after another,
and you're tasting this, and,
the next thing is more tasteful than that,
another tasteful thing, another tasteful thing,
and as much as you feel nourished,
and acquiring strength and vitality from that,
that's what the devotees get,
hearing, that's their pleasure,
hearing and chanting about Krishna.
But, that said, the sweetest songs
are those that tell the saddest tales.
Hare Krishna.