Krishna who is acarcan, he has magnetic attraction.
Krishna. The devotees sometimes they call him Karshni.
So Krishna, Madan Mohan,
Cupid who is bewildering everyone with his seductive charm,
Krishna is Madan Mohan, puts cupid into a state of bewilderment.
But Radharani the ultimate personification,
devotion personified to its extreme, to its limits,
prema rasa sima
She is Madan Mohan Mohini, she can attract Krishna.
Hare Krishna means also what sometimes Krishna is told as Hari.
One meaning who steals away.
But Hare, Hare Krishna, Guru Maharaj said, Radharani she can steal the mind of Krishna.
So Gurudev like to quote this one sloka where a devotee is noticing
that Krishna's mind has been stolen, he's absent his mind,
like we are saying Radharani can steel the mind of Krishna
with her manohar ladus, or divine serving mood.
So he noticed Krishna is lost his mind and in this sloka
is offering his mind to him.
I see you've lost your mind, so I'm offering mine to you.
And one devotee asked Srila Guru Maharaj, he said,
"And what did Krishna say?"
It's one of his divine sloka concepts
"Then what did Krishna say?"
to the devotee offering his mind
Guru Maharaj said, "Krishna said
"Oh what little mind I have left, you want to take that?"