Because sometimes
things are lost in translation,
sometimes things are gained
in translation.
And while we are
on the subject of translation,
it should be noted—
all translation is interpretation.
[Translation | Depth of Understanding]
All translation
is interpretation.
So when
you read something,
and it says, “Guru Mahārāj
wrote this in Sanskrit,
or Guru Mahārāj
wrote this in Bengali.”
And than there’s
a translation,
that translation
is based upon
the capacity of the translator
to render
what they were able
to extract from that.
Don’t take it literally
these are the words of Guru Mahārāj.
They are the words
of a translator, an interpreter.
Someone who saw this word
and on the basis of their capacity
is saying,
“I think it means this
in my language.”
But it would be a mistake
to think
that these are
Guru Mahārāj’s words.
They are not.
That’s why we find
when we read books
that are in translation,
that weren’t spoken
by Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
in English,
they don’t sound like him.
They sound
like something else.
And in this regard, once
one book was being translated
and it just so happened
that Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
spoke about the very thing
that was being translated that morning.
So, I met with him in the afternoon
cause I was a little concerned.
And I said,
“What they are translating …
what you said this morning,
that’s not what they’re translating.”
And, but his answer
surprised me.
He said,
“Is anything coming through?”
and I said, “Yes, definitely
something’s coming through.”
He said,
“Then it has its value.”
He said, “Just as when
you speak on a śloka,
you are going
to give a class,
and you are going
to speak on a śloka.
According to your ability
you extract something,
and you’re sharing that.”
He said, “It doesn’t mean
that having done that
that you have exhausted
all the possible things
that can be said
about that.”
But according to your ability,
your capacity,
you extracted something
and shared that.
And hopefully we are talking
about inspired representation.