oṁ ajñāna-timirāndhasya jñānāñjana-śalākayā
chakṣur unmilitaṁ yena tasmai śrī-gurave namaḥ
namaḥ
mūkaṁ karoti vāchālaṁ
paṅguṁ laṅghayate girim
yat-kṛpā tam ahaṁ vande
śrī-gurum dīna-tāranam
vande ’haṁ śrī-guroḥ śrī-yuta-pada-kamalaṁ
śrī-gurūn vaiṣṇavāṁś cha
śrī-rūpaṁ sāgrajātaṁ saha-gaṇa-
raghunāthānvitaṁ taṁ sa-jīvam
sādvaitaṁ sāvadhūtaṁ parijana-sahitaṁ
śrī-Krishna-chaitanya-devaṁ
śrī-rādhā-Krishna-pādān saha-gaṇa-lalitā-
śrī-viśākhānvitāṁś cha
ānanda-līlā-maya-vigrahāya
hemābha-divyach-chhavi-sundarāya
tasmai mahā-prema-rasa-pradāya
chaitanya-chandrāya namo namas te
Goswāmī Mahārāja: Yes, prabhu, some questions.
Lake City. “Dear Goswāmī Mahārāja, Śrīla
Guru Mahārāja has famously said,
‘The environment is friendly’ and ‘adjust yourself.’
What constitutes a proper and progressive adjustment?
Is such an adjustment solely internal?
Or, would the dichotomies of ‘internal’
adjustment? Is such an adjustment solely internal?
karma respectively? My sincere appreciation and
dandavats to all who make this facility possible.”
We know many times Śrīla Guru Mahārāja
And we don’t want that to
Means, you repeat something to the point of
where it loses its meaning…
Hare Krishna. So, we know
that’s working [LAUGHING]
But that’s just an expression
that Guru Mahārāja was invoking.
He is not the origin of ‘wait
and see.’ It’s an expression, an English
will put ‘WAIT AND SEE’ on the wall. But
that’s just an expression that Guru Mahārāja
was invoking. He is not the origin of ‘wait
and see.’ It’s an expression, an English
language expression, but he employed that
at particular times. But we should consider
the context of when he said that and also
what he said in its entirety. So, one of the
first time I heard him say that, he said,
“Wait and see.” Followed by it he said,
“What leads to what?” He said, “Which
way the Divine Will moves next?” And then
he said, “All events are not meant to please
me.” The implication being that like there
is… Again, another expression: ‘not a
blade of grass moves without the will of God.’
So, when he says, ‘all events are not meant
to please me.’ Somebody may say, “Well,
that rightfully can be said about anyone and
everyone.” But is there someone for whom
all events are meant to please… in the background,
in overview? So, in Bhagavad-gītā Krishna
tells Arjuna:
bhoktāraṁ yajña-tapasāṁ
sarva-loka-maheśvaram
it is meant to please Krishna.
this yajña, all this tapa, it’s…” Another
way of saying it, it’s only meaningful if
it is meant to please Krishna.
There is another famous verse I wanted to
say:
the use of austerities?”And then it reversed
itself and said, “And if what you are doing
It’s saying, “If whatever you are doing,
the end result (tapasya, for example — austerities).
If the end result is not taking you toward
Krishna, satisfying Krishna, then what is
the use of austerities?”And it reversed
itself and said, “And if what you are doing
is pleasing to Krishna, what is the use of
austerities?” So, what we take away from
that, is the central point of consideration,
is what is pleasing or satisfying to Krishna.
Bhoktāraṁ yajña-tapasāṁ sarva-loka-maheśvaram:
“I am controlling everything.” Īśvara
parama Krishna (Brahmā-saṁhitā).
So, when it’s said, “Not a blade of grass
moves without the will of God,” He is controlling
that. If He is controlling even the blades
of grass what to speak of more significant
movements. And we notice that so many blades
of grass are moving without our permission.
So many things are happening we did not give
permission to these things to happen. So,
then we can assume, most likely, we are not
the Supreme controller. Yet we are trying
to structure our lives and exert a certain
amount of control. You know, like, “You
wanna take control!” What? Of the universe?
Or karmic circumstances that you’ve generated,
that you’re responsible for?
tamasa bahu rupena veshtitah karmahetuna
What we see before us in the form of so many
different life forms. Like Padma Purāṇa:
jalajā nava-lakṣāṇi sthāvarā lakṣa-viṁśati.
What is he saying it’s very interesting.
“Whatever you might see or observe,” he
says, “veshtitah karmahetuna: this is a
karmic dress. You are dressed in your karma.
It’s the cause of you are assuming this
particular type of dress.” So many events
before that led to this present iteration.
You are surrounded by karmic circumstances
that you’ve generated. There’s individual
karma [and] collective karma. So, what is
left to you other than interpretation of the
events that you find yourself in?
Sometimes Śrīla Guru Mahārāja also was,
“As long as we’re casting blame on the
environment, on others (you know, ‘the dancer
blames the dance-floor’) — as long as
we’re casting blame on others, upon others,
or the environment, circumstances (so many
things like that), other people (what does
that say, ‘Hell is other people’), as
long as that is the mentality, then you’re
going to be in this world a long time. But,
if you can take responsibility, and to this
degree,” not to, like, ‘and take control
of your life’ — that is not what he’s
saying. He’s saying, ‘take a responsibility,’
meaning, ‘whatever situation you find yourself
in, you’re responsible for that.’ It may
appear this way, that way, another person
said this, you found some unfair thing happened,
saying whatever — actually he said, “When
you come to realization that you alone are
the sole culprit in the world in which you
live, then your days are numbered.” That’s
the beginning of coming out of this plane,
is that realization: “I alone is the sole
culprit.”
I mentioned the other day, when Guru Mahārāja
was talking about something, one devotee said,
“Oh, Mahārāja, I’m just feeling sorry
for the innocent people in this world.”
And Guru Mahārāja said, “There are no
innocent people.” And we think, “But what
about that cute baby I saw the other day?”
He said, “There are no innocent people.
We have all betrayed our Lord!” You wouldn’t
be in this world if not for that. Whoever’s
here, unless some divine associate of the
Lord descended in this plane to take others
back to home, back to Godhead. Other than
that. This is the situation.
So, we find ourselves inescapably in karmic
circumstances — in karmic circumstances
that are seemed to be inescapable. You can
modify a little bit this way or that way.
What does the Bhāgavatam say?
tasyaiva hetoḥ prayateta kovido
na labhyate yad bhramatām upary adhaḥ
This means, wandering breaths and lengths
in this universe you’re on the basis of
action — for every action equal and opposite
reaction, the karmic circumstances that you’ve
generated — it’s more or less faded to
play out in a particular way in terms of happiness
and suffering. So, don’t waste your energy
merely trying to minimize suffering aspect
and maximize the happiness aspect — it’s
already baked into the karmic cake. But rather
direct your energy elsewhere, in inner culture,
self-discovery, self-realization. And that’s
where we come to the necessity of interpretation.
And by that I don’t just mean whimsical
interpretation but sādhu, śāstra, guru,
vaiṣṇava. To see through the eyes of Scriptures.
What does it say?
tvaṁ bhakti-yoga-paribhāvita-hṛt-saroja
āsse śrutekṣita-patho nanu nātha puṁsām
Śrutekṣita-patho — ‘this is the path.’
What is this path? This is the path of where
you see (íkṣa — ‘eye’) through hearing.
That’s how you see — by hearing. What
does it mean? Śruti, śabda-brahman, divine
sound, revealed truth. When you are under
the influence of revealed truth then you can
have a proper perspective of things. Otherwise
known as sambandha-jñāna. In this context
sambandha-jñāna means ‘the right perspective,’
how to see, how to interpret life, events,
ourselves. Atma-samīkṣa means ‘self-analysis.’
But not just analyzing the karmic, the exterior
karmic self, which is the really… Although
it’s called psychotherapy it doesn’t even
begin to approach the soul. It’s dealing
basically with ego, intellect, mind — different-subtle
coverings of the soul. But actual soul is
another thing, and that we hear about sādhu,
śāstra, guru, vaiṣṇava — revealed
truth. It’t not something that you discover
empirically or by the process of elimination.
So how to interpret these events? And what
should be acknowledged first? Because again
we just say, “Guru Mahārāja said, ‘the
environment is friendly.’” All these things
have to be understood in context. The words
he said before that the words he said after
that. Otherwise, out of context it can sound…
what’s the word, with the ‘C’, ‘casual’
or ‘lacking a certain sensitivity’ or
‘insight’ or ‘being dismissive’ or
‘platitudinous.’ He’s acknowledged that
there are things that are happening in the
environment that are a cause of upset to us.
We’re suffering, we’re upset, we’re
disturbed, we feel wronged, the things are
unjust, unfair, ‘why is this happening to
me?’.
I’ve mentioned that a lady wrote a book
called (I think that was a lady) “Why Do
Bad Things Happen to Good People?” I didn’t
read the book but I know you don’t need
to write a book about this. There’s a one-word
answer to this question — karma. That’s
why bad things happen to apparently good people
who seem to have done nothing to warrant or
justify this kind of thing happening to them.
It’s the basis of some past reaction. And
no less than Mahāprabhu himself in the Śikṣāṣṭakam,
where in the fourth śloka:
na dhanaṁ na janaṁ na sundarīṁ
kavitāṁ vā jagad-īśa kāmaye
mama janmani janmanīśvare
bhavatād bhaktir ahaitukī tvayi
So, the ‘janmani janmani’ part. Guru Mahārāja
says, “This is Mahāprabhu expressing a
particular type of sentiment and he says,
‘Certainly, because of my karma I’ll have
to be born again and again.’” He’s saying
that, so how should we think? Somehow devotees
think they’ve got an exemption clause or
something that if they’re just good in this
lifetime they’re going to go to heaven.
[LAUGHING] But what’s expressed here, he
says, “janmani janmanīśvare: certainly,
as my karma plays out, I’ll have to be born
lifetime after lifetime.” It’s more healthy
to think this way. And then what does he say?
“Considering that — bhavatād bhaktir
ahaitukī, just let me have connection with
your devotees. That would be the greatest
guarantee or gift to Me that in this upcoming
lifetime if I can have association of devotees.”
That’s a genuine prayer. Not, “Oh, my
Lord, put an end to this suffering!” That’s
the prayer of a karmi. So-called karmi. I
know we don’t use that word anymore. [LAUGHING]
It was very popular in ISKCON. And
not only. But anyway. So, he is praying in
that way, which means… Again, I’m using
this context as a way to interpret circumstances.
So, Guru Mahārāja’s saying should be understood
in this way. He will mention, “First, in
the Bhagavad-gītā what’s recommended is
toleration.”
mātrā-sparśās tu kaunteya
śītoṣṇa-sukha-duḥkha-dāḥ
āgamāpāyino ’nityās
tāṁs titikṣasva bhārata
Krishna is telling Arjuna, “These karmic
circumstances, they are like seasonal changes.”
And we see here the rainy season comes, temperature
changes, you’re in a particular climate
you have to make some adjustments. Because
you can’t put an end to the rain, the snow,
the heat, whatever. [That] is sukha-duḥkha.
Sukha and duḥkha, happiness and distress.
So, he said, “The way they appear and vanish,
are just like seasonal changes.” So, what
does he tell Arjuna? “Titikṣa: tolerate
it. Tolerate that, don’t give it more energy
than necessary.”
It also reminds me that Śrīla Guru Mahārāja…
This poet — one is Kalidas, the other, I
think, Magha, and they have similar verses
about lotus and chakravāka bird. We know
there’s one lotus, this mystical lotus,
who blooms in the evening. Sometimes described
as a blue lotus or a white lotus, variously.
Chandrikā. Śreyaḥ-kairava-chandrikā (Śrī
Chaitanya-charitāmṛta, Aatya 20.12). Chandrikā.
But in this poetry, they’re saying, when
the sun sets, these chakravāka birds, they
have this unique character or quality that
they mate, but they must separate at evening
and they have to wait again to come together.
So, what’s being told in the song, in the
poetry, is that upon sunrise certain things
are happy. There’s certain lotus that thrive
at that time, they can come together. Then
sun sets, then the moon comes, then some have
to go apart, and some thrive. And why it’s
being told as it’s saying this is the perpetual
cycle. And actually, not even in only the
mundane world but in the spiritual world.
The only difference — one is Mahāmāyā,
[another is] Yogamāyā. Mahāmāyā is the
cause of suffering in this world but Yogamāyā
is creating pastimes that induce separation
to bring out a greater depth of heart. So,
we would say from the point of view of interpretation
it is going back to ‘how does the heart
see things,’ ‘how is the heart going to
interpret these events.’ So, that sort of
things is given there, to say. It’s always
like that. So, the bottom line being, “Don’t
be too (almost like a Gītā advice), don’t
celebrate too much when things seem to be
going your way and don’t be too devastated
when they’re not.” Try an even keel. Or
in another place Guru Mahārāja would say,
if you go deep (when he’s talking about
‘dive deep into Reality’), if you go deep
in the ocean, whatever is on the surface — the
waves going this way, that way, and so much
turbulence, he said — if you go deeper,
you’re unaffected by it. So again, what
does it mean ‘deeper’? That vision, the
way of seeing things.
So, when we are visited by unhappy circumstances,
first line of defense in Gītā is — “Tolerate!”
But then we say, “This is intolerable!”
Then I’m saying of Gurudev. He would say
as he sat beneath ‘tṛṇād api sunīchena
taror api sahiṣṇunā amāninā mānadena
kīrttanīyaḥ sadā hariḥ’ (Śrī Śikṣāṣṭakam
3). The taror iva sahiṣṇunā, be more
tolerant than a tree. He said, “It means
tolerating what is intolerable.” Because,
if you can tolerate something that is just
difficult to tolerate, that is one level.
He ratcheted it up to another level. He said,
“What it means is — tolerating which is
intolerable.” That is a higher level. [LAUGHING]
He said, “Or honoring someone who’s not
worthy of honor,” in the conventional sense.
So, the first line of defence — toleration.
But you can tell that it almost, in some instances,
has a little bit of lingering resentment or
begrudging like ‘alright, I have to tolerate
this.’ But Guru Mahārāja would tell us,
“In the Bhāgavatam it takes it to another
level.” That’s in the Brahmā-stuti, the
Prayers of Brahmā:
tat te ’nukampāṁ su-samīkṣamāṇo
bhuñjāna evātma-kṛtaṁ vipākam
hṛd-vāg-vapurbhir vidadhan namas te
jīveta yo mukti-pade sa dāya-bhāk
So here it’s saying, from a deeper level
of seeing and interpretation. We’ll remember
earlier in the Gītā it’s said after ‘bhoktāraṁ
yajña-tapasāṁ sarva-loka-maheśvaram’
next line ‘suhṛdaṁ sarva-bhūtānāṁ’
(Bhagavad-gītā 5.29), “Yes, everything
is meant for My enjoyment; yes, I’m in control
of everything?” “Even these unhappy circumstances
that are happening?” “Ultimately, yes!”
What is next line? Suhṛdaṁ, suhṛd — “But
I’m your best friend, I’m your dearest
friend, more than you realize or know.”
So that means, whatever’s happening to you
is not unfriendly. Krishna is not inimical
to us. This is not Judeo-Christian God who
is always like ‘do what I say or you’re
going to get a stick,’ punishment. There’re
instances, known instances, where Krishna’s
taken his flute and tapped the cowherd boy.
But they like that. [LAUGHING] And the flute
is made out of chinmoy. So, it’s not that
‘rod of chastisement’ of the scary God.
He’s saying, “I’m your dearest friend.”
So, then that means, whatever is happening
to us, even unpleasant, is not, with malintention,
is not meant to take us down and therefore
friendly.
When I remember in school. It probably goes
by various names like ‘a pop-quiz,’ ‘a
flash- quiz,’ where the teacher would suddenly
tell the students, “All right, class, close
your books.” And everybody groans, “Oh,
no! Why?” As some people think, “Our teacher
is mean. Why is she doing it to us?” It’s
not because she’s mean but what she’s
realized is although everyone’s making a
show of reading the book, the subject materials,
asking questions, answering questions, she’s
uncertain how much they’re actually absorbing.
“Now close the books. I’m going to give
you a little pop-quiz-flash-quiz (whatever
you want to call it) and then we’re going
to know how much you’re absorbing and which
of the areas that need to be corrected or
where you need to focus your attention on
to get a better understanding.” It’s something
like that, that on the superficial level these
things are objectionable to us. But Guru Mahārāja
is saying, “In the Bhāgavatam it says not
only ‘tolerate’ but ‘take it to a deeper
level’ saying, ‘It’s favorable! Krishna
is not trying to take you down but rather
to promote you.’” So therefore, in that
sense — friendly. “That’s when,” he’s
saying, “the environment is friendly.”
But it’s a way of seeing.
What is the first mantra, the primal guru-mantra?
Oṁ ajñāna-timirāndhasya jñānāñjana-śalākayā
chakṣur unmilitaṁ yena. It’s saying,
“My eyes were cataracted with ignorance,
acquired prejudice, acquired tendency so I’m
not seeing clearly.” Like surgical removal.
Lasers now, they remove cataracts. So, I like
that because it’s light. “By light, enlightened,
I’m expressing my gratitude to Śrī Guru
who opened my eyes that were cataracted with
ignorance. I wasn’t seeing myself and my
life circumstances properly.”
Guru Mahārāja also gave an example unlike
a very high level. Not that we should imitate
but we should be aware. And it’s whole in
the life of Śrīla Gaura-Kiśora Dās Bābājī
Mahārāja. Like we heard about Śukadeva
Goswāmī. We think he’s so beautiful and
such a charming figure but on his way to the
assembly of Parikṣit Mahārāja, on the
banks of Jamunā where the Bhāgavatam was
spoken, on his way there, children were throwing
things at him, calling him names, mocking
him, making fun of him. And then they see
that who looks like a mad urchin, when he
enters the assembly, although he’s 16 years
old and naked, that all these sages with their
big long beards they all stand and offer him
the presidential seat at the assembly. Because
they were, [Śrīla] Prabhupāda says, experts
in the art of physiognomy. Even by his physical
form they knew he was advanced and enlightened
soul, and additionally he was legendary already.
In the time of Śrīla Gaura-Kiśora Dās
Bābājī Mahārāja, like: bhaktāvadhūta
mūrttaye, Guru Mahārāja says in praṇām
to him, one of the praṇāms to him. Like
in avadhut people, as young boys do — they
mock, they tease, they make fun, they throw
things. Imagine, they’re doing that to Śrīla
Gaura-Kiśora Dās Bābājī Mahārāja. Sometimes
we think like, “Why am I being treated like
this? I’m a devotee.” [LAUGHING]
When on a train-ride Calcutta–Nabadwīp
someone said to Śrīla Govinda Mahārāja
when he was Gaurendu Brahmachari, they said,
“How come the sādhus get sick? They shouldn’t
get sick.” (Because, you know, they’re
protected by Krishna, this thing, another.
We see that they’re visited by illness from
time to time.) And [Śrīla] Gurudev said
to them, “No, actually it’s the opposite.
Because they are escaping Maya, she’s trying
harder to get them.” So, we will see it
visited upon them even more, not the opposite.
Vamśī Dās Bābājī Mahārāja also said
in his final days (and he was diseased in
so many ways as Guru Mahārāja said). He
turned [INDISTINCT] to me and would go [INDISTINCT],
“This is your vaiṣṇava? Look at me.
Look at what’s happened to me.” But Guru
Mahārāja said, as a way of saying, “Don’t
think that you’ll be exempt from these things
because you’re ostensibly pursuing a life
of devotion.” But rather those who are on
the verge of escaping are more likely to be
attacked.
And what to speak of such an exalted soul
as [Śrīla] Gaura-Kiśora Dās Bābājī
Mahārāj — they mocking him, throwing things
at him. But Guru Mahārāja said, “His response
was, rather than some ego abhimān come, and
chastising those [children]: ‘do you know
who I am?’, he said, ‘I know it’s you,
Krishna, who are behind all of this. You,
who are guiding their hands, they’re picking
up these things, and throwing them; You, who
are putting these words in their mouth making
them… it’s you, Krishna, I know that.’
And then he said, ‘And I also know how to
deal with you. So, I will go to Ma Jaśodā
and lodge my complaint with and then she will
chastise you.’” That’s Śrīla Gaura-Kiśora
Dās Bābājī Mahārāja’s way of interpreting
what’s happening to him. We can’t imitate
that. But at least, Guru Mahārāja is saying
on the basis of what is presented in the Bhāgavatam
that, when we think about things more deeply,
we can think that it must be for my betterment.
Like once, someone was calling Śrīla Govinda
Mahārāja on the telephone, and saying terrible
things to him, and like doing it repeatedly.
So, at one point, knowing it was that person
again, I said (it was like going to happen
again), I said, “Mahārāja, you know, I
can take a next call and deal with this.”
And he said, “Yes, Mahārāja, I know,”
he said, “but I am thinking why is Krishna
allowing me to hear these things?” I thought,
“This is the way.” He could have dismissed
that person as being insignificant or not
even properly pursuing vaishnavism. Easily.
No one would have objected. But no ego, māna-śūnyatā,
we’re told the bhavankur stage. Māna-śūnyatā
— the total absence of ego. He thought,
“Why is Krishna letting these things being
said into my ear?” That he was more interested
in if there is some adjustment that he should
make. It made him reflect upon himself internally
or his circumstances and see if there was
some need for correction. That was the proper
way to interpret. That’s what he means by
saying ‘the environment is friendly.’
Means in the background.
So he said, “If you can adopt this angle
of vision then between all events and circumstances,
if you look deeply, you’ll see the friendly
hand and the smiling face of Krishna. The
veil will be removed and you’ll see the
smiling face and friendly hand of Krishna
in the background.” And we are here for
spiritual culture as someone saying, “Oh,
that’s the greater souls… How?” You
have to begin somewhere and this is the advice
that’s being given to us. Maybe with tears
in our eyes or a heavy heart we may adopt
this angle of vision for some relief.
Goswāmī Mahārāja: Yes, anything else?
Nityānanda Dās: There is one question from
Gupta Govardhan: “We have some stereotypes
of personal relations with Guru but really
what should they be? Should gave know all
the details of your individual situation,
and take care and give some advice? Or should
you just serve him and that’s it? Some people
are hankering for the personal relations with
their guru but what is it really? Is that
for everyone? And some just say, ‘I don’t
have any relations with my guru actually.’
What to do then? Please, give some advice.”
Goswāmī Mahārāja: Most disciples for the
better part of their spiritual lives will
not be in close proximity to their guru. Even
those who were will not be later for the better
part of their lives. Śrīla Prabhupāda himself
said, “I met with my Guru Mahārāja maybe
ten times.” Think about that. Prabhupāda.
Ten times. But those ten times, what he was
able to extract and what transpired between
them. Even if someone was an intimate server
for the most of their lifetime it will be
spent in separation. Śrīla Guru Mahārāja
will say that a real disciple is always living
in proximity, or the zone, of their guru by
remembrance and thought culture, the remembering
the instructions. That’s how it is most
of the time. Think, Guru Mahārāja, he joined
Gaudia Math in 1927. Saraswatī Ṭhākur
left the world the end of 1936 the beginning
of 1937. So, approximately ten years and then
lived another almost 40 years in the absence
of some physical proximity. But his understanding
of Śrīla Saraswatī Ṭhākur and his susiddhānta
— it [was] just living, growing, developing
— went deeper. Guru Mahārāja will say,
“The disciple has a limited capacity to
actually view guru,” who in this context
is virtually unlimited. But with the growth
and development of the disciple so will their
vision of guru evolve and develop.
And sometimes he would give examples of vani
and vapu. Vapu means ‘form,’ you could
say, ‘physical association,’ and vani
means ‘instructions.’ So, he said, “You
may see (like we see now) pictures of the
guru when they were younger, and then pictures
of them five years later, ten years later,
15 years later, and up to the present. Which
form is the guru? Is that the form of the
guru?”
When we were on the veranda in Calcutta with
Śrīla Govinda Mahārāja there’s that
famous picture of Bhaktivinod Ṭhākur where
he has the beard. And Gurudev looked up (and
that was on his wall around) and he said,
“And to think that he is a 14-year-old girl
in Goloka Vrindāvan.” [LAUGHING] So what
is the form of the guru, that we may see this
evolving in terms of what we’re able to
observe externally? Then we’ll understand,
then it must be the divine current that’s
in the agent, the inspired side of the vaiṣṇava,
that divine current that’s consistent throughout
all the different variations of the formal
manifestation of the guru. And not ignore
that, or diminish that, but that can be our
focus exclusively. So just as we see that
change (over time we observe physical changes)
what we were rather advised is to observe
internal evolution and change to become aware
of that.
So, for example, in Śrīla Bhakti Siddhānta
Saraswatī Thakur’s concluding words of
Śrī Chaitanya-charitāmṛta he says that
when he looks very deeply (and his vision
is… he possesses unparalleled depth of such
vision), he says he sees Śrīla Bhaktivinoda
Ṭhākur and Śrīla Gaura-Kiśora Dās Bābājī
Mahārāj as Gadādhara Paṇḍit and Swarūp
Dāmodar. Doesn’t mean that they’re them
literally but that same quality and function.
And Śrīla Guru Mahārāja on the same theme
will say, again quoting Śrīla Saraswatī
Ṭhākur, “If look at my guru deeply, deep
consideration of Śrī Guru, then first I
come to understand there’re the assistance
and the sakhis, and then ultimately Śrīmatī
Rādhārāṇī herself. And Prabhupāda mentions
this in the first chapter, Śrī Chaitanya-charitāmṛta,
in the purports saying: “The spiritual master
either seen as representation of Nityānanda
Prabhu or confidential associate of Śrīmatī
Rādhārāṇī. That sort of depth. And seeing
is possible through the internal development
of the disciple. But all along they shall
want to serve.”
But then again. Raghunāth Dās Goswāmī.
Śrī Vilāpa-kusumāñjali. Favorite śloka
of Śrīla Guru Mahārāja:
dasyaya te mama raso ‘stu raso ‘stu satyam
sakhyaya te mama namo ‘stu namo ‘stu nityam
Saying, “My focus is on service and the
least aspect.” Sakhya in this sense means
more intimate service. You think, “That
is worshipable to me, that is I hold above
as worshipable. If there is no superior servitor
there for me to serve under and be sheltered
by, what would be my interest there?” And
he is the prayojana-tattva- āchārya of this
line, he’s saying, “My focus is on dāsya.
And if out of service necessity to do more
intimate confidential service I’m prepared
to do that. But that’s not what I hanker
for. I’m a servitor, I’m an aspiring servitor.”
Mahāprabhu is saying:
… pāda-paṅkaja-
sthita-dhūlī-sadṛśaṁ vichintaya
[Śrīla] Prabhupāda would say, “As a particle
of dust at your holy lotus feet.” What does
that mean? Why the word ‘dust’? Because
we understand dust that the least aspect right
of anything is dust, like a dust particle.
It’s another way of saying: ‘an atomic
presence, the least possible connection, is
more than enough for me.’ This is the prayer
of the genuine devotees. It’s in the prayer
of Mahāprabhu. It’s in the prayers of Dās
Goswāmī. It’s in all of the prayers. But
newly recruited neophytes, they’re voyeuristically
envisioning themselves as super servitors
in the spiritual world. It’s a hallucination,
it’s fiction. Uddhava. He has intimate knowledge
of the queens of Dvārakā, he’s Uddhava.
Krishna says:
na tathā me priyatama
ātma-yonir na śaṅkaraḥ
na cha saṅkarṣaṇo na śrīr
naivātmā cha yathā bhavān
Krishna says, “There’s no one more dear
to Me than Uddhava. Not Ātmabhū Brahmā,
not Śaṅkara Śiva, not Lakṣmī even.
Uddhava.” And what does that Uddhava say?
āsām aho charaṇa-reṇu-juṣām ahaṁ
syāṁ
vṛndāvane kim api gulma-latauṣadhīnām
yā dustyajaṁ sva-janam ārya-pathaṁ cha
hitvā
bhejur mukunda-padavīṁ śrutibhir vimṛgyām
“My aspiration is as a creeper, a blade
of grass in the soil of Vrindāvan because
there I may get some of… As Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī
and brajagopis are moving in the plane of
service some of the dust from their holy lotus
feet may fall upon me thereby consecrating
my existence.” So, he prays that way. Uddhava.
Raghunāth Dās Goswāmī echoes the same
prayer.
The motto of Śrī Gaudia Math as composed
and sung by Śrīla Saraswatī Ṭhākur:
pujala rāga-patha gaurava-bhange matala saru
-jana visaya range. Pujala rāga. Rāga-mārga
is worshipable above to us. And when there
was some misunderstanding about what is gaurava-bhange
some foolish persons said, “Vidya-mārga
break it!” I said to Śrīla Gurudev, and
Gurudev was just taking lunch. So, this other
genius comes up with this apasiddhantic nonsense
when I asked, “What does gaurava-bange mean?”
He said, “With folded palms and a bowed
head. That’s what it means — that, that
is worshipable to us.”
The higher devotees are always expressing
their appreciation for the least. And supreme
devotee, Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī, Śrīla
Rūpa Goswāmī in identifying her qualities,
the Radhikastakam. The first verse:
hari-pada-nakha-koṭī-pṛṣṭha-paryanta-sīmā-taṭ
am api kalayantīṁ prāṇa-koṭer abhīṣṭam
pramudita-madirākṣī-vṛnda-vaidagdhya-dīkṣā-gurum
ati-guru-kīrtiṁ rādhikām archayāmi
Hari-pada-nakha-koṭī-pṛṣṭha-paryanta-sīmā,
saying, “What is Her mood?” So, we were
talking about the lotus feet, the dust of
the lotus feet — it’s always telling us
to go for the least aspect so leave it to
Śrī Rūpa to go even finer. So, if you’re
dealing with the lotus feet that means the
lowest and least approach. But if you analyze
the lotus feet further what would be the least
aspect of the lotus feet? The nail, nails
on them. Hari-pada-nakha — ‘the nails
on the toes of the lotus feet.’ And he said,
“Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī considers the
nails on the holy lotus feet of Krishna to
be infinitely superior to Her own highest
aspect of self, magnified millions of times.”
If you’re intoxicated by this kind of vision
it gives you a hint. That’s how she sees
it that the least aspect of Krishna is greater
than her highest aspect of self, multiplied
millions and millions of times. That’s the
way to make an approach.
As Guru Mahārāja says, “The Vaiṣṇava
and the inspired side of the Vaiṣṇava
is the guru.” Devotees, they want to render
some so-called personal service. Mahāprabhu…
Rūpa Goswāmī… We could say, Rūpa Goswāmī
also, but Mahāprabhu told Rūpa Goswāmī,
“I want you to go to Vrindāvan.” And
we see on one level, ‘oh, it’s heartbreak,
why Śrī Rūpa will be sent away?’ “Oh,
no, I want you to…” “I want to be with
you.” “Yes, but then you must follow My
order, and My order to you is to go to Vrindāvan
but in pursuance and realization of this order
you’ll always be with Me.”
Guru Mahārāja told me that on one of the
last times we met and he also mentioned in
that same talk, he said that association is
not based on physical proximity and he gave
the example of lice. You know those [ones]
going your skin, bedbugs. He said, “They
burrow into your skin, they couldn’t be
any more intimately related, they’re literally
under your skin.But the consciousness of the
lice and your consciousness, you’re worlds
apart. Physical proximity doesn’t mean association.
But when the consciousness is the same then
you’re connected.” That’s why I was
saying to someone recently, even the nirjan-bhajan-bhaktas,
so-called the real, actual bābājīs (nirjan
means ‘without people’), they’re not
alone. Maybe they’re without the people
of this world, they’re with more people
than you can imagine because they are deeply
penetrated in the spiritual world. It’s
not like they’re just lonely, they have
no one to talk to. [LAUGHING]
Guru Mahārāja is always engaged in this
internal dialogue. This means with a multitude
of spiritual personalities. When we read the
acharyas’ commentaries, if you read Śrīla
Viśvanāth Chakravartī Ṭhākur you began
to feel something like of his personality
and a certain type of association that is
living, breathing, alive in the commentary.
And it’s infinitely superior to trivial
interactions with people in this world. So
why do we approach the lotus feet of Śrī
Guru? Really, out of service necessity. That
is our intention, that is our aspiration.
At the same time Śrīla Rūpa Goswāmī says
in the Upadeśāmṛta that famous śloka:
dadāti pratigṛhṇāti
guhyam ākhyāti pṛcchati
bhuṅkte bhojayate caiva
ṣaḍ-vidhaṁ prīti-lakṣaṇam
So, he is saying, (there’re three with two
parts — so six), “What are those loving
[exchanges] (prīti means ‘loving exchange’)
between devotees?” And we can say with guru
and disciples. Dadāti pratigṛhṇāti.
Dadati means ‘giving and receiving things.’
I mentioned the other day, we had the good
fortune we were in Los Angeles in 1971. It
was before certain things were established.
And Prabhupāda [would] just go for a walk
in the morning — they’d drive him somewhere
and then he’d walk around the front and
when he’d come back, he’d get out of the
car and we’re all waiting in front of the
temple. There were around 30 of us and we
all had flowers. And Prabhupāda would get
out of the car and there was someone walking
next to him had a basket of flowers. And Prabhupāda
would walk up to you, look at you, say ‘Haribol’
or ‘Hare Krishna,’ and you’d hand Prabhupāda
the flower. Prabhupāda would take the flower,
smile, and he’d give you a flower. [LAUGHING]
So you can imagine we were very happy. [LAUGHING]
So, giving and receiving. The devotees sometimes,
they give a gift out of love and affection
or appreciation
and it’s reciprocated. Guhyam ākhyāti
pṛchchhati. Guhyam means ‘secret’ or
‘confidential’ or in this context ‘revealing
your mind and your heart.’ That can be done.
The guru is not a therapist. A dīkṣa-guru
is not a therapist. Maybe a little bit. [LAUGHING]
Bhakti Lalitā: Spiritual therapist.
Goswāmī Mahārāja: Spiritual therapist.
There you go! Psychotherapy. [LAUGHING] Dealing
with psychos. I mean psyche, the soul. Correct
that [jokingly to Nityānanda Dās]. [LAUGHING]
It’s not that everything that comes in our
head (the mind is a mirror, reflective instrument
like a mirror), anything and everything that
comes in your mind you need to tell your guru
about that. “I had a dream last night! It
was really weird.” It’s guhyam, it means
what’s really troubling the heart that needs
to be resolved out of service necessity. Not
some mundane aspect of one’s life. But we’re
aspiring servitors and there may be something
in our hearts that’s troubling us and preventing
us from serving properly. And you hear in
this, what’s described by Rūpa Goswāmī,
he’s saying, “This is amongst devotees.”
That could be the guru and disciple but also
god-brothers and god-sisters.
And what was the last one? Bhuṅkte bhojayate:
and they take prasadam together. That’s
why it’s an important thing that we do.
And you see, here also, when we have our little
celebration on the devotees’ birthdays.
Like today was Vaninath’s birthday, right?
You’d never know it. So how did we know?
Bhakti Lalitā: Prithu. He keeps track.
Goswāmī Mahārāja: Aha, you see — another
devotee. There you go. That’s the exchange,
loving exchange — another devotee said,
“Oh, it’s his birthday!” And then we’re
all are informed and then we express some
appreciation to him.
Dealing with the guru we should be careful
not to make the guru our servant. We may hear
from Śrīla Guru Mahārāja that really the
position of guru is to serve to the disciples.
But knowing that we shouldn’t take advantage
of it. And just for context, he said, “Just
as when the pūjārī or the cook, pūjārī-sevak,
they take some fruit, they wash the fruit,
peel it, cut it, present it very nicely, put
it on the plate, and offer to the Deity. So,
you could say in a sense that that devotee
is the servant of that fruit. In a similar
way, what’s parallel? The guru through instructions
is cleansing the disciples making them fit
to be offered to Krishna. So, it’s a type
of service. And the guru may think like that,
“I’m here on behalf of my gurudev to serve
these extensions of him who have appeared
in the form of disciples.” Prabhupāda said
that, Guru Mahārāja said the same thing,
Śrīla Gurudev — that really the guru sees
the disciples as extensions of his guru thinking,
“I can’t do the desired service myself
and my guru mercifully appeared in the form
of so many assistants. So, I’m their servant.”
But knowing that we shouldn’t think that
way about the guru. Rather we are trying to
offer ourselves in service. If there’s something
we need to consult with to make ourselves
better at service that can be there. But we
should avoid trivial matters.
And I know in my own case that there was some
period when Prabhupāda needed a new servant.
And he was in New York so I had my 15 minutes
of being his servant. I thank the Lord he
didn’t pick me [LAUGHING] because I wouldn’t
have been able to do the desired service.
But I remember something that happened. He
was sitting like you are just on a little
mat and I’m on the other side serving him
prasadam and there’s no one else around.
And he’s asking me all these questions.
He’s asking me questions. I’m not asking
him questions. And he knew Krishna sent someone
who knows everything that’s going on in
this temple and he will tell me the truth.
So, when the leaders come in and say something
less than the truth, I already know all the
answers. So, it was like he was happy that
I was there. [LAUGHING] But anyway he asked
me different things. At one point when I said
I was preaching to Indians that caught his
interest because he’s also looking for the
devotees to send to India. And I said, “But
Prabhupāda, sometimes preaching to them is
difficult because I’m trying, I preach to
them and then they’ll say something like,
‘Oh, I know what is Krishna.’” And Prabhupāda,
he laughed like [SHOWING]. He said, “That
is their dise-eee-ease,” and put a sweet
ball in his mouth. It’s a disease to think
you know Krishna.
jānanta eva jānantu
kiṁ bahūktyā na me prabho
manaso vapuṣo vācho
vaibhavaṁ tava go-charaḥ
Brahmā-stuti again. Brahmā is saying, “Others
may know and I have nothing to say on this
matter. Very little.” But of course, in
the form of these beautiful prayers, 40 or
50 prayers, that form the basis of Gaudia
ontology, he said, “I don’t have much
to say.” That little inspiration came to
him. But then at one point (and this shows
you something about wanting to be a servitor,
and overthinking something, or not doing the
desired service), so at the end Prabhupāda
said, “I want a toothpick,” and there
were no toothpicks. But I happen to know where
some were. [LAUGHING] I just bow down, “I’ll
be back.” I go out and there’s around
a hundred and fifty devotees on the other
side of this door. They’re all waiting in
the hallway, and I come out, and they’re
all looking at me, and I, “Prabhupāda wants
a toothpick!”, and they all go like, “Aaah!”
And they just start running in different directions.
And I run upstairs and my heart’s beating.
I saw this box of toothpicks and thought like,
“Bring back one toothpick?” I just couldn’t
decide with it so grabbed a handful of them
and then I thought, “Oh, I can’t just…
I have to wash them first.” [LAUGHING] I
can’t just hand Prabhupāda, you know, that’s
our system. So, I run [to wash] the toothpicks,
“Oh, now they’re all full of water!”
Running back down I was shaking all the water
out, “Oh, no!” then I open the door, come
back in, and very calmly pay my dandabats.
I hold out my palm and there [are] around
forty toothpicks in it. [LAUGHING] And Prabhupāda
takes one and says, “Why you have brought
so many?” And I said, “For tomorrow?”
And he was like, “Yeah.” [LAUGHING] And
I thought, “I am not a person for this job.”
So maybe you think it’s the dream engagement
but vaiṣṇavera kriyā-mudrā vijñe [nā
bujhāya] (Śrī Chaitanya-bhāgavatam) — we
don’t want to observe the vaiṣṇava,
‘familiarity breeds contempt.’
Sometimes, depending on who, a little distance
may be healthy for our appreciation. And again,
if we stay on theme of what we’ve said earlier,
Krishna’s in the background. Guru Mahārāja
[says], “Yogamāyā sees all the servitors,
she’s aware of who should come forward to
Goswāmī Mahārāja: Hare Krishna.
counselled devotees to wait and see.
degenerate into, what is called, cant, C-A-N-T.