Krishna considers His own, so much so
that in devotional expression, they
take a position superior to that of the Lord at times.
[On the Shoulders of the Lord]
It's revealed in the beginning of the Chaitanya Charitamritam,
Krishna's speaking very candidly, and says
if aishwarya-jnan, too much knowledge
of the majestic aspect of divinity,
overwhelms, eclipses, conceals some potential
for loving expression, He's disappointed.
Whereas He says His preference, stated preferences,
"But when my friends..." He's going above shanta-das, the friends,
there's also shanta in Goloka, that's another thing we can discuss.
I once said to Guru Maharaj, then understanding something,
"Oh, so, shanta-rasa of Goloka would be different than
shanta-rasa of Vaikuntha." And he said "Of course."
We'll say something about that in a minute.
So, what I prefer, we can say, a servitor position.
Garud, Vishnu, and sometimes Krishna.
Garuda, the beautiful eagle-like servitor,
carrier of Vishnu, the famous Garuda.
He's on the Thai money also, you know that,
if you look on Thai money on the back.
Riding on the shoulders of Garuda is Vishnu, Krishna.
It's a very beautiful image.
Also Satyabhama... was it Satyabhama?
No, no... Rukmini, with Krishna.
Krishna gives the parijata flower,
later, Satyabhama wants a tree.
Anyway, so, how ecstatic Garuda is to
feel the Lord on his shoulders, the touch
of the lotus feet and the divine form of the Lord
upon his shoulders and he's flying happily.
How sweet that is.
It's worshipable, and wonderful, and extra-ordinary.
But, Krishna says in the begining of Charitamritam,
"When I'm playing with the cowherd boys, my friends,
sometimes I'm defeated. And the punishment for the defeated
is to carry the opponent on your shoulders."
He's revealing, "You don't know how much joy
it brings to my heart to carry my devotee on my shoulders."
Garuda's ecstatic, carrying the Lord on his shoulders,
but Krishna, He's ecstatic carrying a devotee on His shoulders,
at the defeat of His devotee.
ye prāyaśo 'jita jito 'py asi tais tri-lokyām (SB 10.14.3)
Ajita. Ajita Krishna. He is unconquerable,
but He's conquered by devotion.
śrī-kṛṣṇā karṣiṇī ca sā (BRS 1.1.17)
Krishna, everyone is being irresistably drawn
in attraction to Krishna, and offering themselves in His service.
But Krishna is being irresistably drawn
to the devotion in the heart of the devotee,
and wanting to serve them.
That's the magic, the miracle, of Krishna consciousness.
And then He goes further to say "You don't know
how happy I am when the devotee is riding on my shoulders,
then I am flying, like Garuda I'm flying
with the devotee on my shoulder, I'm so happy."
How can they climb on the shoulders of the Lord
if it is not seva?