Modern psychology,
which is descended from humanism,
they’re trying to encourage people
to believe in themselves.
[Being Humble—Go for It]
So much so, that in the modern world
people are aggressive, beyond assertive,
they’ve gone beyond submissiveness,
humility, being virtuous—
admirable, desirable qualities—
to … in the Darwinian world,
where only the strong survive
and survival of the fittest.
We are being told, “We’ve got
to be assertive, aggressive, go for it
because you’re number one.
you’re worth it.”
All of this kind of things,
which is the antithesis of spiritual culture.
Because for the finite,
any finite to think
that they are the Infinite,
or by another name—God,
is the ultimate folly or foolishness
to think that you are the Supreme Entity,
that the Universe
revolves around you.
Humility is the outcome
of the perceived presence
or proximity of greatness.
It’s not a posing, a posture.
An actor can act humble;
the director can tell the actor,
“In this scene you’re very humble.”
He can tell a super arrogant person—
they may be super arrogant
in their normal life—
“But in this scene
you are very humble.”
They may be totally insensitive—
“You’re very moody, you’re crying,
you’re feeling that …”
So, we are not talking
about an act or pose,
being a poseur—
posing as being humble.
But humility should come
as a natural outcome
of being in proximity to greatness.
Just as if we are standing
on the shore of an ocean—
automatically, as we’re looking
towards the horizon,
we see how vast the ocean is,
automatically feelings of humility
may descend within us.