When we say,
“These higher devotees …”
They are not meditating
as people conventionally
think of meditation.
When they are in the inner world
they’re rendering seva.
It’s not that they
are just thinking
about something
that’s pleasing to them.
Bhajan means direct service,
They are serving
in that plane.
It’s not just having
a glimpse of view
of some extraordinary,
divine …
what do they say,
what’s the word?
Environment, but scene …
Avadhūt Mahārāj: reality.
Goswami Mahārāj: yeah,
but they’re serving there.
So, he says in that world
to the devotee
at his side in this world,
he’s saying,
he’s giving him a commend
of some service
to do in that plane,
and it also has to do
with not allowing
any disturbance
to come in the pastimes
of Rādhā-Mukunda.