We speak of the guru principle,
or guru‒tattva in all of its manifestations.
[Guru | Depth of Field at Infinity]
So, Śrīla Viśvanāth Cakravartī Ṭhākur,
and in one sense
the premiere guru song
the Gurv-aṣṭakam,
sung by all devotees, everyday.
sākṣād-dharitvena samasta-śāstrair
uktas tathā bhāvyata eva sadbhiḥ
kintu prabhor yaḥ priya eva tasya
vande guroḥ śrī-caraṇāravindam
So, we are told that
our beginning conception
sākṣād‒hari—directly Kṛṣṇa.
Kṛṣṇa is the focal point.
Like when you have
in photography:
focus, near depth of field,
other things.
There is also a type
of depth of field called infinity.
So here we’re told,
and Guru Mahārāj’s given
a perfect example,
and he says, just as let me
talk of the Himalayas, Himalaya,
the Everest is the supreme peak.
So, he said,
“You’ll see that from …
in one sense
making your approach,
from the greatest distance
you see Everest.
So, focused on Everest,
with Everest as your goal
you make your approach.
But, the proof positive that
you are coming near to Everest
that you are going
in the right direction,
is you will come in connection
with so many subordinate peaks,
which are surrounding Everest.
That you are coming
in their connection
means you are going
in the right direction towards Everest.
The parallel being that
vāsudevaḥ sarvam iti
Guru Mahārāj identifies this
as the first conception of Kṛṣṇa
of the upper world,
of the spiritual domain,
but not accompanied by His potency.
Bhagavān in earnest means
Lakṣmī–Nārāyaṇa, Sītā–Rāma,
Rukmiṇī–Dvārakādhīśa,
and Kṛṣṇa in Mathurā,
Vṛndāvan—
vṛndāvana haite śreṣṭhe govardhana-śaila
gāndharvikā giridhārī yathā krīḍā kailā [Pj: 3.22]
And like that. And svayaṁ bhagavān
Kṛṣṇa, at the right hand of Rādhārāṇī.
So Everest by parallel
representing Kṛṣṇa,
and going near, coming in connection
with those surrounding Everest.
So, Kṛṣṇa conception
sākṣād-dharitvena samasta-śāstrair,
but then this interesting shift
takes place,
kintu prabhor yaḥ priya eva tasya
vande guroḥ śrī-caraṇāravindam
Which Guru Mahārāj
renders as ‘prabhor priya’—
it’s saying,
“But upon a closer examination
of guru-tattva, the guru principle,
the guru conception—guru,
we’ll see a shift takes place
from Kṛṣṇa to His potency.”
Prabhor priya—the one
who is most dear to Kṛṣṇa.