When we hear about these
different demigods,
should we think, what is known to us
is unknown to them?
[Gods in Illusion | Beauty of Krishna Consciousness]
From one point of view,
like when Guru Mahārāj would say,
“Brahmā, Śuka, Śiva—
they’re aspiring for a drop
of this divine substance.”
So we’ll see
certain instances,
where Brahmā is vimohan,
he is deluded.
But deluded by what?
Kṛṣṇa, it’s Kṛṣṇa-līlā.
It is not conventional māyā.
So one context—we’re seeing him
as the head of the sampradāya,
another context—we’re talking
about Brahmā-vimohan.
And this is not
a simple matter.
No less than Madhvācārya,
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj said,
he eliminated chapter 13
from the Śrīmad Bhāgavatam.
He couldn’t digest that
the head of the sampradāya,
in Guru Mahārāj’s terms,
‘could be seduced’
or Brahmā-vimohan,
put in illusion.
We see in the 8th Canto
of Śrīmad Bhāgavatam,
in the pastime
of Mohinī-mūrti
that Śiva’s bewildered
by this divine manifestation.
And not to leave it there,
just while we’re on the subject …
Baladev
in the brahma-vimohana-līlā …
We’re told, the morning
that that happened,
that that pastime occurred,
was Baladev’s birthday,
Viśvanāth Cakravartī Ṭ􏰅hākur
said.
So he didn’t go that day,
as Yoga-māyā would have it.
He wasn’t cowherding
with the rest of the boys.
Yaśodā kept him home, Rohiṇī …
and they had some …
He was the birthday boy!
So the birthday boy
wasn’t there,
when Brahmā stole the cows,
and all of that …
So, we’re told,
a year later …
it’s a year, an Earth year—
a moment in Brahmā- loka,
that there are three levels
of Yoga-māyic influence over Baladev.
And Viśvanāth makes the point there,
how extraordinary Yoga-māyā is.
So that even Baladev,
he wasn’t aware that this happened.
A year later, we’re told, a few days
before it was a year later, He …
He went from the third level
to the second level
and started making
certain observations.
Then from the second level
to the first level,
things were becoming
more clear,
till it all vanished,
and he realized that …
and marvelled at how
even he didn’t know,
what Kṛṣṇa had done.
That’s something extraordinary.
ahaṁ vedmi śuko vetti
vyāso vetti na vetti vā
[Cc: 2.24.313]
This is part of the beauty
of Kṛṣṇa consciousness
and reminds us
to be humble.
That there is
no final adjustments
in the sense
of a static understanding
of what’s taking place
at any given place and time,
especially related to the pastimes
of Lord and His Divine servitors.