We can’t impose
mundane limitations
upon the prospects
or possibility of divine form.
[Stanislavsky Method of Sahajiyaism]
But
anyābhilāṣitā-śūnyaṁ
jñāna-karmādy-anāvṛtam
ānukūlyena kṛṣṇānu-
śīlanaṁ bhaktir uttamā
[CC: 2.19.167]
But now that form is covered
by layers of karma, jñāna,
by layers of ego,
by layers of acquired tendencies,
acquired exploiting tendencies.
So it’s hidden
beneath layers of ego
and acquired
exploiting tendencies.
How to again manifest?
Through dedication.
The unit of construction
of the svarūp
are dedicating tendencies.
That we have to understand.
It’s not that now we will
voyeuristically envision ourselves
as super‒servitors
in the Super‒super‒subjective world.
As is the mistake
of the prakrita–sahajiyas.
Sahajiya gurus
from the very begining
they say,
“This is your identity,
this is your svarūp,
here is your name,
your dress, your form;
you do these activities,
now practice that
until you realize that.
I call it the Stanislavsky method
of sahajiyaism.
[Laughing]
Stanislavsky …
This was his method for acting.
Meditate on that character,
walk like them, dress like them,
talk like them, think like them,
do everything like them,
and if you are good at it,
you’ll have an epiphany,
and you realize you’ve become
that character, you are not acting.
You’ve transformed
into that character.
It’s great for acting,
but not for the cultivation
of Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
Rūpa Goswāmī warns
against this very thing.
Those who are sentimental by nature,
and those who are acting.
Rūpa Goswāmī made this warning
five hundred years ago,
and I don’t think it was
exclusively intended
for people living now.
That means, even then when
we have stories Chaitanya-bhāgavat
and elsewhere
of someone feigning devotional …
devotion and ecstatic devotion.
In the  Chaitanya-bhāgavat
there is the story of …
when once snake charmer,
and there is a group
of people assembled,
and Haridās Ṭhākur
seeing the snakes, the cobras,
he is reminded
of Ananta Dev,
and he enters a divine trance
and state of ecstasy
on account of that awareness,
and his body
is devastated with waves
of ecstatic symptoms,
and he faints to the ground,
and all the people there bowing
worshipping him,
taking his feet dust.
And some envious
sahajiyās brāhmaṇ thinks,
“For that he gets this?
I can do better than that.”
Then he puts on his show
of devotional ecstatic symptoms,
and the people
are beating him.
And he’s thinking,
“I don’t understand,
when he did it,
you all were worshipping,
taking feet dust …
I do it and I am getting …
a club over the head.”
He’s saying,
“Yes, because what you are doing
is mocking the great devotees,
for whom these things are real.
You are imitating
the mahā-bhāgavata.”