Sometimes Gurudev and Guru Mahārāj
would say, “Your future is so bright,
it’s unimaginable,
you can’t conceive!”
[Who is a Real Enjoyer—
Devotees or Demons?]
They’re seeing the soul,
not a flawed covering
of acquired prejudices;
acquired tendencies
is karmic dress.
They’re addressing
the soul aspect,
“Think, your reality potential
is inconceivably great!
You don’t know,
such a bright future awaits you.”
vṛndāraṇyaṁ sva-pada-ramaṇaṁ
prāviśad gīta-kīrtiḥ
[SB: 10.21.5]
and what does it say?
“In Vṛndāvan,
the soil of Vṛndāvan,
when the lotus feet of Kṛṣṇa,
as He’s walking,
are ph-ph-ph [sound of steps]
pressing His soft,
inconceivably soft lotus feet,
pressing it against
the also soft moist soil of Vṛndāvan”.
mridu-pade pashupangajaya
What does it say?
“The Earth is shivering
in conjugal ecstasy
at a touch
of the lotus feet of Kṛṣṇa.”
So who’s real hedonist,
who’s a real sense enjoyer?
Who wants real, never-ending,
ever-deepening ecstasy—
the devotee or the ... for demon
would be another D-word.
Devotee or demon—that has like a kind
of assonance, alliteration going on.
The materialist or the spiritualist?
(Be a little more generous).
Both are targeting pleasure,
but one is by trying
to acquire, control,
and consume things lower than me,
to generate that;
the other is by offering oneself,
one’s heart, one’s soul, oneself
to something noble,
worthy, higher.
That’s why Guru Mahārāj
appreciated those things.
Because it reminded him of devotion,
dedication, divinity.