What's expressed from the heart of the devotee,
so what's coming out of the heart
of Jayadev Goswami, expressed in the Gita Govinda,
that's giving great joy to Chaitanya Mahaprabhu.
[The Givers of Inaccessible]
So we can't think "Well it's kind of an esoteric point.
How is this practical?
What about the guy on the bus?
The guy in the tuk-tuk?
What is he going to do with this?"
Well, not everything is meant to please
the guy in the tuk-tuk, or the guy in the bus.
They're writing things that please Chaitanya Maharaprabhu.
yā niśā sarva-bhūtānāṁ tasyāṁ jāgarti saṁyamī [BG 2.69]
What's in the mind of Einstein and Heisenberg
and the quark guy, Planck,
that's madness to ordinary people.
But is it madness?
It's madness to ordinary people,
but is it, there's nothing there?
Or there's something very powerful and substantial there?
So what's being expressed in this sort of love poetry,
yes, it's very high and very wonderful,
but that's what Krishna consciousness is,
it's something very high and very wonderful.
Yes, our general position is to provide things
that are accessible, but at the same time,
it's giving accessibility to something
that's ultimately very high and wonderful.
As Guru Maharaj said, the most exclusive
but the means to achieve it will be all-inclusive.
So we're in the all-inclusive mode,
then we'll figure out different ways of accessibility.
But it's to bring people to that most exclusive plain.
Where? What is its characteristic?
Sri Krishna karshini ca sa,
Krishna's so charmed by the devotion
in the heart of the devotee,
that great infinite magnitude sun we're talking about,
comes under the control of the ray, the finite.
From this example, the sun comes under the control of the ray.
How's that possible?
Because what's in the heart, love and affection,
is so valuable, as Guru Maharaj said,
love's the greatest thing ever invented. (As if it was invented.)
That... Krishna's so eager for that,
he comes under the control of the devotee.
That's the extra-ordinary thing.
Hare Krishna