so we're continuing reading
from the chaitanyas to come
the first two verses this is the third one uh
just to refresh
it
be saying how the gods shiva brahma
in disguise they've descended in human form
bearing the gifts of the love and affection
of their hearts as an offering to come to sri
caitanya dave to have a glimpse of his divine form
he who is descendants of bhaktiviyam sudham nija
bhajanam mudram padishaan with his devotees
surrounded by his devotees and he himself is
showing what is devotion pure devotion
the highest type of pure devotion
that of sri radhika
approach with great trouble
the upanishads they're showing
him he said in a far-fetched way
and the moonies um that will satisfy all their
hankering but really to those who surrender
they will find swedish of the sweet madhurima
and what would they find nikila pashu parlambuja
who is seems to be have the gist of the
divine love of the gopis of vrindavan
remember that is what is krishna consciousness
this is not um an interesting um sidebar or
peripheral information it's what krishna they
possess krishna consciousness and can extend
krishna consciousness to others they do that
in the pastimes of sri caitanya mahaprabhu
is the extension of the krishna consciousness
movement to others or say more specific the heart
a celebration of the heart of srimati radharani
and extending her gracious heart to others
so in this verse he says swarupam
prapanasrivaso janita paramananda gaurima
harir dino daari gajapati kripalt sekatarala
he showed that his figure his divine form
is above everything that has been shown
up till now all right jagadotulium which can
never be compared with anything in this world
in such a way he has shown his beautiful sweet
figure so then we think what about krishna kandar
10 million magnitude beauty cupid magnitude
on the cupid magnitude beauty of krishna
in this threefold bending form
how sweet how beautiful is krishna all
right said the sweetness personified
so if krishna possesses the beauty
charm sweetness of 10 million cupids
and known less than the queen rukh mini
m
name it can also mean sound and
divine sound descending divine sound
the path where you see through hearing
so the rupam the form of krishna
is perceived through hearing
not so much through seeing unless premanja
nachorita bhaktive chanina that those eyes
that type of seeing has been
uh infused with krsna-prem love and affection for
krishna so through sound by hearing just as the
vipre putneys they heard about krishna
the wives of the brahman the others and vrendavan
remember not everyone lives you know in nandavavan
maybe they live nearby uh and and the general
area and they're hearing we're told from fruits
sellers vegetable sellers garland sellers when
krishna performs these miraculous pastimes
it's the talk of the town and that town happens
to be vindavan so they're buying something did you
hear what happened what you hear about kalia
and krishna no then they're telling singing
actually all right kalia domina like the
songs of bhakti you know talk they're singing
what uh they heard about krishna leela and
extending it to others so through sound
uh krishna conception impression
is coming to the heart stanis
said your first real contact with reality is
when you hear from a divine agent about krishna
that's the first substantial connection
with reality that is what is accepted i'm
quoting guru maharaj but he's saying mahaprabhu
when and his ramen on the talk talked
with ramen under roy ramananda samban
posing one thing being rejected asking
a question supplying out dismissed
trying to get it what is the substantial thing a
substantial connection with reality when you say
gyane prayasana mandeva
stop trying to understand
the infinite by finite means
as guru maharaj responded to the you know the
questioner the challenger if the infinite cannot
make itself known to the finite then it's not
infinite all of these things are thematically um
consistent right so brahma gyanai prayasamuda
passana monte eva do not try and ascertain
measure or know the infinite by finite means
it always be you know do we only two fingers
too short right the sum total of the
finite is never equal to the infinite
so what are you saying
means the from the mouths of realized
whatever your position is and what does that
mean whatever your position is it's all inclusive
there are no exceptions the same way it's an
absolutely saying whatever your position is
stan he's the town wherever you're situated
if you hear from krishna loving person
then that is your first real connection with
reality and it's not something small it is
uh can be heart swallowing devouring no less than
srimati radharani saying and the brahmara gita
when urba was sent as a messenger to
krishna by krishna to assuage the separation
anguish and the hearts of radharani and raja
gopis so he comes with a letter to read to them to
give them some hope and but krishna
always teasing out a deeper level of
love and affection suggest to them that they um
they could take up yoga and learn to meditate
you know sometimes god is
everywhere think god is everywhere
and they're saying krishna god is everywhere
i mean we can laugh they're not laughing they're
becoming angry he's telling them they should
learn this yogic meditative and like
gyanis analyze things and try and discern
the the you know signal of divinity in
the midst of so much non-divine noise
not appreciated by them radharani
apparently was not even listening
she is on the side and we thought who is she
preoccupied with one rather large bumblebee and
by bumblebee we mean the really big kind that
are bla they're alternately black and yellow
they're deep black and deep yellow color
reminiscent of a certain personality
whose young shama ramachanta
gunas rupam is covered in the
medite abra tari dambaraya
the lightning like dress
so we're told was that like krishna and a
bumble bee drone form come to observe her or
she is speaking to them as if krsna's
his master but that could also be it
but and we mentioned that this talk known as the
brahmara gita means really the song to the bee
that considered to be a specialty of
guru maharaj and giving explanation
but beyond conventional explanation
but one thing we can say one
verse there gives us some hint
what is exp expressed in loving anger it's
in response to the uh teasing of krishna or
the separation from krishna as
we'll hear in charitam written
on the krishna premiere
wonderfully astonishing quality
or characteristic of krsna-prem is
and separation that externally they appear to
be suffering like anything like the effects of
cobra venom while internally relishing some and
guru maharaj's words peculiar strange nectarine
substance these two um simultaneously so
as the maxim and separation the maximum
pressure is put upon the heart upon love and
affection like being squeezed so then some
how do you say
a higher quality
it yields a higher quality of love and
affection than under normal conditions
krsna's addicted to that because they
think like why does he do these things
if he knows separation will
practically kill his devotees
why does this happen repeatedly because it
the under the force of the pressure uh love
and affection under the force of the pressure
of the the the greatest amount of separation
that yields this sweetest type of krishnapram
and as srila gurudev would
say in the case of mahaprabhu
he said you want to understand who
he is what is his tasting matter
kandar pakuti kamini abhishek that
krishna lakshmi sahasra satyam
sometimes we see the picture
of 64. different norah ions
vishnu's one lakshmi one narayan saying
and what is goloka lakshmi sahasra sombra
a hundred thousand a million a
million lakshmi's one krishna
that tells you right away things are
different there and that person akila
krishna sweetness personified
for the devotees
from south india these two books
krishna khan amrita and brahma sangeetha
so then everything must be there
madhuram madhuram madurasyabibo badanamba madaram
the form of krishna is so sweet
and if on that form of krishna that sweet
form of krishna he's saying his face
is even sweeter anangutsavam in the
words of jayadev goswami vishvaysam
anaranjani na janayananda mendivaro
srini shamula kamal anangotsavam
as a festival looking at krishna the
different aspects of krsna's divine
form is the festival for the eyes that's
the opening uh sloka of the gita govinda
no and so that krishna so everything but his
face is even sweeter than the rest of his form
if you have the good fortune to
look upon his gaze upon his face
load his face and then what does he say and on
that lotus face maru gandhim reduce me to me oh
if he smiles oh that's too much his form is
sweet his face is even sweeter but if he smiles
it's too sweet
saying sweet sweet sweet sweet
so that person sweetness personified he
knows everything there is to know about
the joys of union
so why is he come as mahaprabhu certainly not to
with that in mind and saraswati takur addresses
this in the very beginning of the caitanya
bhagavata to impose the krishna persona
on mahaprabhu is uh what is he saying like
it will be um disastrous or words like that
that is the fault of this is
known as the goranga nagaris
to put mahaprabhu and the
position of it and enjoy her
anyone those are not his pastimes
as gurudeva what is this tasting
matter describe aruba goswami p dabir
back to this that it simultaneous like
one's being poisoned by cobra venom and then
bathing in a shower of nectar and how can
you have these two things at the same time
that's impossible that's why gurudev
said yeah this is cannot be understood
by conventional means but this is the tasting
matter of caitanya mahaprabhu the type of prime
yield from the separation anguished
heart right so that krishna
reality of the beautiful uh how what if it says
here that um nothing can be compared to the beauty
of this form oh back to rukh meaning bhagavan
bhuvana she said you're the most hearing about you
your form appeared within my heart and mind
so i heard all these things about her like
anyone who's an aspiring aspirant of the krishna
consciousness movement hear about krsna some
impression comes to the heart you almost said
when you go before the deity you go to be seen
by the deity darshan be seen by the deity why
i think well where's come on we're looking
that's true but he says what
is our capacity to see krsna
limited at best and but that
see how he sees in the inverse
and he's saying but the deity there's no
limitations on the deity's capacity to see us
although um someone who does not
have faith may not appreciate that
but for groomers it's just obvious
it's spiritual common sense
that we have a very limited capacity to see krsna
but krishna has unlimited capacity to see us
and it'll be good for us to present ourselves
before the deity to be seen by the deity that
with our limited capacity to view also
but really what will be most beneficial
is not derived from our limited capacity
to see the deity but rather the deity's
unlimited capacity at seeing us being
bathed in the glands of the deities
so but rook means saying by hearing about you rupa
your divine form i can say i see you and i say
you're incomparably beautiful you must the most
beautiful thing in the world and she adds to that
and now i now it's clear to me why i have eyes
it's to that level like oh this is the function
of eyes is to see your beaut behold your beauty
the function of ears to hear about you and
your holy name and we go further you know the
the divine sound of your flute and your
ornaments everything every sense here's rishikesh
he is the epitome of the fulfillment
of all sensual experience all of it
so she is saying that right and
so then how do we take here it's saying but um
that um nothing can be compared with anything
the the beauty of mahaprabhu
saying well is it the same as krsna
or how should we think right so as
inconceivable as it may be so you have
there's the incomparably beautiful krishna so
um who's infinitely increasingly more beautiful
by the perception of the premic hearts of the
devotees but if that krsna becomes enveloped
by the heart and halo of srimati radharani
sometimes we are krishna 64 just for some
shorthand mouths 64 divine qualities in krishna
although they're innumerable 64 prominent and
radharani innumerable 25 prominent so if you
take the 64 christian and the 25 of radharani and
combine them in one which is
unthinkable and inconceivable
then beholding the divine form
of sri caitanya mahaprabhu
that shiva and brahmav descended disguised
as human beings to have a glimpse of
then we can understand srila ripa
gosvami saying swarupam bibranu jagat
the incomparable beauty of sri caitanya mahaprabhu
and then he says guru maharaj for
many things here he is giving um two
interpretations so he's saying or it can mean
that swarupam can because we mean divine form
here he said swoop it can also means damodar
that swoop dominar showed he is the possessor
of the unparalleled wealth capital in him
you know the crest jewel treasure
you know chaitanya lila ratnasar
means the treasurer
the storehouse like in moths and godiamot
and caitanya the person who keeps all of the
the things you keep for the kitchen
and everything no but everything
yeah it's like everything you
keep in the storehouse all your
the valuable goods you keep there
so that person is called the bandari
and they always have a key you have to go to the
bandari and then they open up and then they have
as you say the ghee the this and everything
you know that would be in the ordinary sense
but interesting what do you call the person who
keeps all the financial assets ending up the
treasurer i mean you can say chief financial
officer but the treasurer is the old word
right but in what's within the word treasurer is
the treasure meaning that person who's keeping the
treasure right the all the treasure means all the
wealth that you have the treasure that you have
the valuable things they're all given to this one
person has all of them that's what's being told
here by rupa goswami saying caitanya lila ratnasar
ratnam means jewels right so you're saying they're
all with through damidar everything you could want
to know about caitanya leela substantially is all
comes from swoop damadar elsewhere i mentioned the
ramananda sambad earlier at the conclusion of that
kaviraj goswami will say what i just presented
here which is extraordinary and guru maharaj said
is you know the basis of his ontological
method he extracts everything from there
kaviraj goswami will say what i presented
here is all based on the notes of srip dominar
comes from the notes of dhammadar and the
fluffed out notes of raginatas goswami
what is his position he's the
secretary of sroop damodar
personally assigned that
position by caitanya mahaprabhu
so damidar raganath dasco swami what they have is
transferred to christianity's kabhiraj goswami and
presented as sri caitanya charitamritam so here i
think sroop swarupam bibrano jagatatulium that the
position of sroop damodar is incomparable like we
will hear that um well at the very beginning of uh
caitanya charitamritam those first
what is that how many 14 17 slokas
that guru maharaj said form the
superstructure of chaitanya charitamritam
how many of them are from swoop damodar including
ones about nitin and advaita but about mahaprabhu
rupa goswami anarpita chirimchirad
kornavathir nakulum but then followed by
so right away this is around the
fourth sloka or so uh sroop damodar
laying the groundwork saying what radha
radha and krishna they're there's ratan
krishna and then they combine as one
when they combine as one that
is sri caitanya mahaprabhu
and sometimes they're separated there's
two and other times there are one
and this guru might as well say which comes first
gore leela or caitanya leela the giver or the gift
we'll hear from chagravarti takur elsewhere
that they're both nitya eternal and running and
parallel that we can conceive in that so we can't
say which one comes first well no there's radha
and then this comes later he said no not like that
they were one they separated they become one again
so bisphenol says no they're these uh gorilla
and caitanya lila are running in parallel
and and he tells us from the very
beginning what is extraordinary and and and
previously uh not revealed
saying radha bhava duti subalita
that he is enveloped by the heart of
srimati radharani and that has converted
shamasandra krishna onto krishna bahir
goran darshitang gariba normally his krishna
shama blackish dark but the heart of radharani
he's enveloped salma sundar krishna is enveloped
by the heart of radharani and that's
turning the radiance of her heart duty
has turned shamas under krishna and the
gauranga sundar mahaprabhu now he is golden
complexion and why because he's saying that
but then why why did this happen see radhayap
he's serving the
variously described as millions billions
or trillions of raja gopis what is not
possible for the infinite krishna and
one has observing her unparalleled
qualities characteristics heart sentiments
kutuki it is awake in the curiosity
within him to experience her position
again and that ramananda
sambhad we're told that uh
quoting the gear to governor radha madaya
to establish the supremacy uh of the
position of srimati radharani saying that
that krishna left the rasa lila to search for
her radha madaya means taking her into his heart
the bridge of sunderies the remaining bridge
of sundays he left them all to search for one
so if we say there's a trillion of these
inconceivably incomparably beautiful
vraja gopis rajasundaris and minus one so
i think one normally in normal mathematics
one trillion minus one most people
would still consider to be a trillion
to be of the same it's quantitatively the same
1 trillion minus 1 is quantitatively the same
right so why is it that krishna there's a
trillion minus one that he leaves the trillion
to go search for the one if quantitatively
a trillion minus one is a trillion
so then qualitative aspect must not
be the consideration but quality
and then so it's a way of
telling us so this one possesses
heart a trillion-fold heart heart of a
trillion-fold magnitude i say that's inconceivable
what should we expect if to consider
the position of srimati radharani the
better half of the sweet absolute she would be
marginally superior to others or vastly superior
or a trillion-fold superior that
that is guru maharaj says uh
quality gives us relief from mathematics right
that means quality gives us relief from quantity
but it very very beautifully said
mathematics right so trillion one
and the magnetic pull of the heart of the one
it tells you it has a trillion fold magnitude
and that's just too uh so that
we should have some uh respect
to that degree and not think she's just marginally
better you know why did she leave or told that uh
vishaka singh in that first of all so many
are singing dancing it's the rasa lila
and uh and as guru maharaj would say
and tell me about that sambandha abhide
and sambandha radha madana mohano
sriman rasa rasa rambi bang shibata
so answering the flute song of krishna
the trillion gopis the symbol and all the groups
are there and the rasalila is in full swing
but why guru maharaj said the uh truth and the zoi
is located in the middle in the central position
saying here the praise talib it's for a selected
group means raja rani's group for govinda
whereas the gopinath and as all the groups
is humble but that still to say that so
then vishaka singing and dancing superiorly
to anything anyone before that then lalitha
and we hear damodar is always supplying the
songs and the slokas the mahaprabhu is lolita
she does that in krishna world
for radharani when she's feeling
the depths of separation from krishna so
she when now that mahaprabhu is enveloped
krishna is enveloped by the heart of
radharani when he's feeling similar
anguish of separation she supplying all
the songs and slokas that she does for her
best friend so anyway that so lolita she sings
and down says in the most superior fashion then
gurman said radharani thinking like so
krishna you take i'm one of the group
there's a group and i'm one of the i'm par
i'm one of the members of the group is that it
so as guru maharaj's deity
gandharva saraswati gandharvika
who is singing and dancing to enchant
krishna so radharani displays infinitely
superior singing and dancing and then leaves
in a huff being taken as one of the groups
because she is in fact governed the priesthood
so but that the
pull of the magnitude of her love and affection
among krishna pulls him away from the trillion and
he goes searching for her all right so sri raat
what is swift sri radha pranayama mahima kidnash
why did he steal the heart of radharani plunder
the heart's mouth because he wants to experience
the sort of pranay love prem that
she alone experiences no none else
what can that mean but mahabhava mahabhavs
so that he wants to experience because we can
say he's descended to you know suave octavium
to experience devotion i mean it's
bhaktapov the heart of a devotee
the love and affection of devotees and that's true
but that's also generic it's non-specific so
yes of a devotee which devotee any devotee
particular devotees the supreme
devotee the supreme devotee so swift
swarupini radha takurani adi rudhabav the
highest type of love and affection for the
gopis and radharani her uh heart is the the
reservoir maha bob chintamani so sriradhaya
to taste what she is tasting also
swadhya yenal bhutta and third baba
not
so first he gives three reasons why
he's why she why he's taken her form
so again that is through damadar an early versus
foundational slokas of sri caitanya charitamritam
and it has
adaitaita he has shown himself that he is very
devoted to advaita krishna or in this case
advaita acharya prabhu he is very favored
to him by his request he had to come here
advaita charger with gangajal and the tulsi leaf
why because he knows one tulsi is so uh powerful
that krishna has to give himself if it's offered
with genuine love and affection the heart of a
duet charger can bring krishna down so then we
have thanks to advaita charges and we have thanks
to tulsi devi antuganga davey as we do every day
prapana srivaso and he showed himself
as surrendered at the holy lotus feet
of srivas again he's always giving too
remember he said krishna here who is
sri vasa lakshmi pati narayan and because
srivas who re she resides where uh um and at
the same time the devotee srivas who was always
surrendered under his feet praphano srivaso
so that
so see here also how this is going from sroop
damodar to advaita to srivastak or to paramananda
and after that gajapati will come with
this srivastakur we know that he is
narada and so narada descended
as mahaprabhu krsna's mahaprabhu
sometimes taken to be sadashiva
who is sometimes
associated with um and say i swear
by kunta majesty the majestic aspect of divinity
so and here we're hearing the glories of damadar
as well so in puri at the after the ratyatra
few days then come the hero punch of me
and and the past times where lakshmi davies um
servitors are abusing the servitors of juggernauts
because there's krishna
jagannath is dwarka krishna
and he has told the goddess of fortune
that he will go visit his hometown
for a few days and don't be suspicious of anything
because i'm taking my brother and sister with me
as they hear the queens of dorica they hear rohini
from vrndavan talk about vrndavan pastimes
and so they hear sometimes of krishna's
teenage sweetheart so now he's saying he
wants to go to his hometown for some time
but tell him not to worry uh brother and you
know sister are accompanying me balabadra and
and after a few days
she thinks about it a little more
carefully and so she goes to retrieve him and
we're told she comes on a palloquine surround
with singers and dancers and so many servitors
and she's dressed in all of her vaikuntha majesty
i swarja
and and this is due to being uh slighted
appearing to have been neglected
right and demanding the presence of jagannath
and when zhang and a serviture say
you know he can't come right now
your call is important
but he can't come right now and uh
the servitors of lexington navy start
abusing beating the servicers of juggernauts
calling them offensive names and language and
and at that time we're told mahaprabhu and his
devotees are observing this and they're giggling
to see these things and it's at that
time that mahaprabhu himself is like
what's going on here we've heard sometimes if the
beloved girl perceives that she's being slighted
in some way or neglect then she neglects herself
doesn't dress so nicely as very morose but here
she's dressed and all vicunta majesty and
being carried on a pelican and a parade a
person you know what kind of um mood what kind of
heart is being expressed here and sroop damodar
at mahaprabhu's request he starts describing
all the different types of gopis and their
different moods and things and we can't discuss
that but it's there for pariah continuous
reading within sri caitanya charitamritam
rasa vishesh given by swoop damodar at the
request of mahaprabhu but toward the end
srivas takur who remember
is narada and he's he wants
you could say that the real internal sentiments
or feelings of damadar will be expressed
so he prods him by saying look at the
opulence of the goddess of fortune
unparalleled nothing can compare to this
we're saying you know atula incomparable
what can compare and what do the gopis have
they're cowgirls they're not vaikunta you know
queens of dwarka or lakshmi's away they're they're
gopis they're cowgirls and what is their wealth
milk they milk cows um they live in a
village lots of trees flowers you know river
they live next to the river with
the trees and they milk the cows
how can that possibly compare to the majestic
i swarja opulence of the goddess of fortune
and hearing that so she he's prodding swoop
down and mahaprabhu warns him saying oh srivas
don't you know that's a shuddha bridge bhasi
i uh aishwarya is not opulence is not a word in
his dictionary and so be careful what you say
around him you might get him excited and say no
it's not that i don't understand what opulence is
i think srivas you're maybe experiencing temporary
insanity like you've forgotten did you oh
get him a copy of the brahma sangitan the krishna
karna do you know mahaprabhu brought these books
back from south india they have unparalleled
revelation within them if you'll go through them
like here's a verse from the brahma sangeeta shri
about that krishna world with those gopi girls
sriya you're talking about sri lanka sriya
khan takanta parama purusha kalpatarovo
the these like these gopis are lakshmi they're
goddesses of fortune as well but what are they
out there those trees in that rural village-like
environment they're called pavriksha trees
they're wish fulfilling that when what are those
wishes for all desires for seva they're supplying
bumis bumi cintamini gonomi toyam
amritam and the soil of that land
is made out of chintamini chanthamune copper
rickshaw lakshava taiju surabiyabi paliyantam
lakshmi sahasra satya sambram so and all the
water there toyama amratam the river you speak of
their nectar toyam amritam and all speech there is
all movement is dance
and there is krsna priya bangsi
with his dear friend the flute
it is the supreme relishable abode and if you look
in the other book which i'll give you a copy of
gem now if you take uh the uh some total
with all the majestic aspect of by kunta and
which is the unlimited bike underworld and waraqah
right and you take all of that and condense it
right it will uh that the entire vaikuntha
world and dwark and all of that can be
condensed into one particle of
the soil of goloka vrindavan
this is way beyond the
contraction of time and space
contraction expansion of time is way beyond that
the vite that's in this one the vaikuntha world
and the all of that you can put in one part of the
soil of loka vendava which is comprised of what
chintamini these chantaminy gems so one chantamini
jam possesses more opulence than the combined by
kunta's dwarka everything one chintamanijam
and what do we find in krishna karnamrtam
chintamani's bhushanam angananam that the
braja gopis are stringing cintamony gems
and making anklets that they
wear on their holy lotus feet
what say you srivas that was free was
dancing and ecstasy that's what he
wanted to hear but he had to prod
tease rupe damadar to make
it come out chintamani is
you know how much opulence is
there in that divine domain
my
foreign
hey
foreign foreign
foreign
i
tanjaya prabhu russia vijaya krishna prabhu uk
tungarasadi odariya lila didi kalyanidi usa
little sunnar prabhukiv tapananin tapanandini
ukraine um
devotees and all fortunate viewers
and her wonderful wednesdays she has wonderful
wednesday program in china there you go
and happy birthday to you
um she established the temple of mahaprabhu in
the heart of silicon valley mahavir maharaja
i think that's everyone all right yes and lila
shakti from brazil oh leela shakti didi and brazil
leela sundaru dandalat and guru chandra does
thank you