Kṛṣṇa consciousness
is all about
the ultimate loving affectionate
familiy relationship.
That’s what it is.
Everything else pales in comparison,
is a perverted reflection of that.
[Affection ad Infinitum]
If a child in this world
(we see little cute children),
sometimes they are
just irresistibly cute—
you can’t take
your eyes off them,
they make you smile.
How cute do you think
Kṛṣṇa is, when He is a baby
or a toddler
crawling around?
As cute as the cutest child here
or infinitely more cute, sweet,
irresistible, and eye-capturing?
I saw a man on the train
when I was going
from New Jersey to JFK,
and this man was on the train
with his little daughter,
she is like four years old,
maybe
and there was another man
who never met them before.
He was totally enamoured
by the cuteness
of this four-year-old girl
and practically offering himself
as her slave
after knowing her
for five minutes.
If that’s possible
in this world
do you think
it might be possible
a similar thing with Kṛṣṇa
or the same thing
magnified ad infinitum?
kandarpa-koṭi-kamanīya-viśeṣa-śobhaṁ
[Bs: 5.30]
Ten million times.
Why only ten million?
Because our brain
doesn’t work after that.
That’s why they
are writing the word ‘infinity’
or up to this point, then ‘tcht!’.
Then the rest means …
We can’t go: achintya;
kāmārbuda—
rasoddāmā kāmārbuda-madhura-dhāmojjvala-tanur
[Śrī Chaianyāṣṭakam: 4]
These sort of descriptions
were given.
So, understand this principle—
whatever you could see
or have experienced in family life,
then understand,
don’t deny it,
embrace it and understand:
“Oh, so this sort of feeling,
sentiment magnified ad infinitum
starts approaching
Kṛṣṇa conception.
And as my … our good fortune
to come in connection
with lotus feet
of guru and Vaiṣṇav
who are leading us by the hand
in that direction.”