Shridhar Swami’s commentary
differed from
what was given previously,
and people were wondering
whether or not it was authentic
[Agent of the Infinite]
and legitimate,
and should be accepted.
And they submitted
to the Bharadwaj deity of Mahadev Śiva.
And they say, “This mantra came
reverberating from the temple,
where Śiva says, ‘I know
the meaning of Bhagavatam,
Śukadev knows the meaning
of Bhagavatam,
and Vyas, he may know
and may not know.’”
How is that possible?
Vyas is the author!
This is a very critical point.
What’s coming down
and passing through the agent
may exceed the capacity of the agent,
that’s also possible.
This was Mahabrabhu’s response
to Sanatana Goswami,
when he was praising Mahaprabhu,
“You’ve given ...
Formerly, when You’ve met with Sarvabhauma,
he gave 9 explanation of atmarama,
then You gave twice as many—18.
That’s 27.
But now You’ve given 60, not touching
any of 27 given previously.
This is beyond human, it’s beyond
human capacity, it's Divine.”
And Mahaprabhu is responding,
“Oh Sanatana, don’t you know,
one letter of Srimad-Bhagavatam
is infinite.
A drop of the Infinite is infinite.
So what is 60 explanations,
why only?”
Then He said, “And actually, by your
association and your necessity
I feel another meaning
awakening within Me.”
And He gave the 61st explanation.
That’s when He was saying,
“By your necessity
I feel another meaning
awakening within Me.
And what’s passing through Me
I may not understand at all.
But what I can understand is that
Krishna wants to grace you through Me,
that much I’m certain of.
But what’s passing
through Me may be beyond ...
maybe I understand,
maybe I don’t understand.”
That is the nature
of Divine revelation.
So the devotees are offering
themselves as agents.
Just as in the Bhagavad-gita,
nimitta-mātraḿ bhava savya-sācin
[Bg: 11.33]
And Arjuna offers himself
as Kṛṣṇa’s agent.