We’re addicted to …
because we live in the world
of time and space
and measurement,
we’re always
measuring things—
this is that far from here,
and Thailand is this far
from India or Russia.
[“A Map of Reality”]
We think like that, so we hear,
“Oh, Ayodhyā’s here,
and Vaikuṇṭha’s over there,
and Goloka ….”
We can’t think of it
in terms of time and space;
we need to think of it
in terms of conscious development
and dedicating conscious tendency—
that’s what separates spiritual regions
from one another:
a conscious development
of dedicating tendency,
not some topographical,
cartographic type representation of it
which an artist is likely to do
if they make a painting—
you know, put Goloka here,
and then the Vaikuṇṭha world,
and then …, like that.
But we’re told,
chintāmaṇiś charaṇa-bhūṣaṇam aṅganānāṁ:
the whole Vaikuṇṭha world is accommodated
in an atom of Goloka.
So you have to really change
your thinking about that,
which means to come under the influence
of revealed truth;
give way to the time,
space, measurement,
consideration that we have
of the limited world.
If we’re going to discuss
the unlimited world,
that needs to be suppressed,
therefore it’s called
the adhokṣaja realm.
There are those who think that
by suppressing sense experience
you’ll experience the higher;
that can only take you to a generic,
neutral position.
But when the higher plane comes down,
then, adhokṣaja:
automatically
the lower experience
is suppressed
in the presence of that,
so there’s total immersion
in that domain.