Then śrama eva hi kevalam[SB: 1.2.8]
As Prabhupād liked to say,
“Then your life
is a useless waste of time.”
[Karma | Past Lives]
Then all you’re doing
is accumulating karma
and suffering or enjoying—
the reactions of karma.
You’re on the Ferris wheel.
By accumulated sukriti
(pious activities)
you’re going to a higher position,
heavenly planets.
Exhausting all your enjoyment credits,
gradually descending into lower species,
going up again …
over and over again.
ā-brahma-bhuvanāl lokāḥ
punar āvartino ’rjuna
mām upetya tu kaunteya
punar janma na vidyate
[Bg: 8.16]
I forget … (don’t) get the last line.
punar janma na vidyate? No …
Anyway, it’s mentioned in the Gita
by Kṛṣṇa to Arjun, He is saying,
“Even Brahmā on Brahmā-loka …”
And it says in the Bhāgavatam,
ā-viriñcyād amaṅgalam.
Viriñci means Brahmā.
Amaṅgalam—there’s a certain amount
of inauspiciousness in his position.
It’s given as an example
of karma-miśra-bhakti
in the B􏰄ṛhad-bhāgavatām􏰄ṛta
sequence.
So, sometimes it is even said
the first birth is as Brahmā,
then descending from there.
How is that possible?
How is it possible for Indra,
the King of heaven, to become a pig?
When a New Age ramblings …
they always like to talk about,
especially the women.
She—“They said, ‘I was a princess
or a queen in my last life.’”
So everyone can
[remember] …
That sounds really romantic—
you were once a queen
or a king, or a princess …
But they never tell you,
“You were once in the body
of a stool-eating pig.”
Because that won’t sell the same amount
of books or Tarot cards.
But Indra, how embarrassing
for the King of heaven
to be … to devolve
into the body of a pig,
and with all the trappings,
surroundings of pig life
with a pig wife,
little piglets.
And Brahma and the other gods,
they are very embarrassed
to see one of their own,
executive officer-jīva
to descend to such
an abominable position.
So they are trying to …
Who—maybe is Nārada,
I forget who,
but trying to bring him
to his senses,
and he’s very …
he’s guarding his pig wife
and piglets,
and his pig sty.
I mean,
“He worked for this!
[Laughing]
He built that sty!”
And so one by one
they start throwing the piglets
into the pond
and drowning them,
and he and his wife were thinking,
“What kind of a cruel man is this?!”
And each piglet that dies, they resume
their position as a devatā in heaven.
And they are all watching
this on a big screen in heaven.
The equivalent of a big screen,
[Laughing] and Indra …
Finally it’s just him and his wife.
Then they kill his wife,
then finally his pig body
is given up,
and then he resumes his position
in heaven Indra.
And he can see the replay
on the big screen of what happened,
and they’re saying to him,
“Would you like
to go back to that?”—No!
Now he’s come to his senses,
his higher self has kicked in,
and he can understand
how he degraded.
It’s with experience,
by practical experience we know that—
it’s difficult to improve,
to upgrade,
but you can become degraded
in 15 minutes.
It’s amazing how quickly
degradation sets in.
As one of the great writers,
perhaps Hemingway,
in a description
said of someone,
“At first things started to fall
apart gradually, then all at once.”
So, asat-saṅga-tyāga,—ei vaiṣṇava-ācāra
[Cc: 2.22.87]
One of the first symptoms of the serious
pursuit of Vaishnavism in earnest
is asat-saṅga-tyāga—to give up
bad association, mundane association.
Or those who are addicted …
associating with those
who are addicted to the mundane.