Guru Mahārāj says,
“Subjective evolution
parallels objective evolution.”
Meaning, and it’s similar to
sāṅkhya as described
in the Third Canto of Śrīmad Bhāgavatam,
there is Kapila’s sāṅkhya,
the theist Kapila,
[and] the atheist Kapila.
They’re both analyzing life, the elements,
the Universe—all these things.
[Soul Driven Evolution]
But we’re told sometimes,
“What’s the difference?”
One—twenty four divisions
of twenty five,
what’s the twenty fifths?
The soul, ātma.
That the soul is what’s driving
all of this.
So the soul is driving
objective evolution.
So we can say, in the subjective
evolution of consciousness
that the soul is evolving
from lowest species,
finished with that body,
terms of karmic imprisonment,
punishment, reaction …
to say …
expressing the reactions
of karmic activity,
but another word meaning
to finish with them …
Anyway, so the soul evolving
jala-jā nava-lakṣāṇi sthāvarā
[Viṣṇu Purāṇa]
from aquatics to plants,
to insects, birds, beasts,
at last to the human species.
So, some interpreters are saying,
“The athāto—
now, that you’ve achieved
human life,
now that you can understand
what I am saying,
now that you can hear
what I am trying
to convey to you,
now that you can conceive
such things properly,
now that you’re
conscience being
whose not only aware
of your existence,
but of а particular inner
necessity you have.”