Sometimes we went
with Gurudev
invited to somebody’s house
for dinner.
So Saraswatī Ṭhākur, that’s also there,
but, you know,
Gauḍīya Maṭh gṛhasthas.
I’ve met some of them,
they’re like out of the pages
of Charitamrita purports.
[Chaste Family Man]
People with full temples
in their house,
Deities, four, five āratis
every day,
they only take prasādam,
they do, they have a whole program
going on in their house.
Like gṛhastha Vaiṣṇava,
even sometimes they’re called
gṛhastha brahmachārīs.
Yeah, which I told about earlier.
When Kṛṣṇa Kṣetra Prabhu
who in Romania,
sometimes we would visit
with this one Indian professor
who was teaching Hindi,
and through him
we could have access to his students,
teach Bhagavad-gītā, give classes, whatever.
But we’d cook at his house,
and he was very happy,
I mean, his wife and family
were back in India,
and we’d show up,
and he’d get all excited.
We’d cook some things for lunch,
and he showed how to make parathas.
And there are different ways
to make them.
I should show this to Vishakha
because it’s, like, another way
where they end up looking
like a diamond‒shape or pyramid.
But ’cause when you take a circle
fold it in half,
and again it ends up
being like that,
but there are a few things
you do along the way.
Anyway, he would do this,
so he’d make his part and our,
and he was really happy
to get some association and everything.
And we were in saffron dress
as brahmachārīs,
and he could probably
pick up some attitude from us,
like, “we’re brahmachārīs”,
and he’s a gṛhastha,
or something like that.
So, he wanted to let us know,
like, I know something
about brahmachārya too,
maybe more than you, boys.
So he was saying,
“My wife lives in India,
and I see her once a year.”
—Uh, yeah?
And he said, “Also I’ve had three children,
and I’ve never seen my wife naked.”
At that point, you know,
it’s just like, “Oh, bub!”
It’s like,
“How do you process that?”
I don’t, I mean, I’m not trying
to put these images in your mind.
[Laughing]
But he said, “I’ve had three
children …” and I believed him,
he said, “I’ve had three children,
I’ve never seen my wife naked.”
We were just like, “Will you allow us
to dress like this in your presence?”
[Laughing]
He means to say,
“I did this dharm …,
Bhagavad-gītā again:
dharmāviruddho kāmo ’smi
[Bg: 7.11.3-4]
and that’s,
and he was for real.