If we say svarūp-siddhi,
vastu-siddhi.
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj answered
this question once.
Sometimes we hear examples
of someone
who is in a very high stage
of spiritual evolution,
and then they fall
from that position.
[Reincarnation of a Saint]
Jaḍ Bhārat
is mentioned sometimes,
who was at bhāva bhakti,
at this stage,
and then a mother deer
had a miscarriage,
with a little baby deer;
the mother died and
the little baby deer was in the stream
in his ashram in the forest.
So he has no attachment
in the world,
he’s in this high stage
of spiritual evolution,
but he sees the little
helpless fawn (baby deer)
and he’s senses,
he’s not heartless,
people who are evolved spiritually
are not heartless or insensitive,
they are actually
para duka duki,
they are attentive
to the suffering of others.
But they know the root cause
of all suffering is separation from Kṛṣṇa,
whether it’s material suffering
or spiritual suffering.
The root cause of all suffering
is separation from Kṛṣṇa.
At any rate, he takes
that little baby fawn into his ashram,
and every day the fawn is …
a cute little deer
and he develops
some attachment for it.
And he ends up leaving the world,
giving up this life
with some attachment
to this little deer,
and in his next life
he becomes a deer.
But he is a deer like,
this is Christmas Eve,
and we are told,
they never let poor Rudolph
join in any reindeer games.
[Laughing]
When Jaḍ Bhārat was a deer,
he was not interested
in any reindeer games.
He wasn’t seeking to admit …
we are told like,
he was this deer—
he liked to hear sādhus,
do Hari-kathā,
with his deer head
he’s going like aććhā;
he likes that,
he takes remnants of Vaiṣṇavas …
he was a very serious deer.
So, the point being
that Guru Mahārāj said,
when this is giving us
an example,
first delineate:
svarūp-siddhi, vastu-siddhi.
That Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur says,
“From svarūp-siddhi,
some deviation …
it’s possible to fall,
deviation is still possible.”
What does svarūp-siddhi mean?
It means when someone
reaches the stage
of awareness of their svarūp,
but not yet posted.
And Guru Mahārāj’s example:
“Someone may have qualified
to become a High Court judge—
passed the test, got the stamp
of everything’s approved,
but not yet sitting in the court
and judging.”
That’s vastu-siddhi—
he’s posted.
Svarūp-siddhi—qualified,
but not yet posted.
And we are told,
as inconceivable as it may sound,
between that awareness
of qualification
and qualification
and being posted,
in that interim state
that deviation is possible,
and it’s possible to fall
from that position.