There are many possibilities,
but at all cost we want
to avoid thinking offensively
about Vaiṣṇavas
of the least adhikār;
what to speak of
to the highest position.
Because in the case
of the highest position
that’s suicidal.
[Progressive Vision]
But Śrīla Guru Mahārāj,
he would remind us,
he said,
“Even a new person
we should show respect to,”
he said, “because first of all
now they’re connected
to what we say
is the highest thing,
and the most wonderful thing,
and the most divine thing.
Now they’re connected to it.
They’re appreciating it,
they have their connection.
And”, he added,
he said,
“God willing,
I may be going slowly,
and they’re going
very rapidly.
So it’s not inconceivable
that they could surpass me,
and I would be
in a position in the future
to receive grace
from them.”
Of course,
hearing such an explanation
we’ll understand—
this is the vision
of a mahā-bhāgavata.
So, who’s the most exalted,
he’s saying,
“Even a new person
we should show respect to.”
That’s Guru Mahārāj’s position.
And just to add to that
he’s repeatedly saying,
“I am a student,
not a finished professor
knowing anything
and everything.”
He said,
“The student.”
And that’s the best position
to be in is a student.
Forever a student.
He said, “Why?
Because a student
can make mistakes,
a student can learn more—
it’s a progressive position.”
Whereas when you’re cornered
in the ‘finished professor’
knowing anything and everything,
never makes a mistake,
everything they say, do, etc.
is perfect.
He said,
“That is a static position,
you can only
go down from there,
whereas the student
can make progress.”