Radha-mukunda-pada-sambhava-gharma-bindu
nirmanchanopakarani-krta-deha-laksam
uttunga-sauhrda-visesa-vasat pragalbham
devim gunaih sulalitam lalitam namami
[Śrī Lalitā-aṣṭakam, verse 1]
[Service Magnitude]
In the Lalitā-astakam,
Rūpa Gosvāmī’s identifying unique
trades, characteristics,
qualities of Lalitā-sakhī,
he has the Rādhā-aṣṭakam,
where he’s describing
identifiable trades characteristics
of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī,
here of Lalitā-sakhī.
And what is he signified
as important that She possesses
the greatest magnitude of eagerness
for the list aspect of sevā,
and Her idea is ‘no disturbance
will enter that plane’,
just as in Mahāprabhu’s pastimes.
Svarūp Dāmodar,
everything must pass
the Svarūp Dāmodar test,
so no matter
how well intentioned
when that one brāhmaṇ devotee,
he writes some śloka
in praise of Jagannāth
and Mahāprabhu.
And devotees are thinking
it’s very nice, the general group,
what he has written is very nice,
please you hear this.
Bhagavat Ācārya
tells Svarūp Dāmodar,
“You please hear this,
this composition.”
And when Svarūp Dāmodar
hears it
he is furious, he is the filter
before things go to Mahāprabhu,
and this is interesting as well—
although Mahāprabhu is described
the mahā-vadānyāya avatāre—
the most munificent, magnanimous avatar,
incarnation of Lord;
so generous,
so merciful to the fallen
but He cannot tolerate
apa-siddhānta.
He’s merciful to everyone,
He is descended
patita-pāvana gaura‒hari,
but if He hears apa-siddhānta—
means the improper representation
of Kṛṣṇa consciousness,
He’ll become angry,
it will disturb His mood
and He’ll be angry.
So who’s so generous, so sweet,
and kind, and affectionate …
This will make Him angry?
So it means not to meddle
in the upper world
with the higher things.
It’s more critical
in the lower stage.
Prabhupād’s example was that
like the child with its feet
on the lap of the mother.
It’s offensive to put your feet
on someone,
but if a mother is holding
a little baby
and the baby’s feet
are walking on the mother,
that is not offensive, it’s OK,
but we see even in this world
as the children start to grow
they get less lap time
and inevitably at a certain stage
they won’t be touching their mother,
their father, their affectionate
well wishers with their feet.
It will be intolerable,
and it won’t be good for them
to continue that way.
So Svarūp Dāmodar
tells that, “Mind it.
You are trying to glorify
Mahāprabhu and Jagannāth
and in the process
you’re going to hell,
because you’re committing aparādh
against both of them,
because what you are expressing
it hasn’t descended
from the higher plane
using you as an agent
for expression and distribution,
but rather on the bases
of your perspective, observations
you are imposing that
on the higher and that’s an offense.
And that man is mortified,
but Svarūp Dāmodar
ever so qualified says,
“But, if we take the go deeper
and take
other meanings of this words …”
Then he mercifully converts
what was aparādhic in expression
into a glorification.
That’s part of the qualifications
of Svarūp Dāmodar.
But interestingly whether
in the role of Svarūp Dāmodar
or Lalitā-sakhī, not allowing
any disturbance to go.
And thematically, in principle,
what are we learnt?
—Not allowing any disturbance
to go into the upper world,
the higher world.
As Śrīla Gurudev,
he had such an arrangement
with Śrīla Guru Mahārāj.
Guru Mahārāj is on his veranda
in Nabadwip
and Gurudev moving
on the ground level at the Math,
conducting all the seva,
to not allow any disturbance
to go to Śrīla Guru Mahārāj.
So that Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
can compose the “Prema Dhama Deva Stotram”,
conceive of “The Subjective Evolution
of Consciousness”,
and “The Golden Volcano of Divine Love”,
and so many other things
that’s Gurudev took the anxiety
and whatever inconvenience
was associated with that sevā,
upon himself.
So that Guru Mahārāj
could proceed with his divine thinking
and in that sense
direct bhajan seva there.