In the Gītā we know,
so it’s mentioned,
what’s material life
comparable to
and the suffering
of material existence—
seasonal changes.
[God | Friend or Enemy]
What is our normal
response to that?
We have to tolerate it.
Like, we are in this room
right now, it’s hot.
We have to tolerate it.
Outside it’s hot
or we hear it’s going to rain—
we take an umbrella.
We factor it in,
it’s part of life.
So He’s telling Arjuna
in Bhagavad-gītā,
when you’re overwhelmed
by life circumstances,
the karmic situation
that you’ve created,
tāṁs titikṣasva bhārata—
[Bg: 2.14]
tolerate it, Arjuna.
So that just to say here.
So first He’s making this, says,
and drawing a parallel,
Gītā’s message—
tolerate these circumstances.
The Bhāgavatam saying,
su-samīkṣamāṇo [SB: 10.14.8],
but if you read it more deeply—
not only tolerate it,
you can embrace it
as something good.
Like, sometimes
I give the example of jiu-jitsu,
the Japanese jiu-jitsu.
The idea is the opponent is coming
with full force, and what you do?
You take them and guide them
in a particular direction.
You take advantage
of that opposition, of the negativity.
So, you think there is a way
to deal with karmic circumstances
on a deep level reading.
You can see it like that,
and so you’ll think,
“Oh …”
And, excuse me,
in the background—
suhṛdaṁ sarva-bhūtānāṁ
[Bg: 5.29]
and this is where
you get to your part deeper,
if we think, connect this to,
“Well, I’m tolerating.”
But we go deeper
in Bhagavad-gītā.
He is saying,
suhṛdaṁ sarva-bhūtānāṁ.
He is my friend, who
bhoktāraṁ yajña-tapasāṁ
sarva-loka-maheśvaram—
[Bg: 5.29]
that’s Sanskrit for ‘not a blade of grass
moves without a will of God’,
it’s for His pleasure.
So we think, “That person, for whom
everything is meant to please Him,
is He antagonistic towards me
or friendly to me?”
And really if we think of God
as being antagonistic to us,
I mean, would He really be like,
just like some mean guy?
I remember seeing
a bumper sticker in Santa Cruz,
at the back of the corner
said, “Mean people rule”.
[Laughing]
So we think like, so, God,
which we sometimes get
from a Judeo-Christian saying, like,
“Obey Me, lest I smite thee
from the face of the Earth,
I’m an angry, jealous God!”—
this kind of stuff.
So, really, He has nothing better to do
than just be mean to people.
It’s so, I mean,
it would be funny,
I mean, that it’s humorous,
if it wasn’t pathetic.
As Guru Mahārāj told, and I saw
what he said of visual on YouTube,
where a baby elephant’s trapped
in the mud, and it’s going to die—
he can’t get out, he didn’t have
the skills sets for … the wherewithal to get out,
and then you see
the mother come over
and, like, pull the baby elephant
out of the mud.
So Guru Majārāj’s just saying,
“If we can witness this,
like an elephant has
this much love and affection
for their child,
God would be something less
than that?”
Or more? Or equal, or more?
I mean, it sounds silly.
An elephant is that kind,
but God,
pitāham asya jagato
mātā dhātā pitāmahaḥ
[Bg: 9.17]
who created everyone,
who’s their ultimate mother,
father, everything,
is less affectionate
than an elephant, than an animal?
It just can’t be.
So, then, we’re back to that
suhṛdaṁ sarva-bhūtānāṁ—
the person who’s behind
controlling everything
is friendly to us.
So, these circumstances
that I’m tolerating,
actually, if I look at them
more deeply,
they’re friendly to me,
it’s in my interest.
Like the … Sometimes you see
a guardian of a child,
whether their parent
or just a guardian.
From our point of view
they’re dealing with the child unfairly.
We think they are being cruel,
mean or unfair.
I mean, sometimes
that may be true,
but let’s just say
in this example, it’s not.
And I’ve seen with my own eyes
like on a tram in San Francisco
some woman dealing with the child,
who was really misbehaving,
but then some people got on
after the misbehaviour,
they didn’t see that,
they just saw the mother,
like, dealing with the child,
they are like trying
to correct the mother,
but they didn’t see all the things
that happened before.
So it’s something like that.
And Guru Mahārāj’s saying,
“If we’re in denial—
we deny the responsibility
for our karmic circumstances:
we’re blaming other people,
environmental conditions,
historical positioning
whatever it is,
if we’re casting blame
outward,”
he said, “then you’re going to be
in this world a long time.
Whereas if you take responsibility
for your karmic circumstances,
and say, ‘I’m alone responsible
for the positions I find myself in’”,
he said, “then your days here
are numbered.”
It’s just like the child
who’s denying any wrong doing,
they get the punishment.
Whereas the child who presents
themselves to the mother and says,
“I did wrong,
and I’m really sorry, and …”,
they don’t need to be punished,
because they’ve acknowledged
their culpability,
their responsibility.