We know that devotees
at the time of initiation
they very much like to hear
the meaning of their name.
[What’s in a Name?]
They are very eager
to hear that.
And even Guru Mahārāj
asked Saraswatī T􏰅hākur.
His name was
Ramendra Chandra Bhaṭṭācārya;
he got initiated, and his name became
Ramendra Sundar.
And he said,
“How shall I …
What that Ramendra
here means?”
And Saraswatī Т̣hākur
began to explain,
“Rāma, Hare Rāma,
that Rāma
is not Rāmacandra
or Balarāma, but
Rādhā–Raman,
Raman–Rādhā—
the lover of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī,
when He is giving joy
and happiness
to Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī
in divine pastimes.”
And Guru Mahārāj said,
“And that sound
is still ringing in my ear.”
So even he asked.
But Śrīla Gurudev,
he didn’t like
devotees to ask.
[Laughing]
It’s just one
of those things. [Laughing]
And sometimes
he would say
if they say,
“What is my name?”,
He’d say,
“What was your
Christian name?
Do you know
what that means?”
So once this boy
from Australia,
who is an excellent craftsman,
he made all those tables
in the Theistic Media Center
at the Sevak Bhavan;
Madhuranan, he was sitting
on the Veranda once,
and,
[in a deep voice]
“Śrīla Govinda Mahārāj,
Śrīla Gurudev?”
Gurudev, “Yes?”
[in a deep voice]
“Can I ask you a question?”
[Laughing]
Gurudev goes like, “Yes”,
and he goes,
“What does
Hare Kṛṣṇa mean?”
Gurudev put
his newspaper down
and said,
“What was your name before?”
He said,
[sternly] “Matthew.”
Gurudev,
“What does Matthew mean?”
[sternly],
“Messenger of God.”
Gurudev said,
“Oh, alright,”
and folded
the newspaper and …
[Laughing]
Because usually he’d say,
“What does that mean?”
and they don’t know
what their name means.
But he said, [sternly]
“Messenger of God.”
[Laughing]
Then he said,
“Alright …”
And he started explaining
something about mahā-mantra.
And I should say, on one level
we are forbidden
from going into the detailed
explanations of that,
and we can say
we don’t even know them.
But this type of analysis …
But what you have there,
what you’ve read there,
that sort of general indication
is what’s given to us.
So sometimes
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj,
Śrīla Swāmī Mahārāj
as well
would point out,
‘Hare’ is in the vocative case,
which means,
in Guru Maharāj’s words,
“No plea
is to be attached to this.”
We are not chanting
for something.
People have
that idea sometimes,
that you will chant the mantra
to get something.
So that was
Guru Mahārāj’s expression,
“No plea is to be attached.
Just invoking ‘Hare—
Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī and Kṛṣṇa.’”
But … And Śrīla Prabhupād
(Swāmī Mahārāj)
when he gave
a general explanation too,
he said, “It’s like a prayer
to be engaged in service.”
So all of these things:
service, seva,
dās, dāsī,
Kṛṣṇa dās, Rādhā dāsī—
they have some general meaning
and some more specific meaning.
And Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
will say,
“According to the inner awakenment
of the devotee,
the aspiring servitor,
meaning is attached or revealed,
or things reveal
deeper sorts of meaning.”
But one thing
Guru Mahārāj said,
that’s really astonishing,
he said, “By chanting
Hare Kṛṣṇa mahā-mantra”,
he said,
“one day you will find
that you are in the harem
of Kṛṣṇa.”