Kṛṣṇa is living, growing,
developing, dynamic.
Nitya-nava-navāyamāna.
Nava-yauvana.
Nava-yauvanaṁ ca [Bs: 5.33]
[Krishna is Evergreen]
Always newer, always fresher.
Sometimes Guru Mahārāj
would say,
“Śyāmasundar means
‘eternally green; evergreen’.”
Because we were always saying,
“No, Śyāmasundara means blue …”,
but Guru Mahārāj said,
“Śyāmasundar means
evergreen. Kṛṣṇa’s evergreen.”
So he doesn’t mean the thing
like the green colour,
but evergreen, just always …
When we heard about
the evergreen tree, we say,
“Oh, these, some are green
and then they go brown,
but these are
always eternally green.
They’re forever green,
they’re evergreen.”
So Kṛṣṇa—like that.
premāñjana-cchurita-bhakti-vilocanena
santaḥ sadaiva hṛdayeṣu vilokayanti
yaṁ śyāmasundaram acintya-guṇa-svarūpaṁ
govindam ādi-puruṣaṁ tam ahaṁ bhajāmi
[Bs: 5.38]
Acintya-guṇa-svarūp;
His svarūp has acintya guṇas,
inconceivable qualities,
and the jīvas are His aṁśa.