Modest natural growth
is the advice of Śrīla Guru Mahārāj.
[KGB Double Agent | Allegiance]
All of what we’re hearing
Sādhu, Śāstra, Guru, Vaiṣṇava,
is making some impression
upon the heart.
We’ve been accepted
by Guru and Vaiṣṇava.
I remember contemplating going to
the temple in San Francisco and joining
—this is a few days before joining,
making that decision—
and I’m reading Bhagavad-gītā
and in one purport
Prabhupād’s quoting
the famous śloka of the Rāmāyaṇa
where Rāmachandra is saying,
“Once I accept someone
it’s forever.”
And once someone says,
“My dear Lord Kṛṣṇa,
please accept me”, it’s forever.
It comes when Vibhīṣaṇa, Rāvaṇa’s brother,
has switched sides;
he’s left Rāvaṇa and
he’s serving Rāmachandra,
but so many unusual things
are happening
that devotees are
becoming suspicious of him
and thinking he’s like
a classic KGB double agent.
I don’t now if Vibhīṣaṇa
was Russian or not.
But he understood this double agent,
or they thought.
So, some were telling Rāmachandra,
"Oust him.
He’s really an agent of the enemy.
Because too many mysterious things
are going against us."
And Rāmachandra said,
“No, you don’t understand.
Once I accept someone as mine,
that’s forever; that cannot be broken.”
So, being accepted by Kṛṣṇa
through His agents,
we may not be aware of the full implication
of all of these things,
but Guru Mahārāj says it’s the opinion of
Mahāprabhu and the higher Vaiṣṇavas
that once you’ve
—on any level, however remotely—
appreciated hearing about Kṛṣṇa
from a substantial agent,
that the flag has been planted
in the heart.
Ultimately that real conceptual seed,
it’s there.
It may become suppressed
from time to time,
but it will ultimately assert itself
being nourished
by Sādhu, Śāstra, Guru, and Vaiṣṇava,
and fully express itself and then
spread its influence all over the heart
and, as Guru Mahārāj says,
then tell all the fleeting desires,
“Anyābhilāṣitā-śūnyaṁ,
jñāna-karmādy-anāvṛtam” (Brs: 1.1.9);
to “Get out. This heart belongs
to me and me alone.”