Trivikram Maharaj: In Brazil there was
a very intense experience.
You know, I never more got that, like ...
You know, someone …
I’ve already read
Chaitanya-charitamrita,
and then you have, you know,
that was my feelings,
maybe, most probably,
I was tripping out,
but I mean, you know, “Someone from
Chaitanya-charitamrita is living there.”
[“Krishna, What’s Wrong with You?”]
Goswami Maharaj:
As Srila Gurudev. Yes, right.
(TM): Someone is coming
from Chaitanya-chairtamrita and manifesting.
(GM): That type of personality
has stepped out of the pages in your life.
(TM): Yes. And living there in
the ashram and doing his … lila.
(GM): It is true! It works.
(TM): That was the feeling.
And everybody had some feelings,
extraordinary feelings.
And then the boy fell.
That was the most …
(GM): Yes. Was not that the day
when you give everything?
Something happened.
Do you know, Lalita?
(GM): The baby, the boy
falls in the water and drowns.
Gurudev told me
that he said about you [Trivikram Maharaj]
“He has just given me everything,
everyone has come here in joyful celebration.”
And a little kid fell in a pond
and drowned.
Died. He is dead.
Like these little children we have here,
that’s why we should be careful.
(TM): Completely careful.
(GM): We are letting them play
and everything …
That child fell in a pond,
that is only this big,
and drowned.
So there is a dead child
laying there,
and Gurudev …
You will tell what he told,
but he told me, he said,
“I said to Kṛṣṇa,
‘What do I tell them now?
I don’t know what to say.
He just gave everything,
we are having a big celebration.
What am I supposed to tell them?
I do not know what to say.
Please tell me what to say.’”
And then Ananda …
(TM): Yes, Ananya Bhakti,
she took the charge,
because she is a dentist so she knows
all the first procedures.
(GM): First aid.
(TM): Yes.
Then she told the father.
I was taking prasadam
with the father;
the father was the guy
who gave me the first book.
Then she told him,
“You must give a massage to his heart,
and I will breathe. Then we do five times.”
You know, CPU or whatever …
(GM): CPR.
(TM): CPR.
Then after some time Rohini started
chanting the mantra with everybody
“Hare Kṛṣṇa, Hare Kṛṣṇa,
Kṛṣṇa Kṛṣṇa, Hare Hare …”
Then, after maybe four or five …
(GM): Minutes?
(TM): Breaths.
The boy starts vomitting the water,
coughing and putting the water out.
And then Gurudev told us …
At that time someone went to tell him,
and he said Gurudev was very silent
and then he prayed to the Lord,
“Why are you doing that?”
And then the boy came alive.
And Gurudev always said,
“Ananya Bhakti saved the boy.”
(GM): Right. He is not taking the credit.
Kṛṣṇa answered Gurudev’s prayer
is what happened.
And later at … What’s her name?
Cesar?
(TM): Neza Caesar.
(GM): Neza Cesar.
At her house,
that program that evening,
I see that boy again.
When Bhuvana showing me
how to put passion fruit
on chocolate icecream.
He loved to eat.
(TM): This is like his specialty.
(GM): And that kid is …
And they go,
“That’s the kid.”
(TM): No brain damage
after fifteen minutes drowned.
(GM): How old is he now?
(TM): Oh, he may be now …
(GM): Fifteen, seventeen years old,
totally normal.
It was a mi …
It’s what they call “A Miracle”.
But the miracle was Gurudev
not just going “Oh, my Lord.”
Not like that, saying,
“What’s wrong with you?!
Kṛṣṇa, what’s wrong with you?
He just gave everything,
we are having a big celebration,
what am I supposed to tell them now?
You tell me what would I do.”
Devotee can express
that kind of anger, loving anger,
Kṛṣṇa likes that that His devotee
can say something like that.
And then Kṛṣṇa says …
Balaram says [to Kṛṣṇa].
When they are all lying fainted
on the banks of Jamuna
He [Balaram] goes,
“These are not Ayodhya monkeys!
These are not Vaikuntha people!
These are Your beloved devotees
in Vrindavan!
Stop this play!
You are breaking their hearts!”
And then Kṛṣṇa
goes like “Alright”.
[Laughing]
And Viśvanāth says,
“Why does He do these things?
Because He is
bhava-grahi janardana,
He is a bhava-eater.”
And He knows, there is what’s regularly
going on in your heart,
that taste … it’s also nice,
but if He puts you
in great difficulty,
the heart will go
to its deepest place
and make an offering from there
that He can’t refuse.
That’s why He does it.
He is addicted to heart.
Hare Kṛṣṇa!