Сreation
is a secondary function
performed by a part of a part
of a part of His expansion,
with His eyes half-closed.
Like we say in this world
when people think they’re
[good at] something,
they go, “I can do that
with my eyes closed.”
“Yes, you can do that
with your eyes closed.”
[Kṛṣṇa Over Viṣṇu]
But it’s generally an expression,
“I can do this
with my eyes closed.”
You can do those kind of things
or maybe not.
Mahāviṣṇu generates
innumerable universes
out of His pores
with His eyes half-closed; half-asleep.
He’s lying in yoga-nidrā
with His eyes half-closed,
half-asleep,
and His glance is personified
as Śambhu Śiva,
full of the sum total of jīvas,
and they’re impregnated
in the material nature
while He’s doing this: [exhales]
So in His outward going breath,
a hundred and fifty-trillion years,
innumerable universes appear.
He can do it
with His eyes closed
while Kṛṣṇa’s playing with the gopas
and gopīs in Vṛndāvan.
That’s beauty over power.
There are many examples
of beauty over power:
Kṛṣṇa over Rāmachandra;
Kṛṣṇa over Viṣṇu.
The ultimate conception of
the ultimate reality is beauty,
and as Guru Mahārāj says,
“Beauty is the ultimate
controlling principle.”
So, Mahāviṣṇu steals that brāhmaṇ’s boy.
Why?
We find out in the Bhāgavatam.
He wants to see
the beauty of Kṛṣṇa.
How to get Kṛṣṇa to come?
He stole the boy
and He’s keeping him there.
… such a cruel thing to do.
And Kṛṣṇa and Arjuna go through
all the layers of the Universe
and then He says, “I just wanted
to see Your beauty, my Lord.”
Should we think Viṣṇu
is not beautiful?
Inconceivably beautiful.
But what was the śloka
of the day?
sarvādbhuta-chamatkāra-
līlā-kallola-vāridhiḥ
atulya-madhura-prema-
maṇḍita-priya-maṇḍalaḥ
trijagan-mānasākarṣi-
muralī-kala-kūjitaḥ (Cc: Madhya, 23.82-83).
Kūjitaḥ means
it sounds very beautiful.
Muralī, Kṛṣṇa’s flute.
Muralī-kala-kūjitaḥ
asamānordhva-rūpa-śrī:
No one equals His beauty,
not Viṣṇu, not Rāma,
not Dvārakā-Kṛṣṇa.
Dvārakā-Kṛṣṇa sees the picture
and says,
“I was so beautiful
when I was younger in Vṛndāvan.”
Like in this world.
My cousin, who’s my age,
she told my mom
—now I won’t say her age,
because somehow over the years
there are like
ten years separating us,
even though we were born
in the same year.
Anyway,
and my mom is ninety-three,
she doesn’t mind me
saying that.
My cousin said to her,
“Aunt Rose, let’s look at some pictures
when we used to look good,
when we used to be beautiful.”
So, Kṛṣṇa also has
a version of that.
He’s saying, “Oh, I was so beautiful
in Vṛndāvan.
Now these days,
maybe I put on a little weight
in Dvārakā.
It’s hard to say.”
Or He sees His own beauty
in a jewelled column and says,
“Who is so beautiful that now
I’m starting to feel
the same feelings as Rādhikā.”
So, even Kṛṣṇa is enamoured
by His own beauty,
asamānordhva-rūpa-śrī (Cc: Madhya, 2.23.82-83),
the rūpa. Rūpa means form,
and rūpa means beauty.
Rūpa śrī, śrī rūpa.