That the Ultimate Reality
is beautiful,
is reassuring, encouraging,
exciting …
I can’t think of the actual word
that I’m looking for.
[The Door to Theistic Culture]
Because we are accustomed
to hear of reality
and the Ultimate Reality,
and things like that,
and the scientists have tried
to make that their …
Everyone else’s dealing
in interpretation—
they’re dealing
in hard facts about things.
That the Ultimate Reality
is beautiful,
they could say,
“Yes, in its expression
or what we observe of it.”
There are what they called
‘the Elegant Universe’—
those kind of things.
But that’s not good,
that’s the least aspect
of its beauty.
That it can be beautiful the way
a person can be beautiful,
that their brains
cannot accommodate or digest.
The beauty of a look,
the beauty of emotional expression,
those things
cannot be denied.
The simple things
that we can do in this world
to deny that the Supreme Reality,
the Supreme Absolute Truth
can express such things,
is sad and pathetic.
That’s why when I was
on my flight from Beijing to New York,
and sitting next to me
is a computer scientist [who] teaches
postdoctoral computer science
to very advanced people, and I thought,
“Oh, this is an opportunity
to ask a series of questions.”
But I only needed to ask
one question,
which was,
and he agreed like,
“Yes, ask me
any question you like.”
So I said,
“As a hardcore
computer scientist,
the way you’ve been trained,
the way you teach …
Can you say
with absolute certainty,
that the Original Source
of all aroma or fragrance
has no olfactory capacity,
in other words, cannot smell?”
And he said,
“As you have worded this,
no, I cannot say
that with absolute certainty,
I cannot deny
that prospect or possibility.”
I said,
“That’s all I need to know
because now
you’ve opened the door
for the possibility
of theistic culture
and the concept
of the Personality of Godhead,
because we can make
a similar case for each sense:
can you say
with absolute certainty
that the Original Source
of all things to be seen
has no seeing capacity?
Seeing, smelling, hearing,
tasting, touching, etc.