Once someone was trying
to say that and explain,
when Gaudiya Math
was accused of promoting slavery,
[Dignity of the Human Race]
saying, “What is Kṛṣṇa das and dāsī—
‘slave girl’, ‘slave’, all slave?”
And not even directly the slave,
but slave of the slave.
[Laughing]
So the British say,
“And we are humanists,
we tried to eliminate
this sort of idea
hundreds of years ago
with the introduction of humanism.”
But Saraswati Ṭhākur’s response,
he said,
“No, Gaudiya Math stands
for the dignity of the human race.
To be the slave of Kṛṣṇa,
the servant of Kṛṣṇa,
that is not a low position.
That is a very high position.”
But sometimes
people shy away from that word.
They think,
“Servant has a nicer ring to it.”
Or they try and act
as apologists saying,
“No, that’s not what
he was saying.”
No, it is what he was saying.
I can show you 108 references
in the talks of Srīla Guru Mahārāj,
where he is using the word ‘slave’:
“Happy dancing slaves of Kṛṣṇa”,
“We are meant
to be the slaves of Kṛṣṇa”,
“Slavery is the only position
to approach Him”.
So then we all
get nervous and worried,
and think,
“Who can we tell this to?”
But we need to hear
the full picture.
ye yathā māṁ prapadyante
taṁs tathaiva bhajāmy aham
[Bg: 4.11]
This is why no less a word
than slavery can be used.
That sort of giving over;
Rūpa Goswāmī quotes Jīva [Goswāmī]
saying, “Like a sold animal.”
Like when Gurudev
offered himself to Guru Mahārāj
and said, “I’m your goat,
if it pleases you to cut off my tail,
you can do that.
Or you can slit my throat—
I’m your goat,
whatever you want
you can do with me.”
It’s not that conditionally ‘I am yours’;
unconditionally ‘I am yours’.
Why is this so important?
Because Kṛṣṇa is reciprocating
the devotion of the devotee.
So for those who offer themselves
as slaves to Kṛṣṇa,
Kṛṣṇa becomes their slave.
That’s what
He reciprocates with them.
That’s how bound He is by the love
and affection of the devotees.
So when the ladies,
the elderly gopīs in Vrindavan,
they tell Kṛṣṇa, “Dance, Gopāl, dance!
We want to see your dance.”
He starts dancing
to make them happy.
“Gopāl, hand me that!”
Sometimes He can … and then
He goes and brings them thing.
But sometimes they ask Him
to pick up something that’s too heavy.
So He just touches it, like that.
But sometimes He is showing,
“I am very strong”.
He is omnipotent,
the Supreme Reality,
but He is a plaything
in the hands of the Vraja-gopīs.
They make Him dance, sing
and play in different ways.
And happily He is their plaything,
their puppet.
So for those who offer themselves
as slave, abject slavery to Kṛṣṇa,
He reciprocates
by becoming their slave.
We give half-hearted approach—
half-hearted response.
But, so what would be the most intense
way you could offer yourself?
—Slave.
That’s the operative word.
And Guru Mahārāj said,
“And not even directly slave—
[Laughing]
slave of the slave of the slave”—
dāsa-dāsānudāsaḥ
gopī-bhartuḥ pada-kamalayor
[Cc: 2.13.80]