A lawyer in the cla—
you know,
like a stock photo of a lawyer ….
You’ll see the lawyer
at the desk
sitting in front of a wall
of law books,
[Living Scriptures]
and the idea being,
you approach this person
and they’re familiar
—intimately comprehensively familiar—
with what’s in
those books,
and they’re gonna extract
from those books
what is relevant to your case,
to your situation.
So, the revealed truth
is like that wall of books,
all these scriptures.
So the saints
are like living scriptures—
they understand substantially
what the content is,
and it’s not some sort
of passive substance;
it’s a passive posing
of a book,
but there’s
spiritually conscious substance
within the pages
of these books.
So we want
a living interpretation
through a living agent that’s relevant
to our life, the life we’re living.
Living truth, through a living agent,
that’s relevant to the life you’re living.
That, we want.
That is what we need.