Guru Maharaj expressed it like this once, he said:
"If we think of it as a current or a stream,
if you're standing on the bank of the Ganga
and you toss a flower into the Ganga,
it enters that current, and it's carried away.
So gradually, it's going further away from you.
[RealTime Current of Lila]
That means being situated in the realm of
time and space and limitation.
But if you run along the bank with the flower,
it remains in view."
So we can say that this is livestream,
realtime livestreaming lila.
That's what's in the Bhagavatam,
that's what's in the Charitamritam,
we sing it everyday, "rādhā-kṛṣṇa-nitya-līlā korilā prakāśa".
It's going on eternally.
But for someone who has the capacity,
they may enter the current of that stream,
in a real, livetime, meaningful way.
It's also part of the purpose of hearing,
hearing the pastimes of Krishna,
they're eternal and unlimited, so each time
we approach them, if we approach with a proper
serving mood, something new can come to us,
and they're extremely visual.
The pastimes of Krishna, they're filled
with all sort of visualizations;
Krishna, His devotees, the Vrindavan environment,
conveyed also is the mood of the servitors,
so the great Acharyas they have the capacity
to appreciate these things with the greatest depth.