oṁ ajñāna-timirāndhasya jñānāñjana-śalākayā
cakṣur unmīlitaṁ yena tasmai śrī-gurave namaḥ
It's all about seeing
and, in a sense, observation
Guru Maharaj said rishi... it's interesting word - the Sanskrit word for creation is shristi
has r/s in there, but s in the beginning. Sristi - like
srishti sthiti-pralaya-sadhana-saktir eka/ chayeva yasya bhuvanani bibharti durga
In "Brahma-samhita", talking about creation - but Guru Maharaj said
one of the meanings of word rishi... That's in "Gita": tad viddhi praṇipātena/ paripraśnena sevayā
upadekṣyanti te jñānaṁ/ jñāninas tattva-darśinaḥ
The tattva-darshi, darshis
darshan -  we think, O, darshan - that's when you go to see the Guru or the Vaishnava
and that's correct, but you'll see the
word use like "sat darshan"
in six different types of philosophies - but what does that mean - "sat darshan"?
darshan is "philosophy", means: perspective, ways of seeing
so Guru Maharaj said the rishis
they are seeing and experiencing the
Truth. And by the truth - remember
we always mean Krishna, a person - not the
truth in some abstract form
The Truth is Krishna. Krishna is the Truth. īśvaraḥ paramaḥ kṛṣṇaḥ/ sac-cid-ānanda-vigrahaḥ
There is no non-vigraha truth - really
so seeing some perspective
shanta dasya sakhya vatsalya madhura
svakiya parakiya - different ways, devotional a way of seeing
so that's - as a poet said - the deep heart's core and then it's coming out
in the form of the mantra, the scripture, the song, the hari-katha
so they're not authors in the conventional sense - or creators - like, you know, in the creative sense
even the leading American literary critic
Harold Bloom, he wrote a book called
one is "The Anatomy of Influence", the other one's "The Anxiety of Influence"
so what he's saying is these modern writers often, if not all the time
they try to present themselves as though
they're like mushrooms
they just sprung out of the soil of the muse, they're not under anyone's influence
they're just giving something original
and that's why they're so great and wonderful
but he says, To be inspired is
to be influenced and that's more... that we can support
tene brahma hṛdā in the Bhagavatam: the inspiration of Brahma is on account of divine influence
he's under divine influence and therefore there's inspiration
so all devotees will think like that
whenever someone is offering praise toward what they've expressed
they defer that praise to under whose influence they are
Guru...Saddhu, shastra, Guru, Vaishnav
which is... they're not just being humble - which they are, but they're telling the truth
and then people will mistakenly think
Oh, then, you know,  we don't get to offer
anything new -  it's always just repeating
something from the past or rote
recitation - no
like Rupa Goswami's: rasoddama kamarbuda-madhura-dhamojjvala-tanur
about Mahaprabhu and Chaitanya-astakam
then Guru Maharaj under the influence of Rupa Goswami
koṭi-kāma-mūrchchhitāṅghri-rūpa-rāsa-raṅgaraṁ
similar - same same, but different
so under his influence something has
sprung out
and, you can say - and I'm just saying this in a happy way that will please...
the Guru is pleased that the disciple like the parents are pleased if the child exceeds them
so, you can say, in a sense, like - what Guru Maharaj - he took that and made it even more
and maybe Rupa Goswami is pleased with that: under his influence something even
as wonderful or more wonderful was
expressed
he says: rasoddama kamarbuda-madhura-dhamojjvala-tanur
discussing the beauty and sweetness of Mahaprabhu that  rasoddama, rasa udama kamar, you know
billions of Cupids in full-blown
cupidity - and I'm re-purposing that word
that points toward the sweetness: madhura-dhamojjvala-tanur - of Mahaprabhu
so he's doing like that and
it's similar to Brahma-samhita
kandarpa-koti-kamaniya-visesa-sobham
but Guru Maharaj says in his verse
koṭi-kāma-mūrchchhitāṅghri-rūpa-rāsa-raṅgaraṁ
that 10 million Cupid's will faint to see the
beauty of Mahaprabhu
so he's taken this and expressed it in a
new way
but it's under the influence of Srila Rupa Goswami
so really to be inspired is to be influenced and that is a good thing
but those who lack humility cannot accept that
humility defined as the perceived proximity of greatness
of that which is greater than yourself
that floods the heart with genuine feelings
of humility
the perception of the proximity of greatness - that which is greater than you
and so can say: divinity the greater Vaishnavas, the scriptures - so many things
but there are cinmoy threads connecting all these things
so the rishis seeing, experiencing, expressing the truth under the influence of divine current
so, you know, they said that [there are] cinmoy threads that are connecting these things
so we know yesterday there was mention of the Chinese New Year and I like to say
the Year of the Boar. I'm comfortable
saying that
and that's why I kept thinking it was Varahadev's appearance day
but there has to be some connection - why
so many of these avatars appear on the calendar
their forms: Kurma, you know, Nrisimha - tiger-lion; Matsya
I said Kurma - and Varaha. And we may think: nānāvatāram akarod bhuvaneṣu
there's so many avatars, various avatars
it could be confusing, you know
so - as innumerable as the waves of the ocean - Vedavyas says in the beginning of the Bhagavatam
or maybe it was Saunaka Rishi, but - it's in the Bhagavatam
the different tellings and
saying: so then 24 are identified
but we know - Jayadeva Goswami in "Gita-Govinda" from which the Das Avatara stotram is extracted, appears
has identified ten principal ones
and interesting, Srila Rupa Goswami
in his "Hamsaduta" the gopis talk about them, but in another way
it's so beautiful - what they say someone could think is offensive
but it's bhama-bhav, it's sweet opposition where they're saying like
as Matsya, the girl, meaning Radharani
cause "Hamsaduta" is spoken by Lalita to a swan to take a message to Krishna in Mathura
saying, "Does He ever remember the two syllables 'Rad-ha"?
but she says that - and the girl with Her heart and the prem as the hook
was the preme and the heart was there and then what did Krishna do?
He took, ate the bait and left the
hook - not captured
and as Kurma - that girl, She gave everything to Him and what did He do?
withdraw His beautiful limbs within His
form and show a hard shell
so she's going through Das avatars in another way:  gopi-vision
They can do that. But meanwhile - back on Earth and more specifically - Varaha
we're told in various pastimes that Varahadev rescues the Earth
Simple enough expression. But how does
that... That should connect -  if we say there are
chinmoy threads connecting everything and why Krishna and...
So in Bhagavad-gita He says, yadā yadā hi dharmasya/ glānir bhavati bhārata
abhyutthānam adharmasya/ tadātmānaṁ sṛjāmy aham - whenever... We know what it says
I'm just gonna say it in a different way, you know: at the point where religion becomes irreligion
at that time He needs to come down or send some avatar, representative,  etc.
because as we told, prakṛti-vaicitryād - pāramparyeṇa... prakṛti-vaicitryād
The truth given - Bhaktivinod Thakur says in the Bhagavatam - in its purity in the beginning
but then it's modified - Uddhava, 11th Canto
modified by the temperament of the
receivers
and then it gradually starts moving away from that
like the classic exercise in journalism class
where, say, there's
four rows, ten students in each row and
the teacher will go and tell the student
in the first row, whisper something to
them - and then they have to turn around
and tell the next student, next-next, go up and down the row like this
and then they get to the end, and then
what she says: before the class
they have the last students here and - what? what were you told? - and they tell what they were told
and then they ask the first student what they were told
and then everybody breaks out in laughter
it's just turned into something else and
the telling modified by the
temperament of the receiver minimally
what to speak of other things
so He says, I will appear at those times and also
paritranaya sadhunam/ vinasaya ca duskrtam/
dharma-samsthapanarthaya/ sambhavami yuge yuge
repeatedly, yuga after yuga, almost like a hint
of yuga avatars: yuge yuge
but yuga-avatars, lila-avatars,
purusha-avatars, guna-avatars, you know,
shaktyavesha-avatars
manvantars - there's like a half a million manvantars,
you know, in a certain time period
so He says in Gita - what we take to be
general principles are laid down there
but our Acharyas - they can extract from
there something more specific or
a deeper level reading - like Guru Maharaja's
"Hidden Treasure of the Sweet Absolute"
showing in a nutshell shlokas and, you
know, yena mam upayantite
parakiya-bhav, etc. - he can extract that,
but just taking it as it is
it's laid the groundwork for so many avatars - so it's there - by inference or allusion
and why did Krishna descend on the Earth? -
we're told: to relieve the burden
so many demonic kings were populating the Earth
it was burdening the Earth
and what is a visual to accompany that? -
like the form of a hunchback woman
due to so much weight, unbearable weight of these evil persons
she's bent over and hunchbacked
like that
but we have the Bhagavatam saying,
the Earth was plunged into
the nether regions - like the Garbhadak ocean
the Southern - like the Patagonia
of the Universe and Varahadev enters
the waters and how interesting - what is
the speciality of the boar?
What is that European delicacy?
Truffles! - So they use them
because they have this heightened sense
of smell to find them - otherwise they
can't find them, so this is the delight
one of the delightful aspects of
Krishna's pastimes - He's omniscient
as default mode. But as Kurma He can't
scratch his back, because He's a turtle
even people go, Can you scratch
my back? - I can't reach that
so what to speak of a turtle - even more
difficult.  So He's omnipotent and He
can't scratch his own back. He's
omniscient he knows everything, so He
should know where the Earth is. How does he find the Earth? - Through the sense of smell
which is also in the Bhagavad-gita:
puṇyo gandhaḥ pṛthivyāḿ ca/ tejaś cāsmi vibhāvasau
jīvanaḿ sarva-bhūteṣu/ tapaś cāsmi tapasviṣu
the seventh chapter: puṇyo gandhaḥ
gandhaḥ means fragrance
puṇyo gandhaḥa pṛthi - pṛthi means the earth
I am the fragrance of the earth
all fragrances come out from the earth, the
soil, right? the lilavadee, goloka champak, plumeria
that flower - it starts, it comes
out of the earth, but so does the
fragrance of the Lotus and all other
flowers - so how wonderful is the earth
and it produced all these fruits, flowers,
etc. - from one soil all of these things
come and He sings in the Gita: think of
that as Me - don't be afraid of it or
or think that by thinking about it you're
necessarily lost in some sort of
whimsical thought - there's a way to
connect this to Krishna conception
there's a way to connect everything to
Krishna conception
because there's only Krishna - actually
the fact of the matter
there is only Krishna and by that we
mean Radha Krishna Lalita Vishaka
Krishna's more than... Like Prabhupad would say
King means Queen Prince princess
kingdom minister you know - when you say "the King"
a king doesn't live in isolation
neither does Krishna, so He is everything
ahaṁ sarvasya prabhavo
"Everything comes from Me" and we go,
"Well what about?.." - Everything comes from Me
- Yeah, but what... - Everything comes from Me
right and if you see something that
seems objectionable, that's probably
because of your connection with it
that it turned into something else
temporarily
like - Guru Maharaj told - the man who takes
the prasad very happily or whatever
and then later when the consequence of eating
reaches its ultimate stage of elimination
he's upset at the foulness of the situation
and, you know, it's a Bengali joke, but then what he's told is
but you're the cause of that
before - I was in another position before
and now by contact with you this is the
outcome - so to speak
so as Guru Maharaja said, it's only that a small part
of the perfect appears to be imperfect
for some time - it's, actually, like a mystical thing
how this happens - as Oscar Wilde said
the real mysterious thing is all of this:
what we see, what's visible
that's mysterious
how did cit get converted into all this stuff
but still - so - puṇyo gandhaḥ the original fragrance
so through the sense of smell
He locates the Earth
that's what we're told - like
searching then traces it all the way to
the Garbhodak ocean and there meets
Hiranyaksha, they battle and Varahadev
wins and then lifts up the Earth with
his tusk and puts her back in orbit
in her rightful position. So at the time of
the appearance of Krishna, although His
pastimes are manifold,
multi-dimensional in purpose and
expression - still a similar situation is evolved, devolved
and the Earth is again
what's the word... no I mean
because we don't want to imply that the
Earth has become degraded, but in a...
I just can't think of the word, but, as I said initially
she is burdened and and in a
sad position, an unhappy one
and so Krishna - although we know ultimately
the Bhagavatam culminates in His divine
play with Radharani and Braja Gopis
still - His appearance, His pastimes with
Nanda, Yashoda, then with the cowherd boys
you know - kumar, poganda, then kishor
but on the way to the kishor pastimes
well, afterwards, actually, but all part of
this that we know to plunge, partially
to plunge the gopis hearts in the depths of
separation where they yield the most
superior type of Krishna-prem
Akrura comes and takes Krishna out of Vrindavan
but also his parents - originally - Vasudev, Devaki
they're shackled by Kangsa in
Mathura and He must go there and again
braja-jana-palana, asura-kula-nasana
the asura-kul needs to be nashed
destroyed. And everything
Krishna does is amazing I mentioned that
Kaliya Ghat where Krishna - the kadamba tree
is there from which He jumped into the
Jamuna to punish Kalia I always found it
particularly charming that Rupa
Goswami says, "He adjusted His belt"
before He entered
that he mentioned that detail
means everything He does is
enchanting and even that looked good
the adjustment of His belt is divine for me
He has the tribanga form, pulled the belt
closer and - see more of His divine
form which is a festival for the eyes - anangotsavam this face I'm gonna run
visvesam anuranjanena janayann anandam indivara
sreni-syamala-komalair upanayann angair anangotsavam
ananga utsav - a festival of form - all the
different parts of his body or like a
divine visual festival
so on the way to Mathura and Kamsa
has scheduled a competition to draw people from
different places - there will be wrestlers
events, you know, a splendid time is
guaranteed for all and Krishna, Balaram,
the cowherd boys
they are village people
kṛṣṇera yateka khelā, sarvottama nara-līlā,
nara-vapu tāhāra svarūpa
gopa-veśa, veṇu-kara, nava-kiśora, naṭa-vara/
nara-līlāra haya anurūpa
the human-like pastimes of Krishna
so He's not a
Brahmin or a kshatriya, He's from the
lower section of society which means: if
you put a middle bar there: Brahmin,
Kshatriya - middle - Vaishya, Shudra
in the middle and Guru Maharaj says always
that the highest truth is always in the
central, in the middle position
so, please, allow Maharaj
don't make him turn away
Jay Srila Bhakti Bimal Avadhut
Maharaj there's a bench there and they
can bring a cushion or bring another
chair from the temple as is appropriate
So what did I just say? - The highest Truth
is always in the middle position.
- Oh in the middle. That's like
Madan Mohan, Govindaji, Gopinath
Govinda's in the middle position
18 chapters of Bhagavad-gita, the six in the
middle. It's just always the middle
the central conception of the infinite
the golden mean: all-accomodating Brahma
all-permeating Paramatma
anor aniyan mahato mahiyan - and what's the
central conception of the infinite? - human-like
two arms - not ten, not a thousand - two
when I was in Loi Bazaar
in "Ganga Prasad", the original
not outside the window they can come in
I mean - what - she's gonna sit out on
the other side of the window and not
hear anything - please
you know, I can just go
so then as they're in purchasing, he's a
cloth merchant and he always likes to
give "Limka"s to everyone, you know, so
there's four of us and he sends his boy
who's now in charge of the shop
but anyway and he goes and he goes
to man, he brings two, comes over then he
goes back and brings another two
I went like that and Ganga Prasad to show
he had some - he said to me
he said, We are not in Vaikuntha
we're in Vrindavan
meaning if we were in Vaikuntha
he could have brought four
but because we're in Vrindavan,
he had to go twice
so the deceptively simple - aprakrita-lila
human-like - they're walking
not even shoes they're having
the cowherd boys, barefoot
so Krishna when they go to Mathura,
they're like these country, unsophisticated
What did Guru Maharaj say about braja-gopis?
silly stupid jungle girls
only He can say that, but he means it a
a charming way: like teenage girls can be
silly or seem to be - they're mad after
this boy Krishna, but if you record their
expressions - they surpass the Vedas - these
so-called silly jungle girls they're
posing that way - when they write something,
they can turn the vedas inside out
upside down. And the Vedas, when they see
what they have, are crying saying
we didn't know! what have we done?!
we didn't express this, we didn't reveal this
we only sent people in a particular
direction - oh, what have we done?! we didn't
know such sweetness existed
so on the way there - they're like country
people, they don't have the latest fashions
you know - Mathura Vogue - so they're dressed
in their Gopa-vesh, a cowherd dress
and on the way there they see this
tailor - going with the clothing rack
and then they think, Oh! Sir! If we
could value some of your clothes
And he goes, What?! You, upstart cowherds
these are the clothes of the king!
How dare you?!
and then Krishna just chopped his head off
stuff happens
mercifully - not a whole lot of
dialogue in that scene i just - done, so
his head  rolling over in the side
body drops, then Krishna's going through
the rack and handing out the cloth
Balaram! I think this kind of - you'd like
this: this will look good on you I'll
take this, they're passing out to the
other cowherd boys, they're all wearing
Kamsa's clothes. Then they are thinking, how
do I look? - You look really good.
and then they proceed, now
they're dressed more appropriately
city attire although it's the King's wardrobe
and then they see this
hunchback woman coming and she's a
what do you call someone - a parfum
perfumer - someone who deals aroma
aromatist, I think, an aromatist
no, the word "therapy" didn't have to be there
it's a aromatist, I believe
anyway something like you know she deals
in oils: essential oils, fragrances, things
like that - and it's interesting
if you think - so remember: how did
Varaha find the Earth through the sense
of smell
how does Krishna find Kubja
whose name is Trivakra -  tri-vakra
means: in three places she's bent over
she's a hunchback - why is she a hunchback?
because of the burden of all these evil
kings, so we find out from Vishvanath
Chakravarti Thakur: she is bhu-shakti
she's a partial expansion of Satyabhama,
the Dwarka queen
so bhu-shakti, like bhumi, the Earth - so
this is the Earth personified who's been...
why is she hunchback? all these
demonic kings - they're burdening
her, they're weighing her down, we're told,
she has a very beautiful face but she is
hunchback and what is her occupation? -she's an aromatist - like the Earth
puṇyo gandhaḥ pṛthivyāḿ ca - all the
fragrances come from the earth, so in
a sense - how does Krishna discover her? -
like Varaha through the scent, through
scent she comes, but here, unlike the
tailor when Krishna asks her first
she is already offering, she's saying, Oh I
think you know... they say: when you put the
oil on your skin - individuals,
different people - they react differently
the same oil doesn't smell the same on
every person, so she picks an oil that's
appropriate for Balarama, one for Krishna
but so then krishna - He can... He knows
everything and knows her situation
and He thinks,  This lady, she's so nice and
just to see her like this... I've come
to restore the Earth to her
rightful position and look at her now so
korun: compassion, mercy and it's so beautiful
then does Kristin do? - with His
lotus feet that are ever sought after
with His very lotus feet of Krishna
He steps on both of her feet
everyone wants to get the dust on
lotus feet of Krishna. Krishna's
got His lotus feet on top of her feet
I don't know if you get more foot than
that, right? and then what does He do?
He bends over and like - remember, Varaha has
two tusks right and that's how He lifts
up the Earth, so Krishna, He steps on her
with his lotus feet and with his two
fingers bends down like that - like Varahadev
and lifts up the Earth, lifts her up
and now she's restored to her rightful
position and she looks incredibly
beautiful and seductive, but due to the
touch of Krishna - just as it says in the
vrndaranyam sva-pada-ramanam pravisad gita-kirtih
Guru Maharaj pointed out: lest anyone thinks there's
some anomaly here from a rasa analysis
that in that verse where Krishna and
Balaram are entering the forest, playing the
flutes, the air is being filled with nectar
barhapidam nata-vara-vapuh karnayoh karnikaram
that obe
anyway, it says in the last line
vrndaranyam sva-pada-ramanam pravisad gita-kirtih
the earth due to the
touch of the lotus feet of Krishna - it is
imbued with conjugal sentiments
the earth that is generally thought of as
shanta-rasa - is imbued
with conjugal sentiments
so you can't have a stereotypical
conception about Vrindavan, so here due
to the touch of Krishna Khubja's become
imbued with Madhura-rasa sentiments and
she starts expressing them toward
Krishna inviting him to her house and
Balaram, the cowherd boys - they start
to giggle, they're all like...
because she can't contain herself: she's
so enamored and she's saying
and it's Your fault
You did this to me by touching me, You're
Sweetness personified now you
touched me and now... and when we say
"sweetness" we don't mean like in
a conventional sense - What's the ultimate
sweetness? - Madhura-rasa
here's Madhura-rasa personified: You touched
you put Your feet on mine, pulled me up
like this - I'm overwhelmed and then so
but Krishna sees the cowherd boys are
giggling and laughing and He says
What are you laughing at? - He said, I think she is
hasya-rasa personified and she knows
you're all a bunch of jokers and she
came here to make you laugh - that's what
He says first - he's trying to save the
situation, but He tells her, I have some important...
Like Gurudev'd say, I have one job in Mathura
with a fellow named Key
I already said, seeing the Hindi movie, "Maharaj Kams ki jay ho!" - So He's got to go kick
some Jayho with Maharaj Kams and so
He's telling her, Later we can get together
together - you know - like I'll stop by
I mean, I assume, it's an ongoing, standing
order, invitation, standing invitation
so, she is, All right, - you know
so Krishna, then - what I wanted to say is...
so, oh, then - well, just a finish
then at that point He enters Kamsa's arena
well, first - outside - Kamsa has different
plans, one is to have this giant elephant -
just kill Him before even makes it
inside and Krishna meets that elephant
and, long story short, He's body-slamming
the elephant with his tail, the elephant
tries to get him - remember, tusk
tusks - there is kind of a Tusk Segway, anyway
so then he's like tries to stab Krishna
and misses them, then Krishna goes
underneath him - he can't find them
and then, finally, Krishna body slams
him a few times, then pulls his tusks out
and stabs him and kills him with it
it's like - you're carrying the weapon
it's like "Rākhe Kṛṣṇa Māre Ke, Māre Kṛṣṇa..."
this is example of "Māre Kṛṣṇa Rākhe Ke"
He just killed him with the tusk
now the Tusk is full of blood from
stabbing the elephant and so Krishna's
carrying it on His shoulder on the way
in, so when Kamsa sees Him making His
entrance and then the arena, he can't
help but notice that Krishna and
Balarama are wearing his clothes and the
elephant he sent to kill Him - Krishna is
carrying a tusk on his shoulder that's
dripping blood and guts, so he's thinking
"This might not be my day, my lucky day"
when he woke up in the morning
we're told - he went to shave and couldn't
see his face in the mirror - that's always
an indication - or he saw his shadow had
holes in it - not good
you know and then you see Krishna
wearing your own clothes and with the
bloody tusks dripping
and you're going like, "Mmm"
you know and then the wrestlers are there
but the ladies from Mathura
they say: gopyas tapaḥ kim acaran yad amuṣya rūpaṁ/
lāvaṇya-sāram asamordhvam ananya-siddham
dṛgbhiḥ pibanty anusavābhinavaṁ durāpam/
ekānta-dhāma yaśasaḥ śriya aiśvarasya
just see - their immediate reaction
is to think of the Gopis
they see how beautiful Krishna is -
gopyas tapaḥ kim acaran yad amuṣya...
this form of Krishna's so beautiful -  what did They?..
we're get to just see it now - for a
moment
they're always seeing Krishna so they are
thinking - what did They do? - gopyas tapaḥ
what tapasya They must have done to
achieve that position? and it's an
interesting word - there it says
lāvaṇya-sāram asamordhvam ananya-siddham
unparalleled perfection
and what is it like?
lāvaṇya-sāram means like
if Beauty were cream - creme de la creme
of beautiful substances is before our eyes
that's what comes from the hearts of
these ladies in Mathura, but immediately
thinking of the good fortune of the
Braja-gopis - and we're told: so when He
enters the arena and Guru Maharaj
likes this verse very much
mallānām aśanir nṛṇāṁ
nara-varaḥ strīṇāṁ smaro mūrtimān
gopānāṁ sva-jano ’satāṁ
kṣiti-bhujāṁ śāstā sva-pitroḥ śiśuḥ
mṛtyur bhoja-pater virāḍ aviduṣāṁ
tattvaṁ paraṁ yogināṁ
vṛṣṇīnāṁ para-devateti vidito
raṅgaṁ gataḥ sāgrajaḥ
that means "with his elder brother"
raṅgaṁ - entered the arena with his elder brother
and what did they see? -
we talked in the beginning about seeing
and different perspectives - what did they
see? -  says "mallānām aśanir " - means
"the wrestlers", the big wrestlers waiting, [about] whom the ladies said, This is not fair!..
they were right, but not in the way they thought
because they're like: Krishna, Balarama
are smaller and these wrestlers are huge,
and they're going, What is this? - And these
grown men - why? - this is, you know, it's like
horrible, they're thinking, but, of course
it is unfair, because on the one side is
Krishna, on the other side is Balaram
but who are these exalted souls that got
to play that part we can think that also
liberated souls. But anyway, so then was
always saying: the wrestlers - what do they
see? - lightning. like...  they're like, Oh-oh
they know that this is not going to end well
and it has nothing to do with relative
size they know something about aprakrita-lila
themselves
mallānām aśanir nṛṇāṁ nara-varaḥ
and nara-varaḥ means like - sometimes they say like an actor, dancer - whatever and
what it reminds me of is the movie stars
when they go to like the Academy Awards
or something and they all, you know, there
they'd go, And there is so and so...
and the person seems to be
perfect in their movements and their
smile, and their laughter and you know
and everyone's "o-o-oh!..", you know, and everyone's
watching them, just everything they do is
perfect, you know... Krishna is that.
They are not that. For a moment... As
Andy Warhol said, for 15 minutes they
may be that
Krishna - fifteen trillion years
on Brahmaloka is a bad of an eyelash
for Krishna. Subru.
so nara-varaḥ - it's saying that
He looks like a movie star
when He enters - you could say in
modern context nara-varaḥ
strīṇāṁ smaro mūrtimān
and the women see smaraḥ means Cupid here
many words for Cupid - smaro mūrtimān
Cupid personified
the women there are like, Oh, my God...  He's so beautiful, so charming
so seductive - cause if one
Cupid is enough to drive everybody mad
then - kandarpa-koti-kamaniya-visesa-sobham
10 million Cupids rolled into one
that would just be too much
to resist - ahaituki apratihata
is irresistible - so - mūrtimān
gopānāṁ sva-janaḥ - and the gopas
just like in the Olympics
like the girl from Izhevsk
won the gold medal at the Winter Olympics
so Indulekha's from Izhevsk
Avadhut Maharaj took me there once
and when we were going there he thought
I might not so excited to go
to a place called Izhevsk, so he said
like we're going to Siberia and
and there're mastodons and you know woolly mammoths
still roaming you know, in downtown
Izhevsk - and so I think
I'm all all psyched up: we're going
in the Arctic Circle or and somewhere
and then later we're on this bus at the
airport leaving and I hear an American
voice and that voice hears my voice,
it's some lady visiting relatives
and so I said to her... And the whole week
I'm giving examples about the cold -
minus 30 - every example I'm using all these
snow-ice-Siberian type examples
and so I say so what do you think of
Siberia? and she looks at me and she goes
This isn't Siberia! - and I go, It's not?.. -
She says, No! like - no, this isn't Siberia, you fool...
and I'm like, Oh - and I turn to Maharaj
and I go, Maharaj, you told me, we were
going to Siberia and all week I'm giving
these examples that are like snow-based
ice-based, you know, negative
absolute zero - this kind of thing and
and Maharaj says, It's like Siberia but he
thought I would be disappointed - like
We're going to Izhevsk. - Where is that?
- Well, it's just another town in Russia
So he sold it as Siberia. So when the girl from there won,
the people think she's one of us
there's this local pride, so it says
gopānāṁ sva-jano ’satāṁ
at Kamsa's Olympics the gopas and the gopis
from Vrindavan - they think that Krishna is
theirs. As we're told,
Rupa Goswami says, grita-sneha
the love and affection, compared to ghee
is "I am yours"
and that's the mood of Chandravali and
her group, he said, but sweeter - madhu-sneha
the one that's like honey is "You are
mine" - and that's Radharani and her group
they feel possessive over Krishna. So back
at that Kadamba tree when we were there
to talk about the pastimes,
to sing some songs
these girls come in Vrindavan everyday
around 4 o'clock in the afternoon and
they're from 4 to 14, to 8, like 4-8-12-16
you know and they come and sing songs
about Gopal, climbing the Kadamba tree,
playing with the Gopis, punishing Kalia
you can understand, they've been
doing this for 5,000 years
generationally - and they were so happy
although we kind of cut in on their time
they waited till we finished Yashomati-nandana,
etc. - and there's a picture and
you can see the leader girl -
she's so happy
why? -  because we're showing
some love and affection for her Gopal
Not for Krishna... They feel, they own... Krishna is theirs. They really feel that
He belongs to them and they're happy if
other people like Him, their Krishna
Like Tarun Kanti Ghosh would always go,
Amar Gauranga - My Gauranga!
So they - My Krishna! so they're saying,
gopānāṁ sva-jano ’satāṁ
means, they are thinking like, you know,
He's from Vrinda-avan!
kṣiti-bhujāṁ... gopānāṁ sva-jano ’satāṁ
kṣiti-bhujāṁ śāstā sva-pitroḥ...
and some are seeing the rod of
chastisement, Vasudev and Devaki
are in shackles and they're saying, Our son!.. - they're thinking like that
mṛtyur bhoja-pater - bhoja-pater means
Kamsa - he's seeing death personified
that's who he's seeing. virāḍ aviduṣāṁ -
some are seeing the universal form
Imagine, they're seeing
everything like that
the ignorant - virāḍ aviduṣāṁ
tattvaṁ paraṁ yogināṁ - and the yogi's are
seeing that Paramatma, they're trying to
connect with in the heart - they're seeing
Is He not now before us? but in an
inconceivably charming form
yam shyamasundaram achintya-guna-svarup
inconceivably beautiful svarup
tattvaṁ paraṁ yogināṁ... mṛtyur bhoja-pater
virāḍ aviduṣāṁ tattvaṁ paraṁ yogināṁ
vṛṣṇīnāṁ para-devateti - and Vrishnis
saying here's the Lord of our dynasty
vṛṣṇīnāṁ para-devateti vidito
raṅgaṁ [gataḥ] sāgrajaḥ - and with Balaram,
His brother they enter, so the Acharyas
say, there's ten different points of
view expressed here according to the
five rases and some subdivisions
one Krishna simultaneously showing all
these things to different people, so many
things achieved in one pastime
so we wouldn't think normally of Varahadev
being connected with madhura-rasa
but there's these cinmoy
connecting threads, so as He lifted
up the Earth, Krishna, like in a varaha-bhav
lifts up Kubja and she becomes
this inconceivably beautiful woman and
the last thing I want to say is this
to offer some praise that Mahaprabhu
has a varaha-bhav also - when He shows up at the
house of Murari Gupta - you know,  knock
on the door - Who's there? - he opens the
door and there's Varahadev - Nimai Pandit as Varaha, as Varaha-avatar
because before - bhakta-bhav and radha-bhav
He's sometimes playing in this way
for various divine purpose, so He goes,
Aren't you going to invite me in? - Oh, yeah!
Goes in and what and does He do?
We've seen in India they have these water
pots, they go like this and then they're
round like that, they have a spout on
they're totally round - like the Earth
and what are they made out of? - Clay
which is... - Earth. - Thank you.
Right, so He goes over in the corner and
lifts it up like He's saving the Earth from the
Garbhodak ocean and Murari Gupta's like, Ah-hhh...
and He's saying, Just don't stand
there, Murari, offer some prayers
and it's very beautiful, because
Murari Gupta says he's not capable
or qualified to offer a proper
prayer but that becomes the prayer
he says, If Anantadev with his thousands
of mouths - in the mouths of
Anantadev the treasure is hidden -
jewels of hari-katha are in the
mouth of Ananta-sesh and coming out.
He says, If Anantadev with his thousands of
divine mouths has been glorifying You
eternally and has not exhausted Your
glories - then what can a fallen person
like me say? - I am totally
unqualified to say anything - to
properly glorify You. - But that's the
prayer, that's the appropriate prayer - how
beautiful it is - "If Ananta with his
thousands of mouths cannot exhaust Your
glories, then what can a fallen person
like myself say?.."
if we, as Guru Maharaj would say,
trace everything back to the central
conception of the infinite - I like to say,
I'll conclude with this because I want to
give William Blake some sukriti
"William Blake - he's a good man."
But he says - because remember
we when we were teenagers
you know, there was a group called
"The Doors" and we thought,
Well, that's really an uninteresting name
"The Doors"?! - You couldn't think of anything better
than that? - "The Doors"? - But then when
they were asked like why is group
called "The Doors"? - they were reading
Aldous Huxley and Aldous Huxley - he'd written
a book called "The Doors of Perception"
which would have been a long
name for a group in those days
you needed like a single word kind of thing
it's before they invented all these like
paragraph names, but anyway - so they said, Jim Morisson said
well, "The Doors of Perception", Aldous Huxley
it was about psychedelics, expanding
your mind, your consciousness, etc.
but if you read carefully, you'll understand: that phrase
did not originate with Aldous
Huxley, but with William Blake who said
If the doors of perception are cleansed
they will perceive everything as it is -
Infinite
it's a wonderful saying, it's true, it's beautiful
it's in harmony with Krishna consciousness
but still it's not very precise
but there's a lot of implications
so then we say, well the
doors of perception - that means the
senses so we're saying if they're
cleansed - then they'll see everything
else it is infinite doesn't mean just
like see this glass in relation to
infinite, but it means another
way of looking, expressing this is
that... that means there must be... when the
the doors of the auditory senses clear that must mean
your can... an Infinite that can be heard,
tasted, touched, smelled, felt - that means
the personality of the infinite,
the personality of Godhead, so what is
another name of Krishna - besides Govinda
and so many others? - Hrishikesh - hrishika isha
doesn't mean just "the lord of the senses",
but in the sense of like the highest
sensual expression, the ultimate
beautiful thing to be seen is Krishna
to be heard is His flute, the sound of His
name, to be tasted is that which
comes in connection with Him, to feel -
every... the full spectral range of sensual
possibility reaches its zenith point in
the personification of Krishna
Who's Rasa-prada - He's giving that, so - hrishika isha
and here's the conclusion is that
what does Rupa Goswami say?
sarvopādhi-vinirmuktaṁ - that means
if the doors of perception are cleansed
it's another way of saying
sarvopadhi-vinirmuktam - and what did he say? -  no substitute! "Upadi" can mean
designation, rank, other things, but in the
Sanskrit dictionary also says
it means "substitute". When you stop
substituting things for Krishna, people
for Krishna, places for Vrindavan or divine [land] - all of this, all of these
substitutions, and he says: when you stop
substituting things other than Krishna
for Krishna then you'll see everything
as Infinite
sarvopādhi-vinirmuktaṁ
tat-paratvena nirmalam
hṛṣīkeṇa hṛṣīkeśa-
sevanaṁ bhaktir ucyate
and this is the good news for us,
because He's hrishika isha - Hrishikesh
because He has senses, you can serve Him
with your senses
and it's not just an option
it's actually what they're meant for
and that's good for us - to see
śrutvā guṇān bhuvana-sundara śṛṇvatāḿ te
the most beautiful thing to hear
hearing about Him
nama-rupa-guna-lila - the form comes
out of the sound
with particular qualities and pastimes
so what does Rukmini say?
now that I heard about You
I understand why there's hearing
why there's an auditory sense - it's not
something we say, Well, that's an option -
you can exercise - is to hear about
Krishna - no, she's saying - that's the only
reason you have ears! and that's
consistent with Sukadev and Radharani
Sukadev in the Bhagavatam is saying
Those ears that don't hear [about You]
they're like a broken conch shell
the tongue that doesn't chant
the glories - like the tongue of a snake
or a frog and you know all these different
things are given in there, and then you
think: well, that's Sukadev, he's
one of those heavy brahmacaris
know gonna stick it to the, you know, people are still attached to the mundane
but what I found interesting was that
the same thing appears in
the Madhya-lila, Chapter 2, which is a
condensed version of the whole Charitamritam
and it's the statements of Radharani
but Saraswati Thakur
purports or statements by quoting
Sukadeva Goswami and what is She saying?
Those eyes which do not look upon Your
divine form are as useless as the eyes on
a peacock plume - She's saying the same
thing, but with this Gopi-bhav intensity
that was earlier expressed by Sukadev
these are the cinmoy connecting threads
Hare Krishna!