When my old friend
was visiting me
and sharing that his faith
was damaged, and he was now …
[Inconceivably Wonderful Creation]
He said, “You know,
whether all of this,
(meaning the world, everything)
comes from God
or just is, or … ”, he said,
“They are both absurd to me.”
Like that.
And I said, “Anyway …
have some more chatni”.
[Laughing]
I didn’t choose at that time
to say anything, but later
I was on a train in the Ukraine,
and I was thinking
about this for months.
And something came to me,
and I thought,
“Yes”, I said,
“but you have something wrong—
is that by dictionary definition
that all of this just manifest
from nothing,
that’s called absurd!”
And on that point I must say:
brahma satya jagan mithyā—
Śaṅkarācārya said, “I will now …
There are so many books written:
Vedanta, the Upaniṣads,
this, that …
Now in a half a line,
I am going to tell you
everything you need to know.
You can read
the Mahābhārata,
you can read the Vedas,
you can read all of it.
I’m going to tell you in a half a line,
not even in whole ṣloka,
in half a line
I’m going to tell you everything.
This is all you need:
brahma satya jagan mithyā—
spirit is truth,
the world is false.
That’s all you need to know,
follow this line of thought.“
But so, in a similar vein I thought,
“Yes, that all this came from nothing—
by dictionary definition
that is absurd.
But that all of this is the creation
of the Supreme Personality of Godhead,
that is what we call inconceivable.”
Not absurd, inconceivable,
and inconceivably wonderful.