We say, "Well, in dealing
with other people
what is the general rule?"
Tṛṇād api sunīcena,
taror api sahiṣṇunā,
amāninā mānadena...
to be humble, tolerant,
offer respect to others.
[Armed with Humility]
But when some ignorant
people heard,
thinking that the Mayapur
Chandradaya Mandir
there are so many
Americans there,
and they have so much money.
The rumours spread that
the Deity was made
out of gold, solid gold.
So they wanted
to steal Radharani
and maybe Krishna,
They are both, like that,
they heard, "They are solid gold".
And when they came,
the leaders of the time
defended the Deities
even... with weapons.
So some people came
to Guru Maharaj,
and they said,
"They are not following
Mahaprabhu's teachings
of being humble, tolerant
and offering respect to others.
But Guru Maharaj said,
"No, I supported them, saying,
'Tṛṇād api sunīcena to who?'
That you've come to molest
the Deity and the Vaishnava,
and then I will practice humility?"
He said, "No, with full force
I will defend the Deity,
the Vaishnava".
So, again, there is
the famous saying,
"ācāryavān puruṣo veda"—
"One who's in connection
with an acharya,
knows what is what".
Otherwise, if we lack
discerning ability,
discriminating ability
or are not in connection
with someone,
who has such ability,
then we will be likely
to misjudge, misread.
So then it would
be better for us
to just be generally
respectful
and not make such
determinations.