And look, you say
‘calling for Kṛṣṇa’.
That’s not something
in the past.
[Krishna Will Protect Me!]
And if you look
to Kṛṣṇa līla,
what would be expected
from progressive servitors?
We hear in the case
of Draupadī,
that when she’s …
this is līla, pastimes, Mahābhārata .
But when she is lost,
she’s gambled away
by her husbands.
And when the Kauravas
want to humiliate her
and humiliate the Pāṇḍavas,
and they call for her,
to enter the assemble,
and they want to strip her, publicly,
to disrobe her
in front of an open assemble.
This woman of impeccable character,
saintly qualities, and dignity.
They want to disrobe her publicly—
now that they own her.
And when she enters
that scene …
What are we told first?
—She’s crying,
she’s calling for Kṛṣṇa.
And there is no response.
And she’s trying
to keep her dignity, modesty.
And at the end,
when she has …
she’s holding with her hands
her remaining cloth,
and when she is
utterly hopeless, and helpless,
she throws up both
of her hands in the air.
She surrenders to her destiny,
her fate,
and she says,
“Hey, Gopī-jana-vallabha!”
When she addresses Kṛṣṇa
as the beloved of the Vraja‒gopīs,
then Kṛṣṇa comes.
But He didn’t respond
before that.
Because mām ekaṁ śaraṇaṁ vraja
[Bg: 18.66]
vraja śaraṇaṁ—
this type of total
giving off the self over to Kṛṣṇa,
and one’s fate to Kṛṣṇa.
ānukūlyasya saṅkalpaḥ
prātikūlyasya varjanam
rakṣiṣyatīti viśvāso
goptṛtve … [Cc: 2.22.100]
Offering oneself to Kṛṣṇa,
expecting “Kṛṣṇa will protect me.”
Rākhe kṛṣṇa mare ke, mare kṛṣṇa rākhe ke
[from Swāmī Prabhupād’s lectures]
If Kṛṣṇa wants to protect me—
no one can harm me,
If He wants to kill me—
no one can save me.
When she reaches
that level, the vraja śaraṇaṁ,
“Hey, Gopī-jana-vallabha!”
Then Kṛṣṇa is miraculously,
mysteriously supplying the cloth.
And we hear, what is that?
—When she was a girl,
and Kṛṣṇa cut once,
and she tore her cloth
and made a bandage
for Kṛṣṇa.
You give little finite to Kṛṣṇa,
and the infinite comes in return.