We know, the same time,
some of the superior devotee
like Kṛṣṇadās Bābājī Mahārāj—
I’ve been a witness,
and Guru Mahārāj mentioned it
on his disappearance day,
once, in praise of him—
the whole night chanting
Kṛṣṇa-nām and kīrtan songs.
[Ekadashi | From Dusk Till Dawn]
And once in Māyāpur that night
we were in this room with him,
and devotees were asking him
different questions,
and he was giving that answer,
“Hare Kṛṣṇa!”
So, someone said, “Bābājī Mahārāj,
how to overcome sex desire?”
He said, “You are trying!
I am trying! Hare Kṛṣṇa!”
[Laughing]
We got some encouragement.
But, anyway, that night as we all ...
It was like eleven, twelve …
I remember, I got to play the drum
at one point,
and he went like,
“Give me the drum!”
[Laughing]
First I was like, “Wow! …”
and he’s saying …
[Laughing]
But, anyway, kept singing and we also …
Then now it’s midnight …
He doesn’t show any signs
of, like, fatigue.
And then finally, we are all like falling;
then now we’re all asleep.
And we went to sleep
to the sound of him taking Kṛṣṇa-nām.
And when we woke up at 4:15
or whenever,
there was just,
“Hare Kṛṣṇa, Hare Kṛṣṇa”—
he was still chanting.
So, he did that so many times.
And I recently …
Our godsister Deva Moyi Didi,
she left the world,
and she was a wonderful disciple
of Śrīla Guru Mahārāj,
and favourite of Śrīla Gurudev,
extraordinary Vaiṣṇavī.
When she was a little girl,
she used to go
to Mādhava Mahārāja’s Maṭh.
Guru Mahārāj, whenever he mentioned
Mādhava Mahārāja’s name,
he’d have to go,
“Hayagrīva Brahmachārī.”
Because he was known
as Hayagrīva Brahmachārī
in the Gauḍīya Maṭh.
So even known as Mādhava Mahārāj,
this famous Mahārāj,
established maybe twenty five Maṭhs.
Very powerful preacher.
Very handsome also.
When Deva Moyi was a little girl,
she would sometimes, like,
sit on Mādhava—
when she was like a toddler—
she sit on Mādhava Mahārāja’s lap,
and he gave her some mercy,
and liked her,
she would go to his Maṭh.
And when Śrīla Gurudev,
when she translated things from,
sometimes from Bengali to English
or back,
she translated some things of Gurudev once,
some English, and he said,
“It became better than the original.”
[Laughing]
He gave such praise to her.
And I had the good fortune to have
her association at different times,
she had some affection for me,
very kind to me,
always encouraging me.
And once we were working
on this publication
called
“Prabhupād Saraswatī Ṭhākur”,
and I had her and her team,
which is her daughters—
they were always like her team,
her girls, her assistants—
doing some transliteration
and things like that.
Anyway, I had to call her about something,
she wrote the biographical parts.
And it was on Ekādaśī,
and the call was there
about 10 o’clock at night.
And we were on the phone, and then
we started to talk about Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
and Mahāprabhu, Gaura-kathā,
Kṛṣṇa-kathā, Vaiṣṇava-kathā,
and it was like midnight, 1 o’clock, then,
I know that at a certain point,
the sun rose.
So we realized,
the whole evening had been spent
engaged in Hari-kathā.
And in a chaste way—telephone, she was
in one location, I was in another one,
and service related ...
But I thought, “Oh, what a personality
that to get so absorbed
in talking about Kṛṣṇa and Guru Mahārāj,
and all these things
to spend the whole evening
discussing.”
That can happen,
if it’s meant to happen.
But, so we hear that the higher section,
they’re always,
Bābājī Mahārāj was always doing that
every Ekādaśī.
That was his capacity.
Adhikār—capacity to do that.