Well, I already just alluded to
what we described.
We hear this in story, remember:
“There are no facts,
just interpretations.”
We hear stories,
we hear stories of great love
and it resonates,
it affects part of us.
So, it means that
we’re actually seeking
to live in the subjective world.
That’s what I’m saying.
Actually, that’s what we want to do.
Just like when someone
goes to a movie,
they really like it if
—they’ll say—
if you just forget yourself
and live in that for two hours.
So, we’re the only species
who really does that,
or, to the extreme,
in human species.
So, what it really points to is:
we want to live
in the subjective world,
and we’re at present
halfway between
the objective
and the subjective world.
In other words, if we’re sitting
and looking at a master artwork
in the Uffizi Museum in Florence,
by Leonardo,
I can’t prove to someone that
this is great art; it’s a masterwork.
But, if that person’s willing to hear,
to undergo some study,
then it’s possible
that they can come to
the point of appreciating
the depth of beauty—
the subjective aspect
of what is there.
We’re always seeking
subjective things.
We’re attracted to hear a story,
whether it’s true or not.
As they say,
“If you want to tell the truth,
write fiction”;
“Art is a lie that tells the truth.”
So, we’re not really concerned
about its objective aspect.
When we look at
the beautiful Renoir painting
of the flowers or whatever,
they’re not real flowers.
Maybe a real flower,
upon close examination,
is more beautiful,
but if an artist does
some sort of representation there,
we’ll appreciate that.
Well, no … We’re saying,
“Oh, but look, so you’re saying that
this flesh and blood
is not real?”
No, I’m not saying that,
but what allows me
to feel this and see it?
I’m seeing it through these eyes,
touching it …
What’s the seat
of this experience?
Then we’ll go to the mind,
and then, more refined
than the mind: intellect.
Kṛṣṇa says in the Gītā that
the soul’s located in
even a more subtle plane.
So, the soul is the enabler
who’s enabling us to navigate
the objective world
and have a sensual experience.