I remember myself,
and at this time some 41 years ago
going into a book store in San Francisco
and getting one of those books.
It was the third volume
of the First Canto.
[The Ultimate Question]
I remember reading
about Śukadev Goswāmī.
And this is the time
of the 60s,
and Haight-Ashbury,
and the hippy movement,
and then, who is the leader?
A 16-year-old boy, who is naked.
[Laughing]
He’s walking around naked.
Just he has long hair,
and he is naked.
And when he enters
the assembly,
the sages give him
the presidential seat
because they can see
by the study of physiognomy
that he is not a madman,
he is a liberated soul
to the extreme.
So, and there is a beautiful description
of Śukadev Goswāmī there;
Gurudev used to chant it
so many times.
He liked it so much
that actually some of the words
he took from the descriptions
of Śukadev Goswāmī
and used in his compositions
in praise of Śrīla Guru Mahārāj.
Because he is described as like
looking like Śyāmasundar Kṛṣṇa,
the beauty of his neck,
his body …
There is
an elaborate description
of just how beautiful
Śukadev was.
But so and I am reading
this book,
and I had some other books
at that time:
Bhagavad-gītā, other things,
but I wanted this.
I always see
in the Bhagavad-gītā purport
the reference
to the Śrīmad Bhāgavatam,
so I am reading this,
and then it says,
“Parīkṣit Mahārāj
asked Śukadev,
‘What is the purpose
of one in life,
specifically for one,
who is about to die.’”
The whole book,
I am reading the Sanskrit,
the Devanagari,
the words-for-words … everything,
and the book
leads us to this point,
and the King says,
“What is the purpose of life
specifically for one,
who is about to die?”
And I am getting more
and more excited,
then it says, “Thus end
the Bhaktivedanta purports
to the First Canto
of the Śrīmad Bhāgavatam.”
And I thought, “Oh, no!
This is unfair.” [Laughing]
And I went like,
“You are kidding!
It doesn’t have the answer
to the question.”
I went back to the store
and asked,
“Do you have the next book?”
and they said,
“Oh, these are used books
and we …” And I said,
“Sir, you have to be kidding;
lead us to this big question,
and you don’t have the next book
that answers the question?”
He’s like, “Don’t give me a hard time,
I just work here.”
[Laughing]
So I realized
that I would have to join
[Laughing]
to get the answer
to this all-important question.
[Laughing]
And actually when
I did join,
they just published
the first chapter of the Second Canto,
where the question
“My dear king …”,
I think, “Thank you, Lord!”
“… your question …”
varīyān eṣa te praśnaḥ
kṛto loka-hitaṁ nṛpa
ātmavit-sammataḥ puṁsāṁ
śrotavyādiṣu yaḥ paraḥ
[SB: 2.1.1]
This question is beneficial
for everyone to hear.