Guru Maharaj told the
concept
"Autocrat, Despot and Liar."
[Autocrat, Despot and Liar]
The devotees were shoсked
to hear those things,
Autocrat, Despot, Liar...
It just didn't sound
like the normal way
you describe God.
[laughs]
Or praise the Lord.
Autocrat? Yes. Then
in Hegelian terms—
Reality is for Itself and by Itself.
In the śloka before,
abhijñaḥ svarāṭ
[SB: 1.1.1]
He's for Himself and by Himself.
As when Oscar Wilde told
in the intro of the
"Picture of Dorian Gray",
"All art is quite useless."
And what he meant to say
in the "art is for art's sake"
movement,
"If it's really art,
the highest type of art,
then it doesn't exist to fulfill
any secondary purpose.
It exists for itself and by itself."
That was he was saying.
Of course he is applying it
to mundane art.
Even then he could
understand this principle.
That if it's gonna
be glorified as art
in the true sense,
it must exist by itself
and for Itself,
for its own purpose.
Not any secondary purpose.
It's not useful—
that's what he meant
by saying "useless".
You can't... Not only it's not useful
for something else,
if you try to use it
for another purpose,
it turns into something else.
And that's what he
[Guru Mahārāj] is saying,
"If you use Kṛṣṇa conception
for some other purpose,
then it's not Kṛṣṇa proper.
It's in the name of Kṛṣṇa
and looking like Kṛṣṇa,
but it's not Kṛṣṇa proper."
bhajanīya sarva-sad-guṇa viśiṣṭa
Jīva Goswami is saying,
"When you come in connection
with Kṛṣṇa proper,
you won't try to use Him
for your lower purpose,
you will offer youself to Him,
for His higher purpose".
That's Kṛṣṇa-conception,
that's why there has to be
the concept of the servitor
and the servant and service,
otherwise
one may say, "Oh,
I like Kṛṣṇa, I like God,
I like this, I like that".
As long as He is fulfilling
your lower purpose.
Whereas we...
I heard Guru Maharaj
said today,
"We are meant
to be exploited by Him."
He is not afraid
to use that language.
However politically
incorrect it might sound.
We are trying to understand
the substance of the thing.
To be exploited by
the Absolute Good
is a good thing.
Autocrat—He exists
by Himself and for Himself
to fulfill His own purpose.
We are afraid,
we are suspicious,
but what do you think
the purpose of the Absolute Good is?
Then we need
to understand the saḥ.
Who is He? What is He?
Rasa-rāj—
He is ecstasy personified.
jyotir-abhyantare rūpaṁ
atulaṁ śyāmasundaram
[Nārada-pañcarātra]
Beyond the light
is the beautiful form
of Śyāmasundar Kṛṣṇa.
He is ecstasy personified,
beauty personified,
sweetness personified,
love and affection personified.
Autocrat. [Then,] Despot.
Autocrat, Despot and Liar.
He said, "Alright, Autocrat,
we can understand something,
but Despot?"
"Yes", he said, "Because
if there is any check
on His autocracy,
we'll become the losers."
Therefore Despot.
He's the Absolute Good.
It's not multi-cultural
pluralistic ascending democracy,
but descending
autocratic despotic theocracy.
Now people are really
gonna be worried.
[laughs]
Of course He is the Absolute Good,
do you want to check
His movement?
The way you have
to check in this world,
look over your shoulder,
cover your back.
jīvo jīvasya jīvanam
[SB: 1.13.47]
Because at every moment
one living being
is trying to exploit another.
We don't want to be exploited.
nimitta-mātraṁ bhava savya-sācin
[BG: 11.33]
Kṛṣṇa tells Arjuna,
"It's already done, but
as an instrument of Divine will
you can offer yourself".
And you will also get the credit.
Autocrat, Despot
Despot, so that His Absolute Good
Autocracy is not checked.
But Liar?
When Guru Maharaj was explaining
this, a devotee said,
"Ok, Autocrat, understood,
Despot, understood.
But Liar?"
He said, "Yes! Because
you are not ready to hear the truth!"
So He has taken
the position of a Liar.
parokṣa-vādo vedo 'yaṁ
bālānām anuśāsanam
[SB: 11.3.44]
To gradually give you
exposure to the truth.
Like the way you teach a child.
When Kṛṣṇa...
when Yaśodā inquires from Kṛṣṇa
at the behest of the cowherd boys
complaining against Kṛṣṇa,
"Have You eaten earth?"
"No, they are just complaining
because I'm beating
them in play,
and they are trying to get Me
in trouble with you.
You can see in My mouth
whether there is any earth or not."
And Yaśodā sees within
the mouth of Kṛṣṇa
the Earth planet,
all the solar system,
the Milky way, the Universe,
innumerable Universes...
His lying is liberating
because He is the Absolute Good.