According to the inner awakenment
of the disciple
is how they will see guru.
[Guru | Instructions and Form]
Guru Mahārāj deals with this
in ‘Śrī Guru and His Grace’
and cautioning us against
being overly
emphasizing
the form of the guru.
Like we hear:
vāṇī and vapu.
Vāṇī—instructions,
vapu—the form.
And Guru Mahārāj says,
even as a side point,
even vani can turn into
a type of vapu,
if it becomes lifeless, mindless
parroting of instructions.
But that said, we see, there is picture:
the guru when he’s a young man,
the guru in middle age,
the guru in old age—
which form is it?
That form before us
of Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur,
the beard …
and I’ve told as once
on his veranda in Calcutta
Gurudev said,
“And to think,
he is a fourteen-year-old girl
in Vṛndāvan!”
So, how will you recognize
Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur?
How will you recognize
Guru Mahārāj, Gurudev,
Saraswatī Ṭhākur,
Śrīla Swāmī Mahārāj?
Not by the picture
that you saw here.
Does it mean
to deprecate the picture?
But that is we worship the picture—
the form of the Guru.
But in that plane they’ll be recognized
by devotional tendency.