Very often,
if not most often,
if not all the time,
whom we’re attached to,
we’re projecting something
onto another person.
[Hungry Heart]
We’re so deeply attached
to a person, place or thing,
but where’s the attachment?
It’s not in them,
the attachment is in us,
it’s some conceptual thing.
They symbolically represent something
to us that we feel we cannot break that,
or we’ll somehow become undone,
be unsafe, full of anxiety,
have a meaningless life,
whatever it might be.
But really,
the seed is within us.
So in one place we’re told,
that laulyam, that hṛt-rogam,
that heart disease,
that mundane attachment to
persons, places,
things of this world,
that will be an obstruction
on the path of progressive devotion.
Then, in its counter-śloka,
Krishna-bhakti-rasa-bhavita-matih
kriyatam yadi kuto ’pi labhyate
tatra laulyam mulyam ekalam
janma-koti-sukritair na labhyate
(Cc: Madhya, 2.8.70).
Here, now he’s saying
laulyam is good.
He just said laulyam
is what will spoil devotion,
attachment,
this type of mundane …
Now suddenly there’s
some other type of laulyam
that’s the real thing,
and if you’ve got that,
that’s your ticket, that’s the
purchase price of Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
So then it means, oh, ultimately,
desire, hankering, attachment,
all these things,
they’re not bad.
It’s towards whom
and where that is located.
Deep in the heart’s core?
He’s saying,
“Janma-koṭi-sukṛtair na labhyate”,
you won’t get
this type of hankering
for ten million births
of doing the right thing.
That’s amazing.
Ten million lifetimes of doing
the right thing won’t give you this.
Where will you get what’s required,
this laulyam, this hankering?
… Laulyam can also be described
as hankering,
as Guru Mahārāj would say,
earnest sincere hankering, not curiosity.
We should not confuse
being curious about something
with genuine hankering for
connection with it substantially.
So, that devotee,
actually Shyamananda Prabhu,
he said,
“How to get this hunger?”
That was the word
being used.
And Guru Mahārāj said,
“Associate with the hungry.”
And we know
from being with Śrila Gurudev,
sometimes Vaiṣṇav Maharaj—Shrutashrava Prabhu
would point this out,
even if we had just taken a feast,
if Gurudev started describing prasādam,
different preparations,
he described them
in such a way
that he awakened
your appetite again.
Even if you’d just eaten,
suddenly you were …
he stimulated your appetite.
And that’s what we’re told,
that will happen in association
with those who have
some genuine hunger
and appetite
for Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
If you can’t follow what they’re saying,
serve them,
and what’s in them
will be transferred to you
like an infectious disease
but in a good way.
That’s why they say, “Make sure you
clean the glasses and sterilise everything”,
and we’re saying
the opposite of that,
if someone’s infected
with Kṛṣṇa consciousness,
take their remnants
and you‘ll be infected too,
and that’s a good thing.
And serve them,
and what’s in their heart,
which is not only
the love and affection,
but the hunger, hankering,
attachment, if you will,
attachment to Kṛṣṇa,
to devotion, to devotees,
that will be awakened
in your own heart.
Hare Kṛṣṇa.