We should not think
that our guru-varga
that they’ve given so much for us
to focus on in our study,
and that they forgot,
some really important thing
they forgot to tell us.
And we’ll find that!
[In The Spotlight]
We see sometime
in Goswāmī literature,
when the Vraja-gopīs
are pressed to respond
in some particular situation
that they have extensive knowledge
of the scriptures, Purāṇas …
everything.
And of Sanskrit language,
and all of its intricacies.
So, they’re really …
we’ll say that they
are suppressing
this sort of knowledge,
this aspect of themselves.
It only comes out
under service necessity.
And as we see
in Gaura-līlā,
it’s Braja-gopīs who take on
position of the Goswāmīs.
And they are writing
so many books …
Jīva Goswāmī, the ultimate
Sanskrit scholar;
Rūpa, Sanātan,
Raghunāth Dās—
they are writing
these incredible books;
so many pastimes
in perfect Sanskrit.
nānā-śāstra-vicāraṇaika-nipuṇau
sad-dharma-saṁsthāpakau
lokānāṁ hita …
there you go again—lokānāṁ hita.
… kāriṇau tri-bhuvane mānyau śaraṇyākarau
[Ṣaḍ-goswāmī-aṣṭaka]
They studied all these scriptures
and extracted from them
for the benefit of everyone.
So, really our focus should be
narrow in this sense.
Like Guru Mahārāj said,
“Most exclusive …”
We’re narrowing our focus
to what is all-comprehensive.
We need to focus
on what’s been selected
by the guru-varga
as being substantial;
become acquainted with that
and not avoiding that.
What is the Bengali saying:
The horse …
What’s in front of the horse,
that’s called the trough.
So, there is the trough
full of food, and it says:
“The horse jumps over the trough
and runs in search of food.”
Bengalis are knowing
many things.
[Laughing]
So, they are serving nectar to us
on a golden plate.
And we’re going:
“Is there going to be dessert?
What is he eating
over there?
That guy over in the dark,
I can’t see it.”
[Laughing]
We are own worst enemies.
So, it’s better …
these things are so important,
it’s better to err
on the side of caution.