Once Raivata Mahārāj
went to see Brahmā in Brahmaloka.
He needed to get a suitable husband
for his daughter, Revatī.
[Husband for a Six‒Meter Daughter]
At the time two singers-dancers
were playing named Haha and Huhu.
So, when they finished, a couple
hundred of thousand years went by.
It’s Brahmaloka.
Jet lag. Time zone.
It’s got more time zones
than Russia.
So, all of this time
went by,
and then Brahmā says,
“How can I help you?”
and he said,
“Well, I was looking for a suitable ...
husband for my daughter,
but she’s in the Tretā-yuga,
and now it’s Dvāpara-yuga,
and she’s 17 feet tall.”
You understand?
She’s like, what is that?
It’s almost 6 meters.
She’s 6 meters tall
because that is
the average height of a girl,
kṣatriya-type girl
in Tretā-yuga.
Brahmā is like, “Hmmm,
let me think for a minute, son.”
He came up with Balarāma,
“Is the perfect,
is the only person
who can be her husband.”
But Balarāma is around 15 feet tall,
like 5 meters.
So then they meet,
and he just kind of …
He can do that,
he’s Baladev.
A little gravity
flow thing going …
Made her
appropriately sized.
[Laughing]
And she is happy.