One of Śrīla Guru Mahārāj’s themes was
‘absolute consideration’ and
‘relative consideration’,
and that always we have
to factor in these two things.
[Absolute and Relative Considerations]
And he mentioned as well
that Śrīla Saraswatī Ṭhākur
particularly in his final days
was fond of saying,
“Religion means proper adjustment.”
So adjustment between absolute consideration
and relative consideration.
After Kurukṣetra this one brāhmaṇ
named Uttanka,
he found Kṛṣṇa and he said,
“You Kṛṣṇa, you are responsible
for all these death and distraction,
for creating so many widows …”
Like alluded to in Bhagavad-gītā
varṇa-saṅkara—
illegitimate children, societies,
all the effects, the negative effects
So Uttanka said,
of war and particularly here
the Kurukṣetra war.
“You Kṛṣṇa, you are responsible
for all of these things.
And therefor I’m going
to curse you!”
And Kṛṣṇa said,
“Hold that thought.
Before you do that
consider this:
as a brāhmaṇ, you are situated
in a higher aspect of the saguṇa plane;
saguṇa means with guṇas,
with qualities.
What are those qualities?
tamas, rajas, sattva—
ignorance, passion, goodness.
That’s mundane world.
So the brāhmaṇ being
the highest aspect of the mundane.
It’s a good position.
go-brāhmaṇa-hitāya ca
jagad-dhitāya kṛṣṇāya
[Viṣṇu Purāṇa: 1.19.65]
Kṛṣṇa likes the brāhmaṇs.
We are told the brāhmaṇs’ hearts
are by nature pure.
So it’s a nice
seating place for Kṛṣṇa.
Still it’s a highest aspect
of the mundane.
So Kṛṣṇa’s saying,
“You are from that position
by your austerities, your tapasyā,
your adherence to religious principles,
your saṃskārs,
so much in your favor,
you’ve accumulated this energy
and also in terms of power.
Power over the mundane.
But Kṛṣṇa reminded him,
He said,
“But I’m situated
at the nirguṇa plane.
So you’re going to curse me
from the saguṇa plane
and it’s not going
to have any effect upon me,
because I’m
in the nirguṇa plane.”