[The Love Delusion?]
Many things that we value
are not objectively verifiable—
like humour,
like what we like things
that are funny. Why should we?
I mean humans
are the only animals who really laugh.
They can go,
“No, there’s a laughing hyena!”
—No, that doesn’t count.
[Laughing]
Well, I’m just saying …
So, humans, we laugh,
we cry …
You can say, “Oh, animals wail!”
That’s true,
because they’re approaching human—
they wail when their babies
are taken away and things like that.
You start feeling.
So what we’re all about is feeling.
Not just objective things …
We can say,
“Oh, well we can make you
feel better with chemistry.”
Better living through chemistry,
or as one author said,
“There’s got to be more to life,
and the story of life,
and the possibility of life;
then the narrative says,
‘My chemicals were bad,
I fixed them.’”
So the idea is just about
chemical balances—
happiness is nothing more
than a particular type of chemical balance.
The things that we’re really
hardwired to seek:
beauty, love, humour …
I can’t prove to you
that someone is beautiful.
I can’t prove love even exists,
and statistically
we could make a case
that it doesn’t exist.
And we could say, like they
talk about the God delusion—
we could write a book called
The Love Delusion.
Why is everyone searching for this?
It that no one has it.
They’re all lying to themselves.
It doesn’t really exist.
But there’s an element
with inside us
that can’t accept that
that it doesn’t exist.
And even in the face
of heavily anti-statistical evidence
that you won’t get it,
you’re not experiencing it,
we’ll still search for it.
So it means really, as subjects
we’re in the situation:
we’re spiritual subjects living and
navigating a mundane environment,
searching for subjective inner fulfilment.
So then it becomes obvious—
we need to repurpose ourselves
in addressing that inner fulfilment.
When we try merely
to acquire, control,
and consume objective things,
it doesn’t produce the type of joy
that we’re seeking.