Shelley’s poem
called “Ozymandias”,
which is about one of the kings
of ancient Egypt,
whether it’s Ramses I, II or III
or any one of them, it doesn’t matter.
[No More Moscow, New York, Paris, London …]
And in the poem,
it is very simple,
but a man, he’s saying,
“I met a traveler from an ancient land,
and he told me of this very peculiar,
extraordinary occurrence
that out in the middle of the desert
he saw a broken statue.”
Like, from the waist here
it’s just broken.
The head lying in one place,
this part—in another,
but then from here down
and the legs.
And then there’s an inscription
upon the bottom, the base.
And it says, “I am Ozymandius,
King of the world,
look upon my kingdom!”
And he said,
“But you see the head broke off,
the arms are broken,
and the head lying in the sand
has got this arrogant look.”
He said, “Whoever sculpted it
did a very good job
of conveying the arrogance
of this man.”
But when it says,
“Look upon my kingdom!”
And he said,
“All you can see
in all directions
are the desert sand.”
“There is no kingdom.”
bhūtvā bhūtvā pralīyate
[Bg: 8.19]
Again, the whole world …
what to speak of that kingdom?
Everything appears,
the whole Universe appears,
and then it vanishes
along with everything in it.
Like, Prabhupād would talk
about the cosmonaut
who was in space too long,
and he kept asking them,
“Where is Moscow?”
[Laughing]
He wanted to look out:
“Where is Moscow?”
No more Moscow, no more New York,
Paris, London … [Laughing]
It appears and then it vanishes.
So Guru Mahārāj said,
“That self we want to connect to
and should, it’s living in eternity.”
He’s saying,
“Try and take your stand
in the faithful world,
in the faithful plane.”
But that ‘muktir hitvānyathā rūpaṁ
svarūpeṇa vyavasthitiḥ’ [SB: 2.10.6]
is an identity that is capable
of growth and development.