we can factor in three types of vaishnava
third class second class first class but why
not serve all the Vice navos as possible guru
Mars would say even a new person someone most
newly connected person said if this is everything
we say it is and it is and now they've expressed
appreciation for it and have been accepted
there now connected to it then you have to
respect them and he said God willing maybe I'm
going slowly and they're going very quickly and
they will surpass me I want to be in a position
to receive their grace one day that's grow Mars
is vision so but I think of the time so guru Dave
he arranged the pus chatia vivant made the first
building for the servitors as the the number
of servitors to LaMotte began to expand from
the Western world and like big Gore purnima
festivals coming and guru Dave and service
to all the devotees he's arranging mosquito nets
but it's getting closer and closer to ghorepani
mo and they're not arriving and he's thinking
and this is before the windows had any screens
or anything that's going to be tough difficult
then finally they arrived and Garuda was smiling
like I earth here and he went upstairs am i
with guru Maharaj and he said now everyone
will be happy the mosquito nets have arrived and
guru Mars looked up and he said but the mosquito
suction they will not be happy so he's even
thinking of them they have a place in his heart