They’re thinking
He’s a man like them.
Once when I was at the esplanade
in Kolkata, in 1974,
[Humanlike Parameters of Krishna Conception]
I mean it’s like
a scene from a movie:
I’m from America,
dressed in saffron,
and an Indian, who’s converted
to Christianity, approaches me.
He says, “Hello, my name
is John Thomas.”
And we start talking,
he’s trying to preach to me,
then goes back
and forth a few times,
now there’s 500 people
listening to our conversation.
Like, where do you have to go
to preach?
Just stop at the esplanade
and start talking to somebody.
500 people listening.
And we’re going back and forth,
now he’s asking me a question,
then it comes out, all the mātsarya,
and at the end he goes,
“What I wanna know is why Lord Kṛṣṇa
is dancing with other men’s wives!”
I went, “Aha”,
turned to the crowd,
now we have a big crowd,
it’s like a show,
“Aha, now the truth comes out,
why Lord Kṛṣṇa’s dancing
with other men’s wives.”
And I said, “bhoktāraḿ yajña-tapasāḿ
sarva-loka-maheśvaram (Bg: 5.9);
everyone, including you,
and me, and your wife,
and anyone else’s wife,
belongs to Kṛṣṇa.
Why have you taken
one who belongs to Kṛṣṇa
for your enjoyment?”
And all the people go “aah!”
Then we talked for some time,
and only in India
will someone admit defeat,
he said, “I haven’t properly
read these things,
I’ll have to study
more carefully.”
Aprākṛta, but like mundane,
but not.
Muhyanti yat sūrayaḥ;
even the gods are deceived
by the humanlike parameters
of Kṛṣṇa conception.
The suppressed majesty
and infinite aspect, suppressed.