So, today is makara-saṅkrānti. Means sannyās-līlā,
smaraṇa of Mahāprabhu. And, weṛe going
to speak about that. But, you said you had
something relevant... yeah.
Relevant question. Maybe Mahārāj finds it
irrelevant, just reject it.
Hare Kṛṣṇa.
Why seeing Mahāprabhu in sannyās-veṣ is
as heart breaking as seeing Kṛṣṇa in
dwārakā-veṣ? And, why being the followers
of Mahāprabhu's teachings, the teachings
that were predominantly given by Him after
taking sannyās, we still worship Deities
of Nimāi Paṇḍit, and take the day when
He took sannyās, as one of the saddest?
Alright, with... I think in the course of
the discussion we'll get to that. And... but,
on this point, we can say with mixed emotions,
because of Mahāprabhu's decision to take
sannyās, it's to rescue the fallen souls.
Then, we can say —well, then that should
be a cause for celebration. But, when we factor
in the love of His devotees, and how happy
they are in their pastimes —that He would
have to give that up. That's where the heartbreak
comes. So... but, then we have to consider
the pastimes of Mahāprabhu, as a whole.
So, we're told, “48 years from His appearance,
to His leaving the world.” And, He takes
sannyās at the age of 24. And, just as a
sidebar about today being makara-saṅkrānti.
What is Makara in... what is it?.. Capricorn
in the western... Anyway... but, makara is
a mythical creature in the Bhāgavatam, that
looks somewhere between, shall we say, a dolphin,
an alligator, and... Who has the longest mouth,
the crocodile or the alli... with the... anyway,
like that. It's a mythical, beautiful looking
creature. But... anyway, this time of year
means; it's when the northern course of the
Sun, or the Earth in relation to the Sun.
So, in that sense, it means like, new beginning.
At the end of one period, the beginning of
another. And, that's a simple way of expressing
some comparison. But, it's there. So, the
20... first 24 years have finished. Now, He
will take sannyās, and into the last 24 years.
Which is called the śeṣ-līlā, or the
final pastimes, divided into two sections.
Madhya-līlā —for the first six years or
so. And, then the antya-līlā —for the
last 12 to eighteen. So... but, these first
24 are very significant and sweet. And, they're
the primary subject matter of Śrī Chaitanya-bhāgavat.
As, Guru Mahārāj said once in comparison
—just an inoffensive— some comparison,
when he was saying, “ Chaitanya-bhāgavat
is rāsa without ontology.”
What they say, “Why?..” Chaitanya-bhāgavat
—there's a handful of Sanskrit verses in
the entire work. Really. We're surprised,
in retrospect, to look and see... oh, there's
a handful of Sanskrit verses. The rest...
so, he's saying, “It's rāsa without ontology.”
Chaitanya-charitāmṛta is rāsa with ontology.
There's a thousand Sanskrit verses. And, a
very... of great complexity, and of a comprehensive
nature. And, so many things are expressed
there with Sanskrit. And, Kavirāj Goswāmī
deals with that —about people who might
complain. And say, “Why is this book is
so full of Sanskrit?” And, he's saying,
“First of all...” [laughing] I mean, it's
interesting that he deals with it. But, he
says, “First of all, there is not that much
Sanskrit in it.” It might be a lot for some.
But, he's saying... and... but... “The great
—the Bhāgavatam is all Sanskrit, the commentaries
are Sanskrit. And, this is the way it's expressed.”
And, he's saying, “And, for the most part,
I put in vernacular Bengali, so, that it will
be easily accessible to everyone.” And,
that's true. We can even say, “Well, we're
not native Bengali speakers, but it's been
translated out, and so forth.” But, those
verses, they're not so easy to translate,
rādhā kṛṣṇa-praṇaya-vikṛtir hlādinī
śaktir asmād (Cc: Adi-līlā, 1.5.1). How,
Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa —they're originally
one. then they separate into two— they become
one again. So, Svarūp Dāmodar, as he's saying,
“What, gaura-līlā is first. They are one,
and then, they become two as Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa.
And, then again...” Or gaur... the other...
the inverse?..
Is like, spring, summer, winter, fall?.. I
mean fall, winter... spring, summer, fall,
winter. How, does this cycle go? Or are they
running in parallel, as, Viśvanāth Cakravartī
Ṭhākur suggests. He even says, “The pastimes
of union and separation are running in parallel.”
[chuckling] So, these... and Gurudev said
once, the word... rādhā kṛṣṇa-praṇaya-vikṛtir,
which we can say, generally means... like
'transformation.' He said, “I've been thinking
about this word for 40 years.” That's what
his Divine Grace Śrīla Bhakti Sundar Govinda
Dev-Goswāmī Mahārāj said. “I've been
thinking about this word for 40 years.”
So, that's Chaitanya-charitāmṛtam, but
Chaitanya-bhāgavat—rāsa without ontology.
It's not ontologically heavy.
And, there the early pastimes of Mahāprabhu.
And, as Nimāi Paṇḍit, the scholar. Even,
we can say, pastimes of scholarly arrogance,
at times, appearing that way. [laughing] But,
so much so that was Gadāhar Paṇḍit is
sometimes avoiding Him. But, how sweet is
that? Gadāhar Paṇḍit is Rādhārāṇī,
and, here's Kṛṣṇa as Nimaī Paṇḍit.
And, She has to like... trying to avoid Him
in the street. Why? Because, He'll say, “Oh,
Gadāhar come here, I want to speak to you.”
And, then He'll engage in some sort of philosophical
discussion. And, ask a question —have Gadāhar
answer it— then defeat that. And, fluster
and frustrate Gadāhar Paṇḍit. Then, who's
reconsidering that position that was just
defeated —and, another one reasserting,
“Alright I'll embrace that position.”
— then He'll do the opposite, defeat that
position. Leaving Gadāhar Paṇḍit utterly
frustrated.
But, it like, He's teasing His favorite, His
beloved. And, it's giving some joy. It's actually
giving joy to Gadāhar Paṇḍit. But, theses
kinds of things are there. But, what does
Gadāhar Paṇḍit say, “Nimaī Paṇḍit
is so perfect in every way, and so sweet,
and so extraordinarily beautiful —has one
flaw. He's not a devotee of Kṛṣṇa.”
[laughing] And, if you realize that, I mean
the humor in that, in a sense, is that...
here Rādhārāṇī is Gadāhar Paṇḍit.
Say... Why did Kṛṣṇa descend as Mahāprabhu?
But, to experience bhakta-bhāv—culminating
in rādhā-bhāv. So, it's as if to say, like,
“You're playing in this way as this arrogant
scholar, and you have these other pastimes.
But when are you going to start showing your
devotional colors, and your devotional mood?
They, the devotees, are eager for that.”
And say, “How sweet is this?” These are
all Kṛṣṇa's most intimate devotees.
And, they're... they have restless anticipation.
When is Kṛṣṇa going to start experiencing
devotion? They can't wait, and it's... what's
the word?.. they're just so... you know...
restless or eager in anticipation of that.
But, He will also show how do you get devotion.
See, if He just came and had devotion, that...
that wouldn't be a good example [laughing]
for others. Because, then they would think,
“I am like that, also. I was born that way.”
[laughing]
I don't know why I do that. I just offended
1.3 billion people. But... [laughing] And,
I'm sure, a few other will be added by the
end of the talk. But, that's what I'm saying.
So, what does he show? You get devotion, through
the association of devotees. Even in His case.
So, He must show for sometime —He's not
a devotee. They're praying for that time,
when He will become a devotee. When He will
show devotion. And then we hear, He goes to
Gayā, and ostensibly, to do the śrāddha
ceremony for His departed father. But, when
He returns, He's in gopī-bhāv.
And, some people think He's lost His mind.
Now, He's always singing the praises of the
gopīs. So... we don't... We see... immediately
going for the highest, like, gopī-bhāv.
He comes back... not in, like... a little
bit of it. —He's come back in full blown
gopī-bhāv. So much so, that He's speaking
against Kṛṣṇa. [laughing] ... That's
a heavy conversion. So, who did you convert
into someone who's, like, in opposition to
Kṛṣṇa? Kṛṣṇa! That's pretty heavy.
Now, you've got Kṛṣṇa blaspheming Kṛṣṇa.
[laughing] But, not in any normal way that
one might think. What is He saying? He's in
mān, which means, a type of loving anger
expressed by Rādhārāṇī and the vraja-gopīs
towards Kṛsna.
Which is symptomatic of, how much they are
madly in love with Kṛṣṇa. And, only
want to hear about Kṛṣṇa, only want
to talk about Kṛṣṇa, cannot live without
Kṛṣṇa. So, even the slightest thing,
real or perceived slight, can set them off
into these... and... you know... anger expressions.
So, He's saying, “Kṛṣṇa.” He's chanting
“Gopī, gopī.” He's glorifying the gopīs.
And, some of the students, they object to
this. They're thinking, 'Why are you chanting
gopī, gopī, gopī?” You can chant the
name of Kṛṣṇa, that would be good.”
What is He's saying, “Kṛṣṇa, He's
a despicable man.” [laughing] They're going,
“Oh, you can't say that.” [laughing] “I
just did.”
“The gopīs, they're so great. But, this
Kṛṣṇa, He's causing them so much suffering,
and heartbreak, and...” And, at one point,
we hear, He's chasing one of His students.
He's going to punish him. So, they think,
Nimaī Paṇḍit's running after someone,
a brāhmaṇ, to punish him for suggesting,
that He chant kṛṣṇa-nām. [laughing]
But, the devotees, when they see, they think,
“Did you hear the good news?” “And what
is that?” “Nimaī Paṇḍit's become
a devotee.” “No.” “Yes!” “He,
He, really?” “Yes, now He's a devotee.
He's always lost in gopī-bhāv.” And...
of course... then, the full spectral range
of appreciation is there.
He's madly taking the name of Kṛṣṇa,
exhibiting ecstatic symptoms, they're having
all night kīrtan. Those students could not
understand His gopī-bhāv —that mān, that
loving anger that betrays the depths of kṛṣṇa-prem.
It can only be expressed in the deepest plane.
But, the devotees can recognize this. He...
and then what does he do? Very humbly, He
approaches them and says, “By your grace...”
Because they're so happy to see He's now a
devotee of Kṛṣṇa. He's saying, “By
your grace, I got devotion. By the grace of
all you —devotees, I take the dust from
your feet upon my head for giving me this
greatest gift.” So, He's attributing, and
it must be... He's attributing this new found
devotion to Kṛṣṇa, as being the mercy
of all of the Vaiṣṇavas.
That is perfect, and that is the way it must
be. But, we... so we see, in the pastimes
before taking sannyās, sometimes, momentarily
—almost like temporary insanity —momentary
displays of Divinity. Varāha-avatār, His...
the mahā-prakāś... was sitting on the siṁhasan
for what... 21, 22, 23 hours, giving —liberally
distributing kṛṣṇa-prem to everyone.
That kholā-vecā Śrīdhar comes, whom He
had robbed... His pastime was just cheating
him. The man... he's barely making a living
selling plantain leaves, plantain cup, and
plantain leaf-plates.
And, Nimaī Paṇḍit's always coming by...
And remember, half of what he gets, he gives
towards gaṅgā-pūjā, and the other half,
he's somehow surviving. He has a metal water
pot that's been patched, like, 20 times. It's
an old battered, rusted, hard thing. He has
no... nothing. And, Mahāprabhu always come
to him and go, “I like your leaf-cups and
your leaf-plates. How much are they?” And,
He's saying, “Oh, well this is what I have...”
“Some discount you could give.” “No,
I mean... I've... this is the rock bottom
price...” “Other people are selling for
cheaper...” “Then buy from them...”
“No, I want to buy from you...” [laughing]
“Half off, give me half off.” “No, that's
absurd—half off.” “Half off, and we
have a deal. Deal? Do we have a deal? Half off.”
And, he's charmed by the beauty of Nimaī
Paṇḍit and the sweetness of His ways.
And, he's, “Alright, for you.” Then, when
that... He's showing the mahā-prakāś, and
that Śrīdhar comes, and he's saying, [slapping
of hands] “I'll give you what ever you want.”
That's the time you say, “I want kṛṣṇa-prem,
or I want eternal devotion, I want...” Many
people, they ask for many things. What does
Śrīdhar say, “My desire is that, that
brāhmaṇ who comes and cheats me, day after
day, that He will do that life after life,
eternally. That's what I ask of you.” That's
how we understand who is a devotee, and of
what quality they are. That's what he ask
for, “Continue this.” [laughing]
So, when Nimaī Paṇḍit observes that,
the devotees, they understand His pastimes.
But, those whom He's come, and they've descended
with Him, to enact these pastimes; to participate,
to assist, to spread, extend to others. But,
whom He's meant to deliver —they don't understand.
And, to what degree? They're offending Him.
And, what will be the results of offending
the Supreme entity. So, now He's getting the
actual opposite of... Clearly He descended
for two reasons: One, to relish the bhakta-bhāv,
culminating in rādhā-bhāv. But, on the
other hand, bahirangha sange-kore nam-sankirtan
(Śrīla Bhakti Raksak Sridhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj) —to liberate everyone, with the
nam-sankirtan movement. It's not going that
way.
In fact, they're offending Him. They think,
He's an arrogant person who thinks He's better
than them, and He's lost His mind. Sometimes,
we know, He's laughing madly. Sometimes laughing
for three hours, six hours non-stop. What
would you think? [laughing] And, Mother Śacī,
you know, she's, like, concerned about her
son. And she thinks if she will put some...
what is that?.. like, brāhmi-rasāyan. The
Ayurvedic head tonic, to like, cool your brain
down, bring you back to sanity. She tries
a bottle, a pot, then thinks it's not working.
He's still laughing wildly, madly.
Puts Him in a bathtub, like up to His neck,
in the same liquid. He's splashing around,
laughing madly. Śrīvās Ṭhākur of the
Pañca-tattva comes to visit. And, she's going,
“Śrīvās —Nimaī lost His mind.”And,
he... what does he say to her, “I want a
drop of what He's got. [laughing] Give me
a drop of that Divine substance.” And, then
He stops laughing. He said, “Śrīvās,
if you thought I was crazy, then I would just
leave the world. What's the point. But, that
you understand, that gives me some hope.”
So, the devotees know. But, the non-devotees,
who He has come to liberate, they do not know.
And, in Guru Mahārāj's words, “The patient
is abusing the doctor.” The doctor's, like,
trying to give the medicine, and the patient
is refusing. And, abusing that very doctor
who's come to rescue them.
So, He devises a strategy for this campaign,
that, if I take sannyās —the custom is
such, that everyone will have to show me regard.
They'll have to respect me. And, we know,
as Guru Mahārāj says, “When you accumulate
—that'll means, you'll accumulate sukṛti—
with the accumulation of sukṛti. You'll
acquire the capacity for appreciation.”
That's important to understand. The accumulation
of sukṛti results in acquired capacity for
appreciation. That's how you can appreciate
Kṛṣṇa Consciousness. Because, it's beyond
rational. So, He internally reaches this decision.
Remember, His wife is 14.
This is still Vedic culture. She's 14. Viṣṇu
Priya devī is 14 years old. And, His eldest
brother Viśvarūp, he already took sannyās,
and father's left the world. So, Mother Śacī,
she's under the care of Him. So, He's taking
care of His wife and His mother. So, to take
sannyās means He'll have to leave them. And,
I mean, this would be heartbreaking in a normal
circumstance. But... what to say... We can't
conceive the sort of love that Mother Śacī
has for Nimaī. So, if you can understand
how you... we think that we love people in
this world, you know, our partners, or children,
or parents, or whatever it might be.
If we amplify that, multiply that —ad infinitum,
then what's... how much maternal love could
Śacī-mātā have for Nimaī; Yaśodā for
Kṛṣṇa. Just as Guru Mahārāj said,
when we talk about, sevonmukhe hi jihvādau,
svayam eva sphuraty adaḥ (Cc: Madhya-līlla,
17.136.3-4) —the current. Current... devotional
current of the... the voltage of the devotional
current of the kṛṣṇa-nām of Yaśodā
when she takes Kṛṣṇa's name. The voltage
of the loving devotional current in the kṛṣṇa-nām
of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇi. What is it like,
when she takes Kṛṣṇa's name? What affect
does that have upon Him? They're inseparable.
How can... how... it's heartbreaking for the
devotees. What the... the devotees, they can't
imagine what this will do to Śacī-mātā
and Viṣṇu Priya. It's killing them. Advaita
Ācārya threatens suicide. And, —saying
that— what he thinks, “If I try to do
it in the day, the devotees will stop me.
So, I'm just going to maintain my composure
during the day; tonight I'll finish myself.”
They're like that. So, He... Nimaī Paṇḍit,
before He meets with Nityānanda Prabhu, only
a few know what He's going to do. And, of
course, Nityānanda knows these pastimes,
but... That's where we... it's hard for us
to conceive because, on the one hand, we know
it's like a play. It's līlā, these are pastimes.
But, by the grace of the Goswāmīs, we're
given some insight. So, we know, that Yoga-māyā,
her... one of her functions is to create spiritual
illusion, by which, this is all perceived
to be real. And, that allows them to experience
the greatest depths of emotionality. Because,
we'll think, “Well, they must know, I mean,
that there will be a happy ending.” No,
even in this... look in our own experience.
The Stanislavski Method... Those actors act...
they go so deep into the part, they're lost
in that character. That's the Stanislavski
Method. You can be so immersed in a character,
that you've become that character. You believe
it all to be happening.
If, that can be achieved by mundane actors,
then, what to speak of the eternally liberated
associates of the Lord, under the influence
of Yoga-māyā. So, it's a level of intensity,
and love, and affection, beyond what we can
conceive. It's not a light thing. So, when...
it's heartbreaking to Nityānanda, but when
the devotees think of what it's going to do
to Śacī-mātā and Viṣṇu Priya. They're...
it... they can't digest that... it's just
killing them. And, what we find, that... that
night comes —which was two nights ago—
and, devotees, they all come... and like,
in the evening visit Nimaī Paṇḍit.
He garlands them. He knows He's going; Nityānanda,
Gadādhar, one or two others, Śacī-mātā.
But, those devotees do not know. But, it just
so happens —maybe, perhaps through internal
inspiration— kholā-vecā Śrīdhar, he
comes. Mahāprabhu drank from his water pot
after the first nām-saṅkīrtan, when He
was utterly exhausted and thirsty. That broken,
busted, patched, rusted, water pot, that's
where He drank His water. And, they were,
like, trying to keep it away from Him. And,
He was, like, drinking that water as if it
was the ultimate nectarean substance, because,
it was the water from kholā-vecā Śrīdhar.
So, he comes and brings this lāu, you know,
gourd: pumpkin-like-gourd.
And, Nimaī Paṇḍit saying, “How can
I not honor this before I go?” Someone else
came and brought some milk, and then he told
Śacī-mātā, “Make something.” So, that's
the last thing that He took before taking
sannyās. And then, that night, for some time
He entered yoga-nidrā. And Mother Śacī
knowing that He's leaving, she placed herself
in the doorway, just out of utter desperation.
And then, at around 3 o'clock in the morning,
He awoke. And, when He saw her, He bowed down
before her, “This body belongs to you mother.”
And...
But, to assuage her heartbreak, He saying,
“You are my mother eternally. In Rām-līlā
you are my mother. In every kind of līlā
imaginable, you're always my mother. In Kṛṣṇa-līlā
you're Yaśodā. In all these other Avatārs—
that is you. You're always my mother, eternally
and forever.” Still, it's unbearable, heartbreak
for her —and He leaves. We know, He swims
across the Gaṅgā and goes to Katwa to the
āśram —Keśava Bhāratī Mahārāj's—
and, approaches him for sannyās. And, He's
saying that, “You can give me kṛṣṇa-bhakti.
That's what I've come for. I want devotion
to Kṛṣṇa, you can give that.” And,
Keśava Bhāratī's thinking, “This is kind
of absurd... But...” And, he's hesitant.
We're told in the Bhāgavatam, with regard
to Viṣṇu Priya,
tyaktvā su-dustyaja-surepsita-rājya-lakṣmīṁ
dharmiṣṭha ārya-vacasā yad agād araṇyam
māyā-mṛgaṁ dayitayepsitam anvadhāvad
vande mahā-puruṣa te caraṇāravindam
(Śrīmad Bhāgavatam: 11.5.34)
This verse is interesting in the Bhāgavatam,
because it's equally applicable to Rāmacandra
and Mahāprabhu, the vande mahā-puruṣa
te caraṇāravindam (SB: 11.5.34.4). When
applied to Rāmacandra, it's saying, “He
gave up the imperial throne and together with
Sītā and Lakṣmaṇ, they were exiled to
the forrest.” And, māyā-mṛgaṁ —the
Māyā took the form of a deer and deceived
Sītā. It's telling the rām-līlā in that
way. Viśvanāth Cakravartī Ṭhākur applies
to Mahāprabhu, saying, tyaktvā su-dustyaja-surepsita-rājya-lakṣmīṁ
(SB: 11.5.34.1). Rājya-lakṣmīṁ means
here, Viṣṇu Priya. He's saying, “He
gave up the imperial throne of the love that's
in her heart.” That's what the imperial
throne is—there. The love and the heart
of Viṣṇu Priya, which, is inconceivable
to us. That He had to forgo.
Why, māyā-mṛgaṁ dayitayepsitam anvadhāvad
(SB: 11.5.34.3), to chase after those souls
who are running after Māyā. We're running,
we're deluded by māyā... we're running after
Māyā's illusion. He's chasing after us to
rescue us. To do that, He had to leave the
imperial throne and enshrined in the heart
of Viṣṇu Devī. So, He's there in Katwa
and the word has spread. Sometimes, people
begin to lament, who had offended Him. And,
now we've driven Him out of Nadīyā, Navadwip,
nadīyā-dhārā kore gaura- jaya re. Guru
Mahārāj would sing that, [Goswāmī Mahārāj
singing: nadīyā-dhārā kore gaura- jaya
re].
They're saying, “Oh, the light of Navadwip,
Nadīyā is gone, what have we done.” They're
lamenting. See, already the transformation
is occurring. And, when He comes... Keśava
Bhāratī, it appears, as though, the sun
is entering his āṣram. The effulgence of
Mahāprabhu is so great. And then, he sees
this beautiful 24 year old young man, and
He want to take sannyās, and he's thinking,
“This isn't good, this is not right.”
Usually, in the Ved... dharmā, ārtha, kāma,
mokṣā, you know, at a later stage. When
life, the life cycle, gṛhastha is finished
in the mid 50s or so, then sannyās. But,
here at 24, and such a beautiful, extraordinarily,
inconceivably, beautiful young man.
And, then people are threatening outside,
they're going, “Bhāratī, if you give sannyās
we're going destroy your āśram. Who do you
think you are?” And, we're told, there're
some ladies going, “Who invented this sannyās
anyway? Where does this come from? Who came
up with this idea? That a man, he should leave
his mother and family, what... this is crazy.
Where does... who started this?” They're
all... and the crowd growing... and Keś...
he's thinking how to get out of this. And,
he thinks, “Then, you have to go home and
get your mother's permission.” I mean, it's
India after all. [chuckling] What was I saying?
Then, He starts running and then Keśava Bhāratī
saying, like, “He's so charming, He's so
beautiful, of course, He will convince...
tell Him to come back. Of course, He'll get
permission. Who could refuse Him anything?”
And, they bring Him back. Then, it's time
for the barber. And, that's the part where
the devotees... they... He's so beautiful
with his hair. You know, His hair's long and
it's perfumed, oiled, like, very nice —and
this they can't tolerate. And, His face is
so beautiful, moon-like face, lotus eyes,
curling hair, it's just... they can't... And,
the barber, he's hesitating; no one wants
to do this. They're trying to delay, find
excuses to delay this. Nityānanda can't tolerate
it. No one wants this. And, somehow the day
drags on and on and on, then it's arranged
that they will, the barber will shave His
hair.
And, then... and, Guru Mahārāj has recorded
this in his Premadhāma-deva-stotram, the
lakṣa-lakṣa-koṭi... Tears from the eyes
of million. They're all crying and wailing
to see the hair falling away from the beautiful
moon-like face... of Nitāi... Nimaī Paṇḍit.
And, that barber, He swears... he'll... he
says, “I will never shave another head.
How could I?” And Guru Mahārāj said, “He
later took the occupation of a sweet maker.”
And, it was said, his sweets had some extraordinary
sweetness to them. Having touched sweetness
personified, the cintāmaṇi touch of sweetness
personified, when he made sweets, they had
extraordinary quality and characteristic.
Then he's... who was it?.. Candraśekhara
Ācārya was assigned as His, like surrogate
to do the rituals of sannyās. He didn't do
anything. Candraśekhar did everything, as
a proxy. And, we're told repeatedly, when
they tried to to the ceremony repeatedly,
He will get up and start madly taking kṛṣṇa-nām.
Then, Keśava Bhāratī starts chanting, they
have a kīrtan, then they, like, try to calm
down and go on with the ceremony. And, it
starts again and again. And, then the time
comes for the mantraṁ.
And, right before Keśava Bhāratī is going
to say the sannyā mantraṁ to Him, Nimaī
Paṇḍit said, “A sādhu came to me in
a dream, and, whispered this... mind mantraṁ.
It this the mantra?” And... which we know,
is generally taken to be, 'tat tvam asi.'
It's the māyāvādi... where they're saying,
you know, “You are... 'thou art that', you
are that Brahmā, that ultimate substance.”
That's how they take it. But, when Nimaī
Paṇḍit says this to Keśava Bhāratī,
He's in essence, initiating him with... he's
giving the real actual meaning, “I am His,
I belong to Him.” That's another meaning,
it's gopī-bhāv. Or, if we take even higher,
“You are mine” —is the type of gopī-bhāv
of Rādhārāṇī and Her associates.
So, Keśava Bhāratī says, like... now, he's
initiated by Nimaī Paṇḍit, and saying,
“Yes, that is the mantra.” [chuckles]
You know... Then, He vibrates the mantraṁ,
and He said... And, he's thinking, “What
name shall be given to Him?” And, there's
a system for giving names —108. Śaṅkarācārya
picked 10 and used those out of the 108 for
his line. We generally use all 108. But he...
and there's some system, which kind will be
given, in which combination. And, he's thinking,
“But, none of that applies to you.” And,
he's saying, “Because, the world is forgetful
of Kṛṣṇa Consciousness. And, you have
descended to distributed Kṛṣṇa Consciousness
to everyone.
That means Kṛṣṇa Chaitanya. You have
descended, you are Kṛṣṇa Chaitanya,
you are Kṛṣṇa Consciousness personified.
And your distributing Kṛṣṇa Consciousness
to everyone. So, your name must be Śrī Kṛṣṇa
Chaitanya.” [laughing] And, everyone, “Jaya,
Śrī Kṛṣṇa Chaitanya kī jaya!” And
who was it?.. Śrīnivāsa Ācārya's father
was there at the time. And, when he heard
this 'Chaitanya,' he became half mad. And,
wandered around going, “Chaitanya, Chaitanya,
Chaitanya!” And, when he went to his village,
and everyone will say, “What happened in
Katwa?” “Chaitanya, Chaitanya, Chaitanya!”
Is all he could say.
So, it, as if it goes without saying, he became
known —whatever his former name was, he
became known as Chaitanya Dās. [laughing]
So, then Nimaī Paṇḍit, He jumps up and
He's saying,
kāhāṅ mora prāṇa-nātha muralī-vadana
kāhāṅ karoṅ kāhāṅ pāṅ vrajendra-nandana
(Śrī Chaitanya-caritāmṛta: Madhya-līlā,
2.15)
Search for Śrī Kṛṣṇa, —reality the
beautiful, immediately. That's... He's searching
for... how,
etāṁ sa āsthāya parātma-niṣṭhām
adhyāsitāṁ pūrvatamair mahadbhiḥ
ahaṁ tariṣyāmi duranta-pāraṁ
tamo mukundāṅghri-niṣevayaiva
(Śrī Chaitanya-caritāmṛta: Madhya-līlā,
3.6)
It was Kṛṣṇa to... would have... told
this... I mean this story... the Avantī Brāhmaṇ.
This verse is invoked at the time of sannyās,
when he's saying, “I will cross over the
ocean of nescience. How? By following all
those sannyāsīs before me.” And, what
did they do? tamo mukundāṅghri-niṣevayaiva
(Cc: Madhya-līlā, 3.6.4), mukunda-sevā,
kṛṣṇa-sevā, serving the lotus feet.
That's how. In that way, it can be... it is
achieved through sevā, not through, so-called
renunciation, vairāgya, this... that. What
is it?.. nirbandhaḥ kṛṣṇa-sambandhe
yuktaṁ vairāgyam ucyate (Brs: 1.2.255.2)
of Rūpa Goswāmī. Through service, through
sevā —tamo mukundāṅghri-niṣevayaiva
(Cc: Madhya-līlā, 3.6.4).
With that verse, and He's going, and with
Nityānanda Prabhu and others. And, He's immediately
heading toward Vṛndāvan, that's His goal.
Search for Śrī Kṛṣṇa, go to Vṛndāvan.
As we were just saying earlier, Prabupād
liked this verse... well, he liked the whole
thing. But, particularly, last verse of Sad-Gosvami-Astakam;
he rādhe vraja-devīke ca lalite he nanda-sūno
kutaḥ (Sri Sri Sad-Gosvami-Astakam: 8.1).
They're saying, “Where is the son of Nanda?
Is He on the bank... kālindī-yamunā, on
the banks of the Yamunā? Or is He with the
vraja... Where is He? Saying, that is the
essences of Kṛṣṇa Consciousness —the
search for Śrī Kṛṣṇa. In the search
is value. They never say, “Oh, now I've
got. Now we've captured the Infinite.”
Sometime, momentarily... Sometimes the higher
devotees, you know, Advaita will see that
in a few days —when he's got Him in Śāntipur.
He can say that. “Now, I've got you. [laughing]
You've tried to deceive me and hide, and I've
got you.” Momentarily, but generally, always
in the search, the search for Śrī Kṛṣṇa;
kṛṣṇa-anusandhān. When we published
Search for Śrī Kṛṣṇa, Śrīla Guru
Mahārāj's, we're so often invoking, and
saying, you know, brahma-jijṅāsā; athāto
brahma-jijṅāsā (Vedānta-sūtra 1.1.1)
—it's Vedānta. That, now is the time to
inquire about, you know, Brahmā. What did
Guru Mahārāj say?, “Brahma-jijṅāsā
—that is a dry thing.” Means general spiritual
inquiry. What is the time now? Kṛṣṇa-anusandhāna,
rāsa-jijṅāsā, inquire about that.
The heart's inner necessity personified as
Kṛṣṇa, rasa-rāja’, ‘mahābhāva’
— dui eka rūpa (Cc: Madhya-līlā, 8.282.2).
Rādhārāṇī and Kṛṣṇa, rasa-rāj
—Kṛṣṇa, mahābhāv —Rādhārāṇī,
combined as one, in Mahāprabhu. … kandarpa-koṭi-kamanīya-viśeṣa-śobhaṁ
(Bs: 5.30.3), 10 million cupids personified
as one, points in the direction of the seductive
charm, beauty, and sweetness of Kṛṣṇa.
So, he's saying, “What, He's reality the
beautiful, ecstasy personified.” What could
be more beautiful than that… If you took
Rādhārāṇī... Here's Kṛṣṇa... one
thing... Rādhārāṇī —the inconceivable
beauty of Rādhārāṇī, is such, that She...
Kṛṣṇa's irresistibly drawn in an attraction
to Her. What would happen if you combined
them as one? Then, that's inconceivable of
inconceivable things, and inconceivable beauty.
So, Guru Mahārāj would... Brahmā's saying,
kandarpa-koṭi-kamanīya-viśeṣa-śobhaṁ
(Bs: 5.30.3), 10 million cupids personified,
hint at the beauty of Kṛṣṇa. What is
Guru Mahārāj saying, and Rūpa Goswāmī
as well, says... what is it?..
rasoddāmā kāmārbuda-madhura-dhāmojjvala-tanur
yatīnām uttaḿsas taraṇikara-vidyoti-vasanaḥ
hiraṇyāṇāḿ lakṣmī-bharam abhibhavann
āńgika-rucā
sa caitanyaḥ kiḿ me punar api dṛśor
yāsyati padam
(Śrī Stava Mala: Volume 1 Prathama Caitanyastaka.4)
What is the beauty of the sweetness of the
form of Mahāprabhu? Ten million cupids in
full bloom cupidity. That sort of sweet, dazzling,
you know... like... beautiful, molten-gold
Gaurāṅga. But, what does Guru Mahārāj
say, “koṭi-kāma-mūrchitāṅghri-rūpa-rāsa-raṅgaraṁ,
prema-dhāma-devam eva naumi gaura-sundaram
(Pds: 2.3-4), svarṇa-koṭi-darpaṇābha-deha-varṇa-gauravaṁ
((Pds: 2.1) —10 million brilliant mirrors
of shining gold.” Sometimes, he said, like,
“When His hair stands on end it's like the
Kadamba flower.” That's when, in a nice
way... Other times like thorns, when the ecstasy
goes in another direction.
Imagine, that —hairs that become like thorns.
[svisht] Other direction, like Kadamba flowers
with saffron pollenate... you know... sprinkled
all over. But, he's saying, svarṇa-koṭi-darpaṇābha-deha-varṇa-gauravaṁ,
padma-pārijāta-gandha-vanditāṅga-saurabham,
koṭi-kāma-mūrchitāṅghri-rūpa-rāsa-raṅgaraṁ
(Pds: 2.1-3), means 10 million cupids will
faint to see the beauty of Gaurāṇga-Mahāprabu.
That's another way of thinking, that 10 million
cupids fainting. How beautiful is that? And,
that Mahāprabhu, He's searching for Kṛṣṇa,
running madly. And, Guru Mahāraj said, “In
almost like a child-like state of Divine ecstasy.”
And, the devotees are following Him, but there's
no... He's not going in the right direction.
Instead of going towards the West, He's going
towards the East, He's going North, South.
He's going all over, and it's as if, the love
and affection of the devotees in Navadwip,
is pulling that, He can't escape that. So,
He's circling. The pull of their hearts is
so great upon Him, He can't break it. So,
it's... He's circling. Until, at last, remember,
He's in this divine madness state, and Nityānanda,
they find Him. Sometimes, they're separated
from Him. They can only find Him by this piteous
wailing. He's crying for His beloved Kṛṣṇa.
So, Nityānanda tells some cowherd boys, “If
this sannyāsī comes by, and He ask you where
the Yamunā is, point in this direction.”
And, at one point, Mahāprabhu, He's, you
know, He's singing, dancing, but He's becoming
a little disappointed, thinking, “I don't
hear any kṛṣṇa-nām, here in this part
of the world, in this part of the country,
what's the matter?”
And, then He sees the cowherd boys. And, they're
going, like, “Haribol, Haribol!” And,
He thinks, “Ahhhh, Vṛndāvan!” Because,
they're dressed like cowherd boys and they're
saying Hairbol. He make that conclusion. “I've...
where is Yamunā?” And, the go, “This
way.” And, He baths in the Yamunā, which
is the western side of the Gaṇgā. And,
He's so happy, cid-ānanda-bhānoḥ sadā
nanda-sūnoḥ (Cc: Madhya-līlā, 3.28.1).
He's praising Yamunā... prema... what is
it?.. ...brahma-gātrī (Cc: Madhya-līlā,
3.28.2)... prema —river of prem. And, then
He sees, there's Nityānanda, there's Advaita
Ācārya, waiting on the shore with clean...
His cloth is all wet.
And, he's waiting there with clean sannyās
cloth. And, Mahāprabhu says to him, “Advaita,
how did you know I was in Vṛndāvan?”
And, Advaita said, “Chahahaha, you're kidding?
Wherever you are —that is Vṛndāvan. Wherever
you go, it's... you know... you're that person.
Wherever you are is Vṛndāvan. How did I
know you were in Vṛndāvan. What kind of
a question is that?” And, then He's coming
out of His trance, realize, “Oh, I've been
duped by Nityānanda. Haaa... I'm prey to
tricks of Nityānanda.” He said, “Well,
Nityānanda didn't actually lie, because it's
the Gaṇgā, and western side is considered
Yamunā, so, technically it's not a lie.”
But, anyway [laughing] you come to my house
in Śāntipur.”
And, that's when the devotees get some relief.
They send Nityānanda to Mother Śacī, who
hasn't eaten or moved for days. She told the
devotees, “You're the natural inheritors
of everything He has, you take everything.”
And, it was heartbreak for them, to see her
like that, and Viṣṇu Priya. But then we're
told, Nityānanda comes and tells Mother Śacī,
“We're all going to meet in Śāntipur,
at the house of Advaita. And, your beloved
Nimaī, who's now Śrī Kṛṣṇa Chaitanya
Mahāprabhu, He will be there and you'll get
to see Him and cook for Him, and” Then Mother
Śacī cooks for Nityānanda and all the devotees.
She makes a big feast. Feeds Nityānanda,
all the devotees, and then she takes a little
prasādam, then they're all happy. Now, everyone's
happy again. They're going to Śāntipur.
So, Bhaktivinod Ṭhākur... And we hear,
when He does go there —as He goes to other
places... When the words spreads that Mahāprabhu
will appear, hundreds of thousands, if not
millions, run in that direction. And, we're
told also, that the gods and goddesses, of
the higher planets, they descend into this
world and blend in, in human forms. Because,
they want to see Him also. So, it becomes,
like, millions. And, they're going, “Where
did all these people come from?” Some of
them have descended from the higher planetary
systems. So, they're madly going. When they
go to the river, there's the river man with
the boat. They get on the boat, the boats
are sinking. Wherever the boats sinks, by
Mahāprabhu's grace, it... there's a sandbar
beneath.
In other cases, they take big pots, turn them
upside-down, and cross the river in that way.
Sometimes, there's so many people going across
the river, that it's like, a biblical parting,
nobody can drown. Just so many people go,
nobody can drown, they just keep going. The
water's parting. [laughing] And, when they
see Him, they're climbing trees. And, suddenly
twigs, on trees, can support human bodies.
Mystical things are... and, everyone just
wants to have a glimpse of the beauty of Mahāprabhu.
They'll ask Him to come out, like in the case
of Vidyā-vācaspati. He'll come out, like,
on the rooftop and wave His arms, and everyone
starts chanting. “Haribol, Haribol, Haribol,
Haribol.” And, they have some kīrtan and
everyone's happy drinking the beauty of Mahāprabhu
with their eyes.
But, it's at that time, that Bhaktivinod Ṭhākur,
in his song, he's taking himself as one of
the inhabitants of Vidyānagar. Who's seen
Mahāprabhu on that rooftop. And, he's saying,
as someone from Śrīvās-aṅgan, saying,
“When will Nimaī Paṇḍit give up the
robes of renunciation and join us again in
our happy kīrtans in Śrīvās-aṅgan. When
will that day come?” And, Guru Mahārāj
is pointing out, “This parallels Rādhārāṇī
and vraja-gopīs saying, 'When will Kṛṣṇa
give up this kingly dress, the Mahārāj dress
of Dwārakā. He's a Mahārāj there.
He'll give up the Mahārāj dress and come
and join with us in our rāsa-līlā back
in Vṛndāvan, on the banks of the Yamunā.'”
So, Guru Mahārāj has identified —This
is the same sentiment. Bhakitvinod saying,
“When will he give up this Mahārāj dress
and come and join us again in Śrīvās-aṅgan.”
So, sometimes Guru Mahārāj would say, as
the entrance,
yathā yathā gaura-padāravinde
vindeta bhaktiṁ kṛta-puṇya-rāśiḥ
tathā tathotsarpati hṛdy akasmāt
rādhā-padāmbhoja-sudhāṁbu-rāśiḥ
(Chaitanya-chandrāmṛta: 88)
Prabodhānanda saying, “Give your full attention
to the lotus feet of Gaurāṇga-Mahāprabhu.”
Those who are sukṛtivān, sumedhasaḥ;
yajanti hi su-medhasaḥ (SB: 11.5.32.4),
refine theistic intellect. They will understand
that, by giving everything, focusing exclusively
on the lotus feet of Mahāprabhu in gaurā-līlā.
They will enter kṛṣṇa-līlā, rādhā-padāmbhoja-sudhāṁbu-rāśiḥ
(Ccd: 88), and subconsciously, automatically
deep from within the hearts core, the rādhā-rāsa-sudhā-nidhi
will begin to flow. In other words, they will
spring out of the soil of Vṛndāvan engaged
in rādhā-dāsyam. So... why did I say this?..
Because... Oh, Guru Mahārāj saying...
So, as gaurā-līlā is the entrance to kṛṣṇa-līlā,
as every atom of Navadwip is capable of giving
Vṛndāvan in full, so, also, the nām-saṅkīrtan
of Mahāprabhu... Gaurā-līlā is magnanimous
distribution of kṛṣṇa-līlā. Navadwip
is distributing Vṛndāvan. The nām-saṅkīrtan
is the rāsa-līlā in distribution mode.
How inconceivable is that?
(yadi) gaura nā hoito, tabe ki hoito,
kemane dharita de?
rādhāra mahimā, prema-rasa-sīmā,
jagate jānāta ke
(Yadi Gaura Nā Hoito: Vasudev Ghosh, 1)
Why did Kṛṣṇa come to... bahirangha
sange-kore nam-sankirtan (Śrīla Bhakti Raksak
Sridhar Dev-Goswāmī Mahārāj), with His...
general... His associates... generally to
nām-saṅkīrtan, distributing krṣṇa-prem,
giving other entrance. But, what is His internal
thing, antarangha sange-kore rasa-asvadan
(Śrīla Bhakti Raksak Sridhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj), to taste rāsa. Who is rāsa?
Not just, what is rāsa. Whom? Rāsa-rāj
is Kṛṣṇa. So, as Guru Mahāraj says,
“Sweetness is tasting itself.” Because,
you see, everyone is mad after sweetness,
and sees the effects that sweetness has upon
people. He thinks, “I want to experience
the same.” So, sweetness tasting itself,
and becoming mad, as an outcome, expressed
in ecstatic dance and song. So, it's said,
“The cause is the effect —the effect is
the cause.” ātma-siddha-sāvalīla-pūrṇa-saukhya-lakṣaṇaṁ
(Pds: 66.1), the ultimate conception of the
ultimate reality is, He's singing and dancing.
Why? On the account... if, He... Īśopaniṣads
say,
oṁ pūrṇam adaḥ pūrṇam idaṁ
pūrṇāt pūrṇam udacyate
pūrṇasya pūrṇam ādāya
pūrṇam evāvaśiṣyate
(Īśopaniṣad: Invocation)
So, it... pūrṇa, just doesn't mean 'full,'
like, you know, a glass is full. It also means;
complete, fulfilled, utterly fulfilled, totally
fulfilled. That is the position of ecstasy
personified. But, in this case, the Supreme-positive
is taking the position of the Supreme-negative.
To relish... Kṛṣṇa relishing His own
name. Only, from the position of a devotee
—can. As Kṛṣṇa —not. But, as a devotee
—and not only devotee— we're back to the
voltage of the kṛṣṇa-nām of Rādhārāṇī.
With rādhā-bhāv, how tasteful is Kṛṣṇa.
He's experiencing that. And, that is making
Him so happy and fulfilled. Like, in the true
sense of the word —ecstatic— means beyond
yourself.
He's besides Himself, beyond Himself. The
end result is it's expressed in ecstatic dance
and singing of kṛṣṇa-nām, which is
the nām-saṅkīrtan movement. So, we're
supremely fortunate, that on this day, Mahāprabhu,
He —despite the personal heartbreak involved,
and it's something real and true. Mother Śacī,
Viṣṇu Priya Devī, and all the devotees,
that to say —rescue all the fallen souls.
He did this. [clearing voice]
So, it's the gift of Mother Śacī, Viṣṇu
Priya, Advaita Ācārya, Haridās Ṭhākur,
all the great devotees. So, the... when I
asked Guru Mahāraj once, I said, “So, which
shall we consider?,,” We see the depths
of rāḍhā-bhāv plunged in the pastimes
in Purī. Particularly in the Gambhīrā,
behind closed doors with Svarūp Dāmodar
and Rāmānanda. So, then I thought, “But,
then... what about Navadwip. Which would be
considered, you know, higher?” And, I'll
never forget. Guru Mahārāj said, “Stalwart
followers of Mahāprabhu prefer Navadwip.”
[laughing]
And, then I could understand. So, it... from
one point of view, we'll say, “The depths
of rādhā-bhāv are plunged behind closed
doors in Purī.” But, all of this does not
make the devotees happy. To see the beautiful
locks of Nimaī shorn away, when He takes
sannyās. The results of those ecstatic symptoms,
it's giving some pain in their hearts. They
only... they want these happy pastimes like
they had in Navadwip. That's the 'good old
days' for them. So, he said, “Stalwart followers
of Mahāprabhu, they prefer Navadwip.” And,
then the evidence of Bhaktivinod Ṭhākur
given in that song, When Will He Join Us Again.
So, all these thing have to be considered
very carefully.
But, at the heart of the matter, is union
in separation. As, Guru Mahārāj... “Necessity
indicates separation.” This is his point.
We have some particular necessity. Necessity,
and it means, we don't have that thing. So,
in that sense, we're separated. And, we know,
hunger produces relish. When you're really
hungry, then you really enjoy... that's when
you enjoy eat... every morsel is just wonderful.
Like the saying, 'hunger is the best spice.'
It's that principle that's... and... and,
thankfully, mercifully, this is something
that's realistic for us to culture. For neophytes,
to try and cultivate pastimes of union, is
not realistic, it's inappropriate, and it's
damaging.
Because, we can't see beyond our senses and
mundane sensuality, at this point. So, we'll
make the grave mistake of imposing mundane
sensuality upon, the objective world, upon
the super subjective sensuality of the aprākṛta-līlā
of Kṛṣṇa. That's a grave mistake. But,
we see the highest, the greatest depths of
kṛṣṇa-prem are mined from the position
of separation, bāhye viṣa-jvālā haya,
bhitare ānanda-maya, kṛṣṇa-premāra
adbhuta carita (Cc: Madhya-līlā, 2.50.3-4).
And, this is a subject matter of Chaitanya-charitāmṛtam.
As, Gurudev said, “What is Mahāprabu's
tasting matter?” It's tasting what you feel
in separation.
It's achieved the deeper region of heart.
Therefore, a deeper type of love and more
tasteful. A deeper sort of relish. And, that
is... this is supreme mercy, in that. That's
the position that is realistic for us. Because,
if one thing we know, we are separated from
Kṛṣṇa. So, that's the only legitimate
sort of culture for us. But, it happens to
yield the very highest things. So, how fortunate
we are. And, Mahāprabhu has come demonstrating
this, in His pastimes. Hare Kṛṣṇa. [clapping
hands] Śrī Kṛṣṇa Chaitanya Mahāprabhu's
sannyāsa-līlā smaraṇam ki! jay!
Jay!
Hare Kṛṣṇa. And, that's why the devotees
don't like to see that... they... so, we worship
Mahāprabhu, not with a shaved head. But,
looking like Nimaī Paṇḍit. [laughing]