You can see guru according to
the inner awakenment of the disciple.
[The Guru is Not a Picture]
The guru is not a picture.
And Guru Mahārāj makes the the obvious point,
he said, “What if you have pictures of the guru
from when he was twenty, twenty-five,
thirty, thirty-five, forty, etc.,
and the form is changing dramatically,
then which one?”
What is Guru?
Is Guru that form you saw at twenty,
twenty-five, fifty …?
As we saw, the picture of
Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur with the big beard.
And Gurudev once said,
on his veranda in Kolkata,
he said, “And to think, he’s a
thirteen-year-old girl in the spiritual world”,
but he’s sitting there with the beard.
So he’s talking about his svarūp,
and his highest expression
in the spiritual domain.
So it’s according to the inner
awakenment of the disciple
that they have some depth of seeing guru.