The person next to us,
they have their karmic circumstance,
their sojourn
in the material world
that’s brought them
to this particular point
and time, place,
and circumstance.
[How to Find Inner Peace]
We have to accept that
for the most part.
And if the Paramātmā
is non‒interfering,
the Paramātmā,
the Super-soul,
the Over-soul,
is not meddling
in the situation,
because that would be
to interfere with the jīva‒soul’s
minute independence.
There can be suggestion,
but not interference.
What does
the Upaniṣads say?
dvā suparṇā sayujā sakhāyā
[Upaniṣads: 4.6]
in one place.
Like two birds on a tree.
The tree is karmic activity.
One bird is
the individual soul,
the other bird is
the Super-soul, Paramātmā,
overseer, observer,
who is observing jīva
as she tastes the fruits
of karmic activity.
So, sometimes
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj would say ...
If you can embrace
this concept.
And it’s thematically resurfaces
at different times in Bhagavad-gītā:
bhoktāraṁ yajña-tapasāṁ
sarva-loka-maheśvaram
suhṛdaṁ sarva-bhūtānāṁ
jñātvā māṁ śāntim ṛcchati
[Bg: 5.29]
It says, “jñātvā māṁ—knowing this,
what's just been described—if you know this,
then śānti;
Om śānti, śānti, śānti ...
You can get a little bit
of peacefulness in the world,
if you understand
that in the background
that person for whom we say,
as, again, the aphorism says,
“Not a blade of grass moves
without the will of God.”
It obviously moves
without our consent.