Raspberries
that I like very much;
Vijay always brings me
like a big bowl of them.
Raspberries
that are so delicate
that even underscores
the point,
they’re so soft and delicate,
then they can
come out of the soil.
It’s predicted
in the Bhagavad-gītā.
[I’m the Wonderful Taste]
puṇyo gandhaḥ pṛthivyāṁ ca
[Bg: 7.9]
Kṛṣṇa says, “I’m the …
what you get out of your …
I’m that.”
The gandhaḥ—
the original fragrance
of the Earth,
All these varieties of aroma …
He’s raso vai saḥ, it’s Kṛṣṇa.
These things
should not be seen
or appreciated separately,
divorсed of Kṛṣṇa conception,
raso ’ham apsu kaunteya
[Bg: 7.8]
He’s expressing,
when you taste something,
and you,
“Oh, this is wonderful taste!”
raso ’ham apsu kaunteya—
it’s Kṛṣṇa,
directly and indirectly.