God helps those that help themselves.
There has to be something from your side.
[God Helps Those Who Help Themselves]
Very often we meet someone
in Krishna consciousness,
and they will say that they like Krishna,
they like the devotees,
they like Krishna, they like everything,
everything, and they accept everything.
But then you say,
“But what about initiation?”
and I remember, we were
in … Kazan, that’s the city, right?
So, and someone had been given
the japa-mala before initiation,
and they said, “I’ve got everything,
why do I need? I have …”, you know.
They will make some case like that.
Sometimes I have told them that yes,
it’s good that you accept everything.
You are accepting Krishna,
Krishna conception, and that’s wonderful.
That’s what we want—varaṇa.
Śravaṇa-daśā—hearing stage,
and then varaṇa—acceptance.
But acceptance has to be mutual.
It’s not a one-sided affair.
So, there is the acceptance
from your side, that’s good.
Then what we need is the recognition from
the upper world of the mutual acceptance.
That from the upper world
or the agent of the upper world
that you have been accepted
as sincere … what Gurudev
would call ‘a sincere seeker’:
“My Guru Maharaj told me, ‘Wherever
you will meet sincere seekers,
you will extend this
Krishna-nama to them.’”
Krishna-prema bija-prada:
“You will give them
the seeds of Krishna-prema
through this Hari-nama.”
So it has to [be] …
there should be this mutual acceptance.
That’s something else to factor in.
God helps those that help themselves.
Something from your side
indicating your sincerity,
your desire for a connection
with Divinity,
your desire for some help,
some shelter, all of these things.