Our taking of Kṛṣṇa-nam
is a service aspiration,
not to free ourselves
of impending karmic reactions.
[Guns, God, and Goodness]
Like Flannery O’Connor, a famous writer,
southern writer of short stories,
she has a famous short story called
A Good Man is Hard to Find,
and without going into
the details of the story …
some family who's out for an outing,
their car brakes down, blah blah blah …
long story short: in the end there's
a man who's trying to kill them all,
and when he points the gun
to this one woman,
at that point she becomes
very religious
—this is sort of like
the key part of the story—
and she makes this sort of, you could say,
cynical, or s[notty]... an observation, she's saying …
Gee, I mean,
she would have been very fortunate
if at every moment in her life
someone had a gun
pointed to her head.
Then she would have
really been holy.
So, the devotees are not taking
Kṛṣṇa-nam or aproaching Kṛṣṇa
to escape impending
karmic reactions,
but rather
offering themselves in service
to the lotus feet of
Guru and Gauranga, Rādhā-Govinda,
and whatever service will come
through that line to them,
they’re very honored, privileged,
happy to accept that.
Guru Mahārāj made the point,
he said that in the spiritual world—
you can see in posters
or you won’t see in posters—
gopīs chanting on the japa-mala.
You don’t hear … some Vraja-gopīs,
they go, “We need, you know
it’s time to churn the butter,
make yoghurt”,
[and another gopī replies],
“No, I've got to chant my rounds.”
[laughs]
No, we’re told, when
they’re churning, their bangles
are making some sound,
and they're singing
about the pastimes of Kṛṣṇa.
Viśvanāth Chakravartī Ṭhākur
and others like to point out,
when some events
happen in Vṛndāvan,
these Vraja-gopīs, they’re very
capable poets, singers, composers—
they start composing songs
spontaneously
about the pastimes of Kṛṣṇa,
while they’re doing their different sevā.
Vande Nanda-vraja-strīṇāḿ
pāda-reṇum abhīkṣṇaśaḥ
yāsāḿ Hari-kathodgītaḿ
punāti bhuvana-trayam
[SB: 10.47.63].
And this vibration that’s coming from them
is purifing everywhere,
and they’re just churning butter,
making different things,
going about
their household duties,
because at that point, Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
said, “Kṛṣṇa-nam is automatic,
they’re situated in Kṛṣṇa-nam.”
Kṛṣṇa-mantra haite habe saṁsāra-mocana
Kṛṣṇa-nāma haite pābe Kṛṣṇera caraṇa
[Cc: 1.7.73].
The mantram, a mantra with Kṛṣṇa in it,
will liberate one (saṁsāra-mocana);
but Kṛṣṇa-nam
—a contrast is being drawn here:
Kṛṣṇa-nam will take one to the service
of the lotus feet of Kṛṣṇa,
and when one has achieved that,
it’s on automatic.
Hare Kṛṣṇa.