The progressive position
is the intermediate position;
progressive devotion is enacted
from the intermediate plane,
vision of madhyama-adhikārī.
[Guru: Heavier than the Himalayas]
Guru Mahārāj also pointed out,
in Gauḍīya Maṭh, he said,
“Controversy was kept
from the neophyte section
because they will be unable
to handle that—laghu.
Guru means ‘heavy’,
heavier than the Himalayas.
Laghu means ‘light’,
light as a feather.
So we see what is the cliche,
stereotype—light as a feather.
A breeze comes in,
lifts the feather up,
it’s twirled around
and then falls in there.
Another breeze comes, lifts the feather up,
drops it in another place.
The plight of the neophyte—
hearing one thing:
“That makes sense!”,
and going in the …
hearing in another place the opposite—
going in another place:
“That makes sense!”,
going that plane …
Confusion.
Unable to discriminate
between higher, lower,
desirable, undesirable,
genuine devotion, feigned devotion,
counterfeit devotion;
what is condemned
cannot understand
what is in their own interest.
So laghu has to connect to guru.
Why guru is heavier
than Himalaya?
tasmād guruṁ prapadyeta
jijñāsuḥ śreya uttamam
śābde pare ca niṣṇātaṁ
brahmaṇy upaśamāśrayam
[SB: 11.3.21]
When we are indicated
to go to guru.
What is guru—
brāhmaṇa;
totally, so much sheltered
in the spiritual conception,
cannot be moved by any misconception,
that personality.
Sometimes Guru Mahārāj would say
this śikhā, will be …
he says,
“Take the śikhā and tie—
the laghu disciples shall tie their śikhā
to the lotus feet of guru.
So when the winds of misconception come,
being tossed this way and that way,
still being tied
to the lotus feet of Gurudev,
will survive the onslaught
of misconception.
So ... and, just to continue
the conceit, that
guru kāraṇa ... dhāraṇam—
the captain of the boat—
human form of life being the boat,
the guru being the captain
and the winds are vedā, Kṛṣṇa coming …
how to negotiate those winds,
is how to sail the boat properly.
What was it that I saw
the other day,
when you go into the wind?
What is it called?
It’s a nautical term.
Where they decide at some
point to turn the boat and ...
Tack!
So it is called ‘tack’.
So sometimes what
appears to be counterintuitive,
guru will know that
what is favorable, what is unfavorable.
Laghu needs to be
in connection with guru,
the disciple needs to be
in connection with guru
to properly navigate,
to understand
what is the purport
of the scriptures.