Whenever you make
an intellectual approach
to Divine substance,
that can be the end result.
It could be anything,
is the point.
[The Gods are Bewildered]
Kṛṣṇa consciousness’ beginning,
middle, and end is the culture of faith.
So, that’s why Brahmā,
He also had questions
that could not be answered.
How can a five-year-old
cowherd boy …
He doesn’t have
four arms like Viṣṇu,
He’s not carrying
a giant scepter with jewels,
He has a stick in His hand,
and a flute stuffed in His belt,
and food in His left hand,
and He’s eating with His friends
on the banks of the Jamunā.
So, he has questions,
he’s going like,
“How can that be God?
I know Nārāyaṇ, he looks like God—
four arms,
crown, lot of aiśvarya,
that sounds …
seems to be God.”
This is supposed …
All these grown adults
bowing down to a little boy
with His stick.
You’ve seen the sticks,
that kind of stick.
We see them, they still do it—
the little cowherd boys in India.
They have a little stick, they tap
the calves with, for herding them.
So He has a stick,
flute in the belt,
food in the palm,
eating with His friends.
So, muhyanti yat sūrayaḥ
[SB: 1.1.1],
the Bhāgavatam tells you
in the beginning,
“Gods are bewildered in trying
to understand Kṛṣṇa conception.”
Brahmā-vimohan, Indra-mohan,
Mohinī-mūrti with Śiva.
If we think, we are going to know
every last detail,
then it’s not Kṛṣṇa conception.
Saraswatī Ṭhākur said,
“Then why He is called adhokṣaja,
adhaḥ akṣaja?”
What are we told? Akṣaja—
the eyes, the senses;
adhaḥ means, when He decides
to reveal something of Himself to you,
all your sense experience
is pushed down,
so that can happen.
It’s suppressed.
The inversion meaning—when you
are in full-blown sense experience,
what is Saraswatī Ṭhākur saying,
“Trying to, like vultures,
looking for vulture food:
the eyes want
to devour something,
the ears want
to hear the sweet sound,
the tongue wants to taste …
Like vultures.”
That’s why Guru Mahārāj said,
“Saraswatī Ṭhākur did not advise
taking Kṛṣṇa-nām
before a picture of Kṛṣṇa”,
which we could say,
“Oh, many, if not most devotees,
they do something like that.
Oh, but our param-guru,
or my param-guru,
he’s saying not to do that.
Why?”
Your eyes will turn that image
of Kṛṣṇa into vulture food.
When the artists asked Kṛṣṇa,
“Is this what Kṛṣṇa really,
(that was Prabhupād)
is this what Kṛṣṇa
really looks like?”
He said, “Not exactly,
but you’ll recognize Him,
when you see Him.”
Gopa Kumār, he recognizes
Kṛṣṇa when he sees Him.