Rūpa Gosvāmī’s poetry
is so beautiful and sometimes
with Śrīla Guru Mahārāj’s writings
is also compared.
[Ontological Substance and Poetic Beauty]
Because you have ontology.
This is what
Śrīla Keshava Mahārāj said.
Śrīla Bhakti Prajñān Keśava Mahārāj.
He took sannyās from
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
and gave sannyās to
Śrīla Swāmī Mahārāj Prabhupād.
When he heard
the Prema Dhama Deva Stotram,
with joy, he said,
“No one can compete with him.
It because we find here
this perfect combination
of ontological substance,
and poetic beauty.
Sometimes the substance is there,
but the language is not so nice,
or, I mean not so nice in the sense
of the poetic sense.
Other times the poetry,
the style is very charming,
but the substance
isn’t there.
So, of the two, we can tolerate
when the substance is there,
and maybe the language
is a little stilted
or it’s not
the most charming flow.
I mean I don’t want
to speak in any way
to comet offence;
one of the offences
to the Holy Name—
blasphemy the Scriptures,
But in a sweet way,
Śrīla Gurudev said,
“Some of the things
Vedavyās has written,
we hear the grandeur
of the ślokas like
janmādy asya yato ’nvayād itarataś cārtheṣv abhijñaḥ svarāṭ
tene brahma hṛdā ya ādi-kavaye muhyanti yat sūrayaḥ
tejo-vāri-mṛdāṁ yathā vinimayo yatra tri-sargo ’mṛṣā
dhāmnā svena sadā nirasta-kuhakaṁ satyaṁ paraṁ dhīmahi
[SB: 1.1.1]”
That is beautiful,
but Gurudev said,
“That is like the dance of elephants.”
Like, you are astonished
but you don’t want
to come too close.
You want to watch from a far
the dance of the elephants.
It’s not so inviting, but
that majestic rhythm there.
He said, “Whereas when Vedavyās,
(and it’s composed by Vedavyās)
when he comes
to the gopī-gita,
the gopī-gita in the 10th Canto
of Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam.
When these expressions come
from the Vraja-gopīs,
then it’s very sweet, the meter changes
and we have
tava kathāmṛtaṁ tapta-jīvanaṁ
kavibhir īḍitaṁ kalmaṣāpaham
śravaṇa-maṅgalaṁ śrīmad ātataṁ
bhuvi gṛṇanti ye bhūri-dā janāḥ [SB: 10.31.9]
So this tava kathāmṛtaṁ ta …
ta-va-ka-tha-am-rtam ta …
The first and the seventh rhyme,
and there is other internal rhyme.
Very … the alankar—the poetic
ornamentation is there,
and also
the ontological substance.
So, when Śrīla Keśava Mahārāj
gave this praise to Śrīla Guru Mahārāj.
papa-tapa-dava-daha-dagdha-duhkha-khanditam
krsna-nama-sidhu-dhama-dhanya-dana-sagaram
prema-dhama-devam eva naumi gaura-sundaram
or the pranamami sada prabhupada-padam
sujanarbuda-radhita-pada-yugam
(means ‘on yugam’)
yuga-dharma-dhurandhara-patra-varam
varadabhaya-dayaka-pujya-padam
pranamami sada prabhupada-padam
guna mañjari garima guna hari vasana vayanam
very sweet, but
the substance is there.
svarna-koti-darpanabha-deha-varna-gauravam
padma-parijata-gandha-vanditanga-saurabham
koti-kama-murcchitanghri-rupa-rasa-rangaram
prema-dhama-devam eva naumi gaura-sundaram
Hearing these type of ślokas,
Keśava Mahārāj said,
“No one can compete with him,
there is no contest.”
I mean that’s
spiritual substance
and the beauty,
the poetic beauty.