We find, when Gopa Kumar
arrives in Goloka Vṛndāvan,
his first day
in the spiritual world,
[Day One | Spiritual World]
it’s pretty amazing.
And he arrives there
after going through all the fourteen
varieties of planetary systems,
all the Vaikuṇṭhalokas,
through Ayodhyā …
he’s been everywhere,
and he is
in that divine abode,
and when he’s searching
for Nanda Bhavan—
the house of Nanda Mahārāj,
and he meets some Vrijabāsīs,
and they look so sad.
He’s never seen anyone
this sad and pathetic in his life …
in his lives—
he’s been everywhere!
We have a stereotype
that spiritual people
should always be smiling.
They always have
a big smile on their face.
Not so.
He enters Vṛndāvan
and he’s thinking,
“I have never seen a more
miserable group of people
in my life …
in my lives!”
[Laughing]
Imagine that—he’s reached
the highest abode,
and he’s never seen this type
of misery upon someone,
someone afflicted
with this type of misery,
and sadness, and anguish.
So much so
that when he will say:
“Can you tell me where’s the house
of Nanda Mahārāj?”
“[Gasp!]”, like, “Woah!!”
Or others, they look like
paintings or statues.
And he’s saying,
“Give an indication,
is it that way? Just … point,
or something, please!”
He can’t understand
why they’re so miserable.
Till they see a dust cloud
off in the distance …
It’s Kṛṣṇa, Balarām,
the cowherd boys, and the calves.
The dust
from the calves’ hooves
bringing this giant
dust cloud—goraja.
As Gurudev said
in Govardhan,
which is the place of aspiration
of everyone in this line,
and Raghunāth Dās Goswāmī,
nija-nikaṭa-nivāsaṁ dehi govardhana tvam
[Śrī Govardhana-vāsa-prārthanā-daśakam: 3]
“Please, Govardhan,
give me shelter nearby You.”
When the devotees were there
coughing on all the dust,
Gurudev said,
“But you all prayed for the dust”.
[Laughing]
And he said, “But you prayed
to get that dust,
and now it
has come to you!”
Then he understands,
with the approaching dust cloud,
that the reason everyone
is so miserable:
it’s just a typical day
in Vṛndāvan,
and Kṛṣṇa, Balarām,
сowherd boys, cows—
they’ve gone
to the forest for the day.
And the few hours,
the hours they’re gone
is an intolerable separation
to the Vrijabāsīs.
That’s why they’re
so miserable—
they’re feeling separation
from Kṛṣṇa.
So how will we understand
what is spiritual?
bāhye viṣa-jvālā haya, bhitare ānanda-maya,
kṛṣṇa-premāra adbhuta carita
[Cc: 2.2.50]
Kṛṣṇadās Kavirāj Goswāmī,
he’s saying that externally,
it appears as though
one has been poisoned,
while internally
they’re relishing some,
in the words
of Guru Mahārāj,
“some peculiar strange
nectarine juice.”