In our position
direct contact with Kṛṣṇa
yields little substance.
[Deep Krishna Connection]
In the case
of actual exalted devotees
the most indirect contact
yields the highest substance.
So, if Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī
sees a tree, a tamal tree …
maybe a very deep
Kṛṣṇa connection.
We hear about
the Vedic science
of auspicious
and inauspicious signs.
Like if you’re going travelling,
if someone goes
by carrying empty buckets—
inauspicious.
If those buckets
are full of something—
auspicious.
And there are
many other things.
So, we are told,
they indicate, “Oh!
Now it’s a good time to travel.”
“Oh, no! Not to travel.”
When we were
with Mr. Shau,
Avadhūt Mahārāj
and I in Puri,
we were in some place
and were about to go to do something,
and someone sneezed.
Mr. Shau said,
“We have to wait.”
[Laughing]
But what’s interesting,
Chakravartī Ṭhākur will say,
“This science,
we can trace this science back
to Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī Herself.
But She observes
all these different signs
as indicative of whether
or not meeting …
it’s favorable
to meet with Kṛṣṇa.”
That’s the value
of this science.
So, Guru Mahārāj
will say,
(when it comes to interpretation
or how we see anything)
“Depends on where
we take our stand.”
So, if we take a stand
in the nirguṇa-plane,
which is where
Śukadeva begins from,
then we’ll see things
from a certain perspective.
And there’s gradation
in everywhere and everything,
so we go deep
into the nirguṇa-plane.
That means we have
the objective world,
subjective world,
super subjective world and
the super-super subjective world,
means Goloka,
the aprākṛta-līlā of Kṛṣṇa,
where everything is perfect
and will be interpreted
in terms of the Absolute,
a highest interest
of the Supreme Absolute.
As Guru Mahārāj said
how to show Subal and Śrīdām:
“Ready to fulfill
the inner desires of Kṛṣṇa.”
There’s that plane.
Then here, in this world,
basically we are operating
in terms
of the intermediate position,
madhyama-adhikārī,
distinguishing,
“Well, this is good,
that’s not good;
this is desirable,
that’s undesirable.”
Some discrimination
is being applied.
But from a higher perspective
everything is moving perfectly,
according to the sweet will
or the will
of the Sweet Absolute.
Guru Mahārāj would say,
“We have to prepare
to surrender ourselves
to a whimsical Lord.
In this world we don’t want
to be subject to someone’s whims,
but when you are dealing
with the Absolute
why the hesitation?
He’s the Absolute,
ultimate and absolute good.
His whims are
for the eternal benefit
of everyone and everything.