Mahāprabhu in the mood
of a devotee,
He’s relishing this
devotional position.
As we’ve told recently
with the Khirachora Gopīnāth,
it’s mentioned,
when Mahāprabhu
was telling the story
of Mādhavendra Purī there …
When the pūjārī brings the khir
to Mahāprabhu, and Nityānanda Prabhu,
and His group,
it’s mentioned there, that Mahāprabhu
tasted this before as Gopīnāth.
[A Most Wonderful Thing]
He’s also Kṛṣṇa,
so He’s already taken it.
So is this redundant?
No. Because now He’s going
to taste prasādam,
that’s what He wants to do.
And He is telling us
by these pastimes,
that the position of the devotee—
that’s a greater taste,
that’s a greater position to be in
than Kṛṣṇa.
And only He can say that,
because He’s Kṛṣṇa.
If He wasn’t Kṛṣṇa,
we might doubt it.
We could say, “Well …”
But He’s Kṛṣṇa,
and He’s saying,
“Take it from Me, Kṛṣṇa,
the Supreme Enjoyer,
that the position
of the devotee,
particularly the highest devotee—
Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī,
is greater, it’s a more
wonderful thing.”