The Vaishanava's strategy
is to remember
or take shelter
of the devotee of Kṛṣṇa.
[Devotee's Strategy]
Because,
ahaṁ bhakta-parādhīno
hy asvatantra iva dvija
sādhubhir grasta-hṛdayo
bhaktair bhakta-jana-priyaḥ
[SB: 9.4.63]
The devotees are always
in the heart of Kṛṣṇa.
If we factor in
ye yathā māḿ prapadyante
tāḿs tathaiva bhajāmy aham
[BG: 4.11]
Kṛṣṇa is saying,
"I reciprocate devotion."
So, if devotees are incessantly—
and we're talking here
about substantial devotees,—
they are incessantly in remembrance of Kṛṣṇa,
śrotavyaḥ kīrtitavyaś ca
smartavyaś cecchatābhayam
[SB: 2.1.5]
They're always thinking of the lotus feet [of Kṛṣṇa],
that's why they're qualified in that way.
So, as they're totaly...
they never stop thinking of Kṛṣṇa,
Kṛṣṇa never stops
thinking of them.