What is the actual
original function, purpose
of the senses,
of sense perception
beyond just navigating
the mundane world?
[Bitter Truth Reveals Sweet Absolute]
What really is
the ultimate purpose of
seeing, hearing, tasting,
touching, smelling, feeling?
In the Second Canto of
the Bhāgavatam
when Śukadev Goswāmī
begins speaking
to Parīkṣit Mahārāj
answering his questions;
there’s a series of verses,
five or six verses
that are very heavy,
where he says,
“If the tongue
isn’t used for vibrating
the Holy Name of Kṛṣṇa,
or glorifying Kṛṣṇa,
it’s like the croaking of frogs.”
Then it says,
“Those ears that don’t hear,
are like the earholes of a snake.
The eyes that don’t behold
the divine form of Kṛṣṇa,
are like the eyes on
a peacock plume.”
So, each one of the senses
is denigrated in that way.
And we think,
this is that sweet boy,
sixteen-year-old boy
Śukadev Goswāmī,
suddenly saying these
very heavy things.
Is he cruel?
Is he mean?
Is it some fanatical
brahmachārī speaking,
who’s just
insulting everybody?
Rather we should see
this as …
it’s brutal, the description,
because of the intensity
of feeling in the inverse,
that how beautiful is
the form of Kṛṣṇa,
how sweet is the sound
of Kṛṣṇa’s Holy Name,
the sound of the flute,
how soft is the body of Kṛṣṇa,
and how extraordinary is
the fragrance, the scent, of Kṛṣṇa.
All of these things
are so wonderful
that someone will say:
“If you’re not using it for that,
you’ve wasted your life.
What are they for?
What are your senses for?
Even in this world we have people
who say things like that.
They’ll say, “Oh, if you haven’t done this,
you haven’t lived!” Right?
It means that it is
a particular level of intensity
of feeling of appreciation.