If we think of what Narada told Vyas,
then we'll get a hint of how to interpret what is there.
Absolute Good Breaking Bad
And one thing we're told, he said,
in the jugupsitam dharma-krte anusasanah sloka
that he condemned mundane religion.
Guru Maharaj paraphrased in this way
by saying "You've told people how to get free from their disease,
but you didn't tell them about a healthy life.'
Because the emphasis is on - here's the disease, how to treat the disease,
how to come to the healthy position.
But the positive aspects about healthy life,
that, he did not properly indicate.
He said "You've done a great disservice
by indirectly promoting mundane religion",
religion meaning religion followed to live happily in the mundane world.
Not with the target of entry into the positive, serving, spiritual domain.
So he used the word jugupsitam,
it means: condemned.
Sometimes Guru Maharaj would say
"Traitor, treacheror, you're a traitor to the cause."
Narada's chastising him very severely.
But after we hear the passtimes of Krishna
with Radharani and Braja gopis,
when Pariksit Maharaj sees the apprehensive look
on the faces of the sages assembled there,
he again uses the word jugupsitam
and says, "In the beginning, Narada was chastising Vyas
for, in a sense, giving religion -
as it was understood up to that point -
that it would mislead people.
Now.. and you're saying, now the dharmic dharma projita kaitava,
the purest thing, is going to be given,
and what did you just tell everyone?
That not only is Krishna aprakrita lila,
krsnera yateka khela, sarvottama nara-lila,
nara-vapu tahara svarupa,
a man, human like passtimes,
but now you're telling us he's an immoral man.
So people who are moral and follow religion -
that's to be rejected,
and here's Krishna, violating the principals of religion,
we're supposed to understand 'this is the highest thing'.
Very interesting new religion you're presenting here.
So following moral principals: bad.
Breaking all these principals: good.
Well, yes, when you're - if you're - the abosolute good, yes.
Then your stealing is worshipable,
your seeming encroachment upon the properties of others
is a delight.