oṁ ajñāna-timirāndhasya
jñānāñjana-śalākayā
cakṣur unmīlitaṁ yena
tasmai śrī-gurave namaḥ vande 'ham sri-guroh sri-yuta-pada-kamalam sri-
gurun vaisnavams ca
sri-rupam sagrajatam saha-gana-raghunathanvitam
tam sa-jivam
sadvaitam savadhutam
parijana-sahitam krsna-caitanya-devam
sri-radha-krsna-padan saha-gana-
lalita-sri-visakhanvitams ca
nama-srestham manum api
sachi-putram atra svarupam
rupam tasyagrajam uru-purim mathurim gostha-vatim
radha-kundam giri-varam aho radhika-madhavasam prapto yasya
prathita-krpaya sri-gurum tam nato ’smi ananda-lila-maya-vigrahaya
ananda-lila-maya-vigrahaya hemabha-divyacchavi-
sundaraya
tasmai maha-prema
rasa-pradaya
caitanya-candraya namo namaste
Yes, Prabhu, a question. we have a question from Navin Krishna Prabhu
from Saint Petersburg.
our teachers say that we should not try to
serve Krishna directly we must try to
serve his servants but in Sri Sri Prapanna Jivamritam a large number of
shlokas are dedicated to the service of
Krishna directly for whom.. What is an
example? he doesn't even exhibit them..
how can you make that statement and then
not give an example... next question!
The paradox in a nutshell is this writes
the journalist Oliver Morton in
"The Planet Remade" 2015 "Humans are grown so
powerful that they have become a force
of nature and forces of nature are those
things which by definition are beyond
the power of humans to control and of
court how far or to what destination may
acquired prejudices and acquired
tendencies of mankind take us is the
catastrophe inevitable or we still have
a chance to avoid it
I'm reminded of the teachings of
Prahlada Maharaja Krishna's teachings in
bhagavad-gita srimad-bhagavatam and
elsewhere and there is a narrative that
the world we're dealing with her somehow
fundamentally different than what it's
always been and I think that is
incorrect when for example in
bhagavad-gita when Krishna identifies
the problem problems of material
existence janma-mrtyu-jara-vyadhi-
duhkha-
dosanudarsanam on birth death old age disease
these things these things are there
beginning middle and end of material
existence and only in different ages
different times and circumstances
there's some variation but it's
essentially the same the teachings of
Prahlada Maharaja depending on how you
calculate it they're anywhere from
millions of years ago to over a hundred
million years ago and they're still
valid in our present circumstance
because they're addressing this
fundamental problem
which is you know mortality
and an art and literature it's one of
the great themes of art or literature
there's the expression memento mori'
things us that remind us of our
mortality I mentioned Chekhov and this
stories that he wrote which has the
title is the name of a person that I
can't pronounce
"Yonych" here you go same but in that
story in a nutshell the part that I find
a particular interest and we're told
Chekhov's the you know the master of the
short story and they say that the short
story is more difficult to write than
the long story because everything in a
short story has to be essential you
can't introduce something that has no
bearing on the story or what you're
trying to present so everything has to
be very tight even more difficult. Some
say is the poem wherein if it's
perfectly executed there's not one
non-essential word. So the short story
he's considered one of the masters if
not the master and the reason I give
this little sidebar is that so if
there's some element in the story it's
essential.
It's not random, anecdotal or it's
central to what's being presented there.
And the part I found a particular
interest is that this person, this man
meets this Russian girl in Saint
Petersburg at a party she's like and the
theater and the art like the singer,
dancer , actress something along those
lines. And he's infatuated with her there
may be some notable age difference
whatever but he's infatuated with her
and at this party she passes a note to
him, saying "Meet me in the cemetery the
graveyard at midnight", so he goes home
and and he's looking at this note and
he's thinking that she is toying with
him just making of intent about making a
fool out of him
so he's saying I'm not such a foolish
man that I'm gonna go off into a
cemetery at midnight so make a complete
fool out of me
and that's how he was thinking around
10:30 (laughing)
as the clock got closer he started
thinking but what if she actually goes
and I'm not there that would be tragic
that would be a catastrophe to use the
language of this learned fellow and how
to avoid such catastrophe because that
would be a true catastrophe in life
so maybe 11:30 11:35 he, whatever they
had in that day, where they call a
handsome,  the horse-drawn carriage gets
his driver takes him out to the cemetery
and is approaching and then midnight
comes and she's not there so then we
good thing all that build-up for nothing
thought he's supposed to be the master
of the short story,  he leads you on like
this and then the girl doesn't show up?
and you had so much anticipation in your
mind about what could happen, the lovers
will meet and and she's not go so maybe
she is the plan is to just see how
foolish he is. Is that the point? But
while he is there for the no-show girl
he is walking down the aisles and seeing
all these headstones or tombstones
and they say they have the name of some
man or woman, boy or girl born on this
day, died on this day... and he starts
thinking to himse "lf they were young
people who had love aspirations in their
hearts wanting to meet their counterpart
their ideal, their soulmate there and
and this is where it ended, right? he is
saying they had all these aspirations
and then they end up here. Memento mori
it's one of the great themes of
literature
so through this almost a ruse, right,
about the man obsessed with the woman
she gives him the note, they gonna meet
... what is he really drawing your
attention to, is a mortality, right, and the
the catastrophe if there is one. Like I
mentioned this famous line from Dylan
Thomas in this poem, the vegans you know,
when I said "Do not go gently into that
good night", "Rage rage against the dying
of the light..."
and people say, oh you know they love
that spirit and what is expressed there
But he's obviously a great poet
and all of that. But really, by that
time is little too late to start raging
on your deathbed, about what might have
been, right? What you would be raging about
as the how you wasted your time. That
could be a cause of rage or lament "Ohh my God, I just wasted my life on so many
distractions, trivial pursuits etc I
wasted this valuable opportunity"
it's a Narottam Thakur in his song "manushya-janama paiya, radha-krishna na bhajiya
janiya suniya visha khainu..." This is
a little different type of poetry, than
what people are commonly familiar with,
saying manushya-janama paiya, I got human life
here's this essential Vedic teaching
that is echoed in so many places whether
in the Gita, the Bhagavatam, the Puranas
and the poetry of the Vaishnava kavis
manushya-janama paiya... because, right,
I got the human form of life, what is
implied but not stated Padma Purana "Jala janava lakhani Stavrala vinkshati
krimaya rudra sankhya ka.."
It say eight you know the 8,400,000 different
species of life. Like, I like to say "You
only live eight million four hundred and
thousand times" so Jala janava..
so many aquatics.. he goes some it's in
parallel with objective evolution, from
aquatics to plants and trees,  insects
plants, trees, birds, bees etc until last
you achieve human species and what does
it say that you know "Athāto brahma jijñāsā..."  why does Vedanta begins with
saying:  "Then therefore you know
thereafter you should do this", meaning
having achieved this position what is
what distinguishes human life from
animal life ? Brahma jijñāsā spiritual
inquiry. "Rage, rage against the wasting of
the time not spent"... and Atma samiksha — self reflection, spiritual inquiry, right?
What is Prahlad saying ...
making much
the cover and not the substance within.
that's how growing. Substance versus form
putting all the emphasis on the
form and not the substance within
that's the waste of time
and like that's a catastrophe. To not use
this opportunity
Brahmana and Kripana. .....
....
the difference
between Brahmana and Kripana.
Kripana means "Kripa na..' miser
why is this person called the miser the
same because what what is the flaw of
the life of the miser is having achieved
so much wealth they they don't spend it.
that what is I don't know true or
apocryphal,  but the story of the famous
wealthy man who died inside his vault
not kind of thing even if it's not true
it's a good story
so Kripana, means he's achieved so
much wealth he's not .. (spending it) so why are they saying a human beings a Kripana?
You got the wealth of human life, which means this opportunity for self-examination
"Brahma Jigyasa", spiritual inquiry and you
did what? You wasted your time and in the
Iron Horse Tavern getting drunk, like the
poet who said "Rage, rage against the
dying of the light..."
you know.. dried died a drunken "cirrhotic"
if there is such a word, you know, that's
what he died from. So what's all the rage
about?
righ,t that's how you spent your time...
in a drunken stupor, so say a "Kripana" now is a miser in that he achieved the most
valuable wealth which is human existence
and wasted it!
so Narottama saing "hari hari! bifale janama gonainu
manushya-janama paiya, " I got birth as a human being".. and then right to the point.
Not just some general "Who am? Where
have I come from? where am I going?"
generic off-the-shelf sort of
spirituality. He gets right to the point:
manushya-janama paiya, radha-krishna na bhajiya
I wasted my life, by NOT
worshipping Radha and Krishna. That's the
opportunity that one can get... sudurlabha
bhagavata hi loke satsanga seva nirninam.
human life is this rare
opportunity and what's the treasure to
be achieved in human life "Satsanga seva nirninam"
To get the association of
the lord's devotees without which there
is no substantial connection.
So the this is the catastrophe of human
life is to waste this opportunity.
in terms of the environment and things like
that. The great environmentalist Theodore
Roszak, who wrote a book called "Where
the wasteland ends" he said and I think a
key statement here. He said and he talks
about all the external erosion that we
observed and that's been documented and
people are so concerned with
and rightfully so, but he also got right to
the point. he said the external erosion
that we observe around us is the outcome
of inner internal erosion. So if you do
not address internal erosion then all
these fixes for external erosion are
will end, you know, futility if you don't
address the central issue, internal erosion.
talking about acquired
prejudice acquired tendency what's Srila
Guru Maharaj
extracted from the Bhagavatam, hummus rid
rhogam heart disease and here we're
talking of the deep heart score to quote
another poet named our core
consciousness and what is that disease
consumerism exploitation Jeeva Jeeva
Jeeva naam one living being living at
the expense of another so we know when
it's really guru Maharaj was in Sri
Gauri Ahmad and his he was given the
savor to go to some government official
and collect a donation for the building
of a mod perhaps the Madras Cody Martin
Selden South India someone had promised
it previously so it really only had to
do was come and say some Hari katha
something some kind words collect a
check and but they when he arrived he
found that man who promised that
previously was no longer in charge and
there was someone new there and that
person said to him I assure you if there
are any that's the word extra funds it
won't be used for making a mod a temple
but will use it in some humanitarian
work you know feeding the people
clothing the people housing the people's
something like that but not for some
Mart or some temple
surplus on that sort and guru Maharaj
said that he felt well he was shocked
first to find out us and could not think
what to say to him to modify alter his
thinking and it this teaches us
something too about how reliant we are
upon our Shri Guru Varga so he's saying
internally he began to pray this feel
about these siddhanta sarasvati talk war
for help the service opportunity is
there and he wouldn't think and then on
his watch it slipped away and vanished
in' and some inspiration came to him but
from what would seem to be an unlikely
source and we were discussing this the
other days he tends count of the shrimad
bhagwat on Radha and Krishna's pastimes
with the Raja go peace so everything
what does that have to do with a
donation for the gaudiya mutt and
building a temple how can that be
relevant or be the relevant thing and
that's loca as we told when the sages
assembled are perplexed by what they've
heard from sukadeva goswami that nor it
is chastising veda vyasa for
conventional religion that people
invoking conventional religious ideas
and understanding people will remain
bound
and not be liberated and what is the
antidote for that Krishna Lila and not
only Krishna Lila Radha Krishna Natalia
their pastimes of Radha and Krishna with
the roads ago piece the madhura rasa
pastimes this is the oh shoot the
medicine Bobo's shinobi Ramat meant in
the beginning of tenth canto that
normally medicine is bitter and doesn't
taste good hey whenever someone gives
you you know there's something supposed
to be good for you or it's some matters
and it tastes horrible it's the worst
thing ever and they always try and make
you feel better by saying it's good for
you so never tatar shiro pogium on odd
paavo she - ribeirão be Rama Janusz my
slow cooker etc what's mentioned nearby
Prickett my eyes - cigarette goes my
said mmm
this is really different this is that
medicine that cures the heart of heart
disease but is very sweet tasting and
enlivening and beautiful that's very
nice so the medicine is very sweet but
those sages saying now and you've told
us days sweet pastimes of Radha and
Krishna and the brazuca peas and were
perplexed and suka Dave off is a variety
of slokas to qualify to contextualize
thus and one of which is
the one that concludes with grid rhogam
what has been a very creditable Dube
reared on should be snow slow down with
Owen Australia data Varney aid yard but
deeper on bhagavati pretty love jicama
grid rogue Omashu up e in OT ocarina
dear so he's saying how these things
have to be received and understood
conceived like Gurudev would give her
the example of compared with homeopathic
medicine he said not only does the
medicine have to be identified but the
potency of the medicine the dosage of
that potency and if that wasn't enough
he said and your time for healing must
have come so and I playing segwaying
from that or playing off I reminded me
of another medicine where heart medicine
which is nitroglycerin and so you could
say there's no nitroglycerin is heart
medicine it's a boy you know get me a
big bottle of it you know no no don't do
that
don't bang the bottle say it has to be
administered in a particular amount and
then otherwise it can be lethal as we're
saying Shiva drank a notion of poison
what was the end result Neelkanth ah his
neck turn blue in other words don't try
this at home right other slow car you
know do as I say not as I do
I mean as a matter of speaking but in
this one saying so these pastimes
thereof and he says here instead of
using the word Krishna he says Vishnu
so that could throw some people off or
be more rightly understood as he's
saying sometimes Vishnu means God so
what he's telling is Krishna is God
otherwise if he just said Kristen I
think he's this particular person who
had these type of Palestine he's saying
now these are the pastimes of the Lord
McCready Tom Raja Badu Peter
humpty-dumpty Vishnu but to understand
this verse red Honda toe on Australia
it's the culture of faith you have to
hear from those who love Krishna that's
what Krishna consciousness is about
hearing about Krishna from those who
love Krishna really Bach toasty Mesa
College 80
bhaktya 2029 Osaka Christmas Saint Arjun
your love and affection for me qualifies
you hey not that you're a scholar very
because why would the greatest devotees
the brezza Gopi they're not scholars but
interestingly when they appear in
Gourley alone they're great scholars an
event oh there's no one more clever than
them but how an appropriate allele
Orinda van as guru mars-1 said just a
silly uncivilized jungle girls and no
one is more clever than them no one
loves Krishna more than they do they own
copyright registered trademark Krishna I
had so much so it's only they can give
Krishna
to others so but what is said there is
that so this is the medicine for
cheering heart disease and what is that
disease you know exploitation
consumerism to acquire control and
consume things that are lower than us as
a means for fulfillment self
satisfaction to address the needs of the
heart so every time it will not do that
right only this medicine but because
what is the heart it's yearning for its
counterpart the ideal the ideal
counterpart praat the uncle Augie Conde
Pratt the younger more we're told that
that comes from srimati radharani
herself saying to Kristen
only you can address every hankering of
every atom of my existence and the
absolute must be nothing less than that
and not only that to address
everyone's every atom of every Souls
hankering simultaneously the absolute
cannot be anything less than that so
Rupa Goswami describes Krishna Aquila
rasam Rita more tea
because he's reciprocating when santa
dasya sakhya vatsalya Medora so guru
Maharaj is telling this man in essence
what people are suffering from is heart
disease it's an internal condition not
to make light of external suffering but
that's not the real problem the real
problem to be address in this world of
mortality while you have time is this
heart disease which can only be cured by
hearing about Krishna and particularly
his sweet pastimes with the brazuca
peace tava khatam written toptygin
imbued item commercial poem Shravan
among alum streamer dr. Tom movie green
ant eat a burrito jana mahaprabhu help
when pratap arruda mars sang the slope
of the gopi Gita to Mahaprabhu at the
intermission of the Rath Yatra and Maru
was resting in the garden from all the
singing and dancing and Mahaprabhu got
so excited he doesn't know who he owes
he concealed he dispense with the kingly
dress and took the dress of a humble
voice nose and was massaging
mahaprabhu's lotus feet and reciting the
Gopi Gita technically speaking who he
was was unknown to mahaprabhu who had
refused to meet him as a king so it's
Varian and what are we told what did he
do to achieve this position if we have
to support this ontologically we got the
grace of the devotees and he took the
humble position of a sweeper so to this
day you see every year in the Rath Yatra
that the
descendant representative Roberto
Perugia Mirage comes out with a broom
and sweeps before the chariot of
Jagannatha so he took the the least
position again this is underscored that
is how you enter into this by taking the
least position it's sometimes guru Mars
would say establish a cottage in that
paint something a little something my
problem HUD said fix me as an atom in
the dust of your holy lotus feet and the
iene on the ternoon joking Quran petite
Imam mr. mayor van Bhutto creepy our
table creeping out of a powder Pankaj ah
sorry some duly such a sumbitch entire
right an atom an atomic presence in that
plane that is the the correct aspiration
but any connection without so what is
our present condition is suffering and
forgetfulness of Krishna I which we
could equate with separation the Braj
ago peas their suffering and remembrance
of Krishna
but separation in both cases separation
one in forgetfulness of Krishna one and
remembrance of Krishna intensified on
account of intense remembrance of
Krishna but the cure is the same and how
beautiful is that it's not like Oh for
these lower fallen Souls that give them
this type of medicine not the good stuff
not top shelf no they're saying the same
thing that gives relief to their heart
mysteriously mystically will give relief
to your
heart tava khatam rhythm the neck I'm
Rita means the it addresses the
mortality factor problem issue hey Rick
do what is that man's name you know but
all Prabhu his name really is Burt enjoy
not so therefore everyone calls them but
all through no it's like a Bengali thing
so Murray tune means one who conquers
death so Maruti Morita Morita with you
so Maria Amrita which we some is
rendered as nectar means that which
conquers death the nectar that you know
gives in a generic sense immortal life
so the bread Jacoby is saying tava kata
the talking about you hearing about you
is on Rita it deals with the death with
the the mortality problem kava khatam
rhythm top to GE venom and what extends
your life in the mortal world that that
wouldn't be a gift right rage rage
against the dying of the light tava
gives you life and the world that's
worth living the substantial world top
the Jairam cubby Peter Edith um cubby it
means like poet's poetry Colma xalapa
hum removes all the obstacles
unnecessary things suffering
shovin among the lung and so hearing
about you that's the beginning of all
auspiciousness and Subhadra you've heard
that name
occasionally clay shocked me Subhadra
mochila goethe crit
sandra non-dairy she shot Maha Shri
Krishna garcinia chose our rupa goswami
says
Krishna consciousness one-ounce me
Subedar it's giving all us for Shravan
among the lung just hearing about you
everyone knows that who's here and in
connection with the Krishna
consciousness movement the day the
moment that you heard about Krishna is
when auspiciousness entered into your
life and you heard about Krishna from a
devotee among Sri Madhavi Tom I say
srimad out this then you're filled with
wealth real wealth right not the type
the guy who died in the vault counting
his money you know or fearing that it
would be taken away from him this is
sailordiy means treasure real wealth
srimad artem boovie grinnin TT buried ah
Jana and in this world people who are
giving this they're the real altruist
the real humanitarians the real
benefactors right no you know
benefactors one giving right anyway of
mankind of humankind they're giving
something substantial so when he said
this or sang this sloka it's one of them
in the Gopi Gita mahaprabhu junta and
and
yeah booyah booyah yeah like they're the
givers they're really giving something
this is real giving you're giving real
substance who give this and what you've
given me
I cannot reciprocate all I can do is
embrace you and embraced prataprudhra
Mara's forgiving him good the songs of
the go-go bejita what the Gopi is sing I
think that is the only thing that can
cure the heart print rhogam of the cures
of heart disease and so a place where
this can be heard this is real service
to humanity and guru my said that man
turned to him and said Xiaomi do I
believe in God and then guru I said your
tears are the evidence of that the man
broke down crying when he heard this
explanation it touched his heart and
then he realized yeah this the the mod
the temple that's the most valuable
thing you could establish for the people
yes and these funds will be given for
that
so the catastrophe to be avoided is not
an environmental crisis external erosion
is the outcome of internal erosion grid
rhogam heart disease rage against the
wasting of the time the wasting of that
life that could have engaged in krishna
culture so but let me say memento mori
oh we're gonna die remember that it's in
literature it's in all the books
everything you know it's it's all over
the internet every day there's never
been an order with one day in this world
where the headline was no one died
yesterday no breaking news no one died
you know California man achieves
happiness there are no stories like that
hi not for one moment they can't say
give a news story and say there was one
moment in the last 24 hours when no one
died what to speak of a 24-hour period
not even one moment where no one died so
we're living in a graveyard
could it be Chekhov's graveyard he got
us there didn't he we graveyard dwellers
if you say no the world is a giant
graveyard fine fossil fuels anybody we
have been fuelled by the dead as we race
toward we're going faster than ever
towards the grave people before us they
were slowpokes so there's two ways to
deal with it the problem is mortality
that's the catastrophe let's say just
that word keeps coming around so there's
like the religionists way of dealing was
and then scientists and techno impending
more mortality I I like that the great
atheist Christopher Hitchens when he got
terminal cancer and somehow maintained
his humor I guess you could call it
gallows humor to a certain degree but he
would not relent on his atheism so he
was faithful to the end or faithless to
the end I'm not sure or a combination of
the two but he said whenever someone
gets one of these terminal diseases it's
always it's always presented as a battle
they're gonna fight this thing you know
he's a real fighter she's a real fighter
she's gonna fight this you know and as I
said if Ladbrokes was taking bets I
would bet on counter
so oh then Christopher Hitchens said he
said it's as if to say after a long
struggle with mortality he finally
succumbed in other words it's inevitable
there is no overcoming this in the
conventional sense yet so you have
religions
deloo you know like grandma went died
and went to heaven kind of thing and
then you have science on the other side
seem better living through chemistry you
know through technology we're gonna be
able to give you eternal life they
wouldn't use that word but that's what
they're promising you know scan yourself
make sure to back up you know and then
download yourself into a robot made out
of diamonds and you've got eternal life
it's really what they were promised I'm
not making this up it sounds like I'm
making it up I know that but I'm not and
the founders of Google believe this it's
one of their projects when they asked
Larry Page they said you know how much
research are you putting into curing
cancer and extending people and I said
no we're doing that he said but you know
they have all the the you know the the
date of the metrics etc and
that you know even if you find some kind
of a cure the average person will extend
their life by five to seven years they
have some data like that
he said and I'm not making this up you
can google it he said but what if we
could cure death what about that and
then kind of you know slipped out that's
their project whether it's true goo you
know getting all this information genome
mapping does that the other thing it's
to cure death to give eternal life so on
both are pursuing the same thing
the religionists and the technologists
one through some kind of theistic
culture the other through scientism
technological advancements but the
target is really the same interestingly
enough and they're both have these
promises and both we could say in a
sense are non verifiable so you're
buying into a narrative people forget
that the on either side on any side
you're hearing something and it's
resonating with you and you're believing
that now once I know we have all this
reserves in them but just just for the
sake of argument you didn't do all those
experiments yourself you're taking their
word for it that these things are true
or verifiably true so when it comes down
to it you're it's faith-based you've
heard something someone there's a a
compelling narrative that warranted
believe
you believe in it on either side it's
belief you hear something and you
believe that they say no but we have
experiments that maybe you do I mean you
say I I didn't do them personally I'm
taking your word for it so I heard from
you you made a very good presentation
and I believed in you and what I believe
in your narrative it's compelling right
you make a compelling case for what you
say but these two things are always
there I mean and we can frame it or I
like to as the Devas and the asuras you
know like two teams in the final event
on one side we have the Davos you know
the other side we have the asuras but
what's interesting about us Devas are
not necessarily devotees I remind you of
that so here which happens to be
Southeast Asia we know and nityananda
das and our sundar Ananda Prabhu there
can verify the interest in Cambodia
Angkor Wat true and the temple there
encore wat as it like we say mod and
this part of the world they say wat for
mod just to make it simple temple this
you know will be variously described as
the largest Hindu temple in the world or
the largest religious complex in the
world right that would be an often used
descriptor and there are well we call it
a mural or what's on the walls how would
it be Berra Leafs
bah relieves a lot of massive you know
the size and all I mean massive it and
it happens to be the pastime of the
korma avatar and Mohini Morty and the
churning of the milk ocean by the Devas
and the asuras so one good thing like oh
why do they / God you know and I used to
think this too in the it appears in the
8th canto of srimad-bhagavatam remember
shrimad bhagwat um again it's has
structure to it so we're dealing with
certain things in the first canto laying
the foundation second counter suka dave
begins his teachings third canto we have
like Kapila descriptions of the universe
and sustains Kapila forth count to count
Oh pre to Maharaj what else
Kaku Mara's pour on John its fifth canto
descriptions about the mundane universe
and teachings of rishabh Dave and the
six count Oh a Jameel ayat and citraketu
and seventh canto pro-law pure devotion
first appears
prahlada maharaja and teachings of pearl
admirers I alluded to quoted earlier and
eighth count oh we get Mohini Morty I
mean I'm really just roughly summarizing
just for the sake of us bringing us
their to the eighth counters you know
the body thumbs moving in a particular
direction
hi it's has a structure to it or
superstructure whatever you want there
was the thread going throughout and it's
not that I discovered those but guru
Mara is being informed about these
things so even in his sloka yeah dummy
amo Hamas trivago become cation purty
pod but pretty padam manu bhutan up your
love Davide ax-cut ocular Rossum were t
Shama Leela of alum bomb madhura rasa D
Sri Racha Patil save save an arboretum
no fear rod ha Potter 7 I'm confusing
too but they're similar same meaning
though saying although her name is not
mentioned extensively every step of the
way everything every slow car is meant
to take us in the direction of the
service of her holy lotus feet which
means
Medora rasa that is what the bagua time
is about so if you're studying some
section of the bagua thumb and you're
not seeing how it's related to here
you're missing something because it's
only going this way it's all going in
this direction so guru maharaj is
showing us all this connects to that
always will connect to that so the the
in this particular regard for me I was I
thought like though this is a wonderful
pastime the Davis on the asuras there
churning the nectar ocean at first they
can't do it and the the quorum avatar
appears there's the mandora mountain and
on the plea that as a turtle tortoise
although he's omnipotent he cannot
scratch
zone back and we all know that's true
sometimes there's an itch anyway you
cannot do it on your own so that I mean
how like and once mildly humorous but
playful like for Krishna to appear in
this way
who's omnipotent to come as a tortoise
who has an itch that he can't reach
right so what do they do they put them
under mountain
on his back and Vasuki sir and they're
churning back and forth and the mountain
is moving like this I mean the serpent
like a churning run and it's turning the
mountain and that's relieving the itch
on his back and he's like going and as
he breathes out the Vedas are being
generated but and that churning then the
moon comes out is produced the hooch is
raba whores Arava taw indra's elephant
and lakshmi devi so the moon and lakshmi
devi
the surya bunk show that krishna appears
in and shri goddess ultimate maha
lakshmi sri there will be some pastimes
nectarine pastimes being more precise
about what is nectar and immortality so
Davis and asuras like up to the moment
we speak everyone trying for immortality
right because the real problem here the
inevitable problem facing everyone is
mortality
it just kind of ruins your day so how to
overcome that so that with they've heard
of this on Rita like girl rumor says
it's Frimpong to be Shay I'm Rita
saputra oh you're children of nectar
children that don't be satisfied with
anything less than this you were born
from it you're born to taste it it's all
about this this ultimate substance but
from the Asura point of view what is
their concept of immortality is like
Larry Page and the guys at Google to
live in this world forever that's their
version of immortality why because as
proud might say due to a poor fund of
knowledge they're not educated about the
immortal world where they have some
prospects some possibility there beyond
karma and gown so they want immortality
like classic Asura IPO you know they
want immortality and the Devas they also
they in general we say they want to live
in this world forever too but in a nicer
way right in Swarga loca we might say
some of the more refined ones of
more refined the idea of what that could
be but still it's gross mundane subtle
mundane right what they want this
substance everyone wants this substance
that makes you a mortal but I don't
remember which Greek myth it is but the
one person ask the gods for immortality
and they granted mo immortality but he
forgot to ask to be eternally youthful
so that's sort of backfired
he just got older and older and older
like the opposite of the Picture of
Dorian Gray
Oscar Wilde nailed this point also about
youth another yovana being eternally
youthful and his story the Dorian Gray
the painting ages and sculpt how do you
say portrays express all the karmic the
reactions to his sinful activities are
visible on the portrait while he remains
eternally youthful up to a point because
it's not possible so they want that
so but then I noticed so I read that and
we read that section and what is our
capacity to extract from there like
those davison asuras not even but then I
noticed at the conclusion of the bog
would come the last chapter which is
very short it's only 20 something verses
so you think this is a last chapter of
the bagua Tom out of the 18,000 slokas
here's the conclusion the very last one
Babaji Marez like so much nama sankirtan
amiyo sabah pop up or national
pranaam Oh Duke Oh someone else tun
namami how him Purim he loved to sing
that because it saying the very last
verse of the barber time is singing the
glories of Nam sang kirtan saying
whatever with described up to this point
this is how you're gonna get it right so
engage in Nam son kirtan um sarva pop up
Renault's and that will destroy
everything in auspicious in your life
tun namami Hadean poem this you know
this is the supreme way of worshipping
krishna and this aides like those
brother Kofi's I'm talking about you
singing your name how how merciful is
that the infinite to appear as though
finite Krishna so but anyway but before
that earlier on the chapter there's this
verse begins priest Abram Adam and
Amanda Righetti grab agua con do you not
need Rollo come authority at cetera
talking about the korma avatar and it's
very beautiful what is described there
and it's saying also that the the rhythm
of the ocean the tide comes in and then
it goes and that and we know we everyone
is charmed by that right the oceanfront
property go to the island the plate you
know you're gonna hit it's like it's
hypnotic
and some will say healing and it's many
things and the bottom says it's the
breathing of the Lord
that's the breathing of karma avatar it
comes in and out and generated the Vedas
it's it's echoing the breathing of the
korma avatar and as guru Dixit and
intimately connected with madhura rasa
so I said the groomers I don't
understand why that the conclusion of
the bog would come this albeit wonderful
pastime from the 8th canto I don't see
the connection here why that would
appear again and and when so many others
are not being referenced in this
conclusion why this particular one it's
baffling and srila guru mars as he said
you know he scans the scriptures the
statements of the greater joy it's not
that he had a prepared answer but he
went deep and came out with us and he
said what was the object of the their
churning this ocean was to get amrita
but as we said depending on one's
conception you have like generic
off-the-shelf immortality and then
something that is more specific he's
saying so they wanted Amrita I said what
is the bog wa Tama ballets the bog with
Tom as he said we mentioned in golden
volcano and the intro and he said the
byway tom takes us from the plane of
intellectual jugglery into the domain of
rasa the purpose of Baba kama is to
deliver Medora rasa Krishna conception
were Medora rasa is fully expressed
that's its purpose because they're
saying hearing that that can break the
stranglehold that lust has upon the
heart the rid rhogam the heart disease
that can cure that only that not not
conventional religion as inadvertently
given by Veda Vyasa chastised Barnard in
the beginning no you've got to give this
only this substance can do it
so we're saying without their they
wanted amrita for whatever they think
that is right their conception of Amrita
but he's saying the bagua tom was saying
that this Amrita this ultimate nectarine
substance is in fact madhura rasa that's
what it is that's the life-giving nectar
it's that substance not some generic
conception about living forever and
overcoming dying and these kind of
things you think so it's saying that
that Amrita they were searching for is
this it's Medora rasa and that's the
Medora rasa d3 rod ha propanone property
that's the ending of the earth she's the
and she is the source of that srimati
radharani
so manu shan jianmi pyar Radha Krishna
na ba Jia the catastrophe of human life
is to not use your time to waste your
time being distracted by other things or
substitutes trying to substitute
something with us when in fact this is
what it is meant for
that surprised me when groomer said
these I thought this is just amazing
he's connecting every part of the bagua
tom to one place to this aspiration the
service connection to the holy lotus
feet of srimati radharani Shama Lila
Avalon bomb the whole shamili Allah
another way his expressed mother is
dependent upon her and our problem is
substituting anything and everything for
that that's the catastrophe and it can't
be averted all hope is not lost
tava khatam rhythm table the G venom Co
be buried item call masha'Allah Shravan
among alum stream Marathi tom movie
green aunty de bourree dodging are my
everything and those who give this to
the world they're really serving the
people and giving them something of
inconceivable value
a charge of on Peru Chauvet da profits
at so many times if you're in charge you
know don't be shy
John on the CR theta Geneva sorry go
robot oven
guy rupa sanatan but GG ba gopala bhatta
h i go time Cody Tandang jaha who is a
big no-nos Abby stop H I go sidearm we
toda once about a pottery no more up on
the ground
Kundera Tirana say be bhaktas on a boss
John imagine I'm a male I belong H I go
died of a projectile Oh boss Rajasthan
Italy liquori lo Prakash anand a ball
over debug event of guru bhai Saab apart
a messiah
Hey
hurry bow
so what this sundar govinda dev-goswami
maharaj ki jaya Mishnah pods little
bhakti rakshak sridhar dev-goswami
maharaj ki BOGO Anjali bhaktisiddhanta
sarasvati talk or he die die supporting
our sweet sweet guru gauranga Gondar
BOGO bindus and our zucchini see get
aroused / donkey see rupanuga guru baba
ki jai namaha urges will heard us talk
work 'yes i shri krishna chaitanya burn
it down on this weird way to get out
harsh about city go back up in the key
see see Radhakrishna go back over now
Shyamalan the radha kunda getting over
donkey died Brindavan donkey died nobody
padam ki jai sri chaitanya saraswat
Mackey died
Don the David when a day we walk today
we toasted a week he died she go to go
over donkeys no pod vishva Vorenus
release he bhaktivedanta swami
prabhupada ki jai sri chaitanya saraswat
mater charge abend ikedaya
dodge feel about the people I would do
with my eyes key to I sort of like tea
runs on mother sit on maharaj ki jai sri
lake aditi he died a buggy love you too
David no see he died he's super the Devi
dancing he died Bella bonds of ravu keys
i save a brenda ki jai some Abeyta
booked opened ikedaya
neat I go premanande a
mr. Ferguson Maharaj King now a
traditional none of us wrestle or at
Imola done the words so I had a vdd
thank you for being here Maharaj all
glories to the assembled devotees
creation sahadev
Krishna Kunti done the words to one and
all with vital appreciation cool odd
with us honest to you David us see the
notes
Rajeshwari didi dandavat pranams from
Eva team Brazil tan ingeras Thunderbirds
and under little Ukraine dandavat jay
goswami maharaj pro shortened us Salt
Lake City the underworlds all the
reservoir Adam Allah such a good
metaphor of the churning oceans for the
present times goswami maharaj always so
brilliant
none of us from no way from Claudia joy
the one the home home grain from Norway
none of us from no way thank you to all
the lovely devotees who made this lovely
service possible it is the spiritual Bom
Bom Bom and from her replying to
Canadians send my regards to Maharaj
from Kunti from California's with the
vanity that's all we could be from Kunti
in so send my regards to Maharaj from
County from California / Switzerland
okay you're expressing their
appreciation for the wealth of our