What we mean
when we say ‘devotee’,
because Śrīla Gurudev,
liked to quote
one of Śrīla Guru Mahārāj’s
godbrothers, saying,
“Whether someone is 1 per cent a devotee,
5 per cent, 25 per cent,
50 per cent, 75 per cent,
99 per cent,
100 per cent,
that has to be factored in.
[Love Transcends Good and Bad]
What Guru Mahārāj sometimes
referred to as taṭastha vicār—
impartial analysis to determine
higher, lower; superior, inferior;
desirable, undesirable;
favourable, unfavourable.
You have to be careful.
What is it that compels us
to engage in this analysis?
Curiosity? Envy?
In the beginning of the Bhāgavatam,
dharmaḥ projjhita-kaitavo ’tra paramo
nirmatsarāṇāḿ satāḿ [SB: 1.1.2]:
this paramahaṃsa-saṁhitā,
the qualification to enter into
an understanding of the Bhāgavatam;
an understanding of Kṛṣṇa conciousness;
the qualification to understand
the devotees, nirmātsarya—
to not be envious of them.
What does that mean?
I mean it’s a negative prescription
or prohibition,
but it has a positive implication.
Negative, not to be envious.
What is envy?
Defined in this context,
is to not allow someone to be seen
in their rightful position.
To not recognise that,
and to be more specific,
to not recognise devotion,
to not recognise
devotional tendency.
Nehābhikrama-nāśo ’sti
pratyavāyo na vidyate
sv-alpam apy asya dharmasya
trāyate mahato bhayāt [Bg: 2.40]
A little bit of this is extraordinary
and eternally beneficial.
So these other aspects of a person
in terms of flaws, perceived defects,
whether they be character flaws
or improper behaviour etc.
they’re not eternal characteristics.
They might temporarily show something
and vanish,
whereas the devotional tendency is
of a lasting, permanent, eternal nature.
Śrīla Gurudev, when he was giving
some of his final words,
he said that everyone has
some fault, something;
and whether it is big or small,
that is not the question.
And he said that with the same cadence
of the famous Shakespearean
“To be or not to be,
that is the question.”
So Gurudev said,
“Big or small, that is not the question.”
He said, “But what must be recognised
is their devotional tendency,
serving tendency”,
and he said,
“that must be recognised
and respected.”
So that is the vision
of the devotees.
Guru Mahārāj says our only hope
of connecting with the upper world,
what to speak of the highest aspect
of the upper world, Goloka Vṛndāvan—
what is it known as?
—The land of love.
Love conceals all deficiencies.
And if we recognised that
despite someone’s apparent flaws,
that they do have some serving tendency,
spirit of devotion, dedication,
then it’ll be better for us to think
if I could get
a little bit of that from them,
what they’ve got,
the good thing they’ve got,
my position will improve.
So let me think of them
in such a way
and deal with them
in such a way,
to appreciate
their dedicating tendency,
and maybe some grace
will come to me from that.