They don’t say
like the Indian man said to me,
(I told Prabhupād
when he asked me
about my Indian preaching)
and the Indian man said,
(we would come to preach,
and he said)
“Oh, I know what is Kṛṣṇa.”
And Prabhupād said,
“That is their disease.”
[Erotic Potential in Unalloyed Devotion]
Beyond the grasp
of the mind and the intellect,
this is important.
ataḥ śrī-kṛṣṇa-nāmādi
na bhaved grāhyam indriyaiḥ
[Cc: 2.17.136]
At the same time
we are saying
the name, form, qualities
pastimes of Kṛṣṇa
are beyond the grasp
of the mind and intellect.
The senses beyond what can be seen,
heard, tasted, touched, smelt, and etc.
or conceived of in the mind
or intellectually.
So then what are we doing?
What is the Kṛṣṇa conscious project?
We just said the whole talk
up to this point was about this possibility,
now we’re saying
that it’s not possible
with your senses, and your mind,
and your intellect.
Well, what Śukadev said?
—“Beyond this realm,
what I saw
was not a mundane form,
a mundane person,
mundane relationship.
That’s why every part of the Bhāgavatam
is significant.
He was certified earlier,
Remember, he is
a sixteen-year-old boy, naked,
wondering, when he goes pass a pound
where women are bathing naked.
How would be average modern
sexteen-year-old boy responded that?
—Let’s not go there.
Śukadev Goswāmī …
They saw nothing—
not even trace elements
of exploiting tendency in his vision.
This is significant.
So, he’s already been certified —
here is no interest,
in a mundane … female form
or mundane sexuality.
Then what does he hear about?
—The erotic pastimes of Kṛṣṇa
and the Vraja-gopīs,
and that captures
him wholesale.
So, then what does it tell us?
—There is erotic potential
in unalloyed devotion.
Madan Mohan.
Freud—
“Eros is driving the world.”
The erotic principal is driving,
making the planet spin.
Madan, Cupid, so
sambandha-jñāna,
sambandha-tattva deity.
Madan Mohan, we are all bewildered
by Cupid.
Kṛṣṇa is so beautiful,
Cupid becomes bewildered.
And also it means that
the bewildering influence of Cupid
can be broken
by becoming redirected
towards Madan Mohan Kṛṣṇa.
Kṛṣṇa with erotic potential.
That’s what it means.
So it’s very visual, very sensual—
the spiritual project.
That requires a deeper level of seeing,
acquiring a proper angle of vision.