That fortunate soul’s wondering
the length and breadth of the brahmāṇḍa,
means the world of misconception
and all its variagatedness;
[Seed of Reality]
from the Indra—
the king of Heaven,
to the indra-gopa germ
on a bacterial level,
have all the possibilities.
We’re saying,
“A fortunate soul
get some connection
with Divinity, with Kṛṣṇa
through His agent—
Guru.
He [Śrīla Sanātana Gosvāmī]
mentions in the Hari-bhakti-vilāsa
about seed, quality of seed.
We’re saying:
bhakti-latā-bīja—
means the seed conception,
seed Kṛṣṇa conception.
As Guru Mahārāj included
in the Śrīla Gurudev’s
praṇāma mantra:
Kṛṣṇa prema bija pradan—
giving the seed of affection,
love and affection
for Kṛṣṇa.
But then there is quality
and gradation everywhere,
quality of seed.
So Guru Mahārāj quoting
Hari-bhakti-vilāsa saying,
“If superior quality of seed
is available
no inferior seed
should be planted.”
That’s the consideration.
When he was told someone
who had been apparently
in connection with Kṛṣṇa consciousness
for many years
resumed their position
in a mundane world,
even in the position
of an atheist,
he said, “If the quality of seed
is very high
and it was planted very deeply,
that’s not possible.”
Or will take it …
at least it will reassert.
There is a question dormancy,
suspended animation;
many things to consider.
As we consider
many things in this world.
Like cancer,
this example can work
in both directions.
The doctors say,
“We believe
we’ve removed it all.
Then they find out
sometime later:
“Oh, no, it reasserted itself.”
Something was still there—
it’s such a powerful thing,
it’s reasserting itself again.
It’s got recidivism.
That’s in a negative sense,
it can also be understood
in a positive sense.
If the seed, the quality of seed
is very high, deep,
profound connection with reality,
then even if circumstantially
it enters the suppress position,
or to the extent
of by what is normally observable.
It can’t be seen, it’s no longer visible.
Still it may reassert itself
in time.
nitya-siddha kṛṣṇa-prema ‘sādhya’ kabhu naya
śravaṇādi-śuddha-citte karaye udaya
[Cc: 2.22.107]
These activities … hearing, particularly
hearing from an agent of reality,
awakens kṛṣṇa‒bhakti in the heart.
Means it’s there in a sense
in a dormant position,
awakened by superior association.
bhaktyā sañjātayā bhaktyā
[Cc: 2.25.140]