Om Vishnupad Srila Bhakti Rakshak Sridhar
Dev-Goswami Maharaj tirobhav maha-mahotsava
tithi ki ki ki jay! Nitai-Gaura premanande
Haribol! Hare Krishna!
Gopa Kumar Prabhu: Srila Bhakti Sudhir Goswami
Maharaj ki jay!
Srila Goswami Maharaj: Srila Guru Maharaj
when he is a young man, but deeply under the
influence of Vedic literature, understanding
shastra, scripture. One of his relatives detected
in him some detachment from the world. And
he thought this doesn’t bode well for his
future, thinking of mundane family life particularly.
Hare Krishna. So, he thought, “Maybe I can
discourage him from all this Krishna culture.”
And so, he was someone who was educated and
up on the latest science theory so he said,
“Did you know the universe is so big: there
are stars so far away and the speed of light
is… What is it? 176 thousand miles per second.
(I forget in kilometers three hundred thousand
kilometers. —347 thousand kilometers per
second.) So, and you know that the light from
that star has yet to reach the Earth. So,
do you think, I mean, God’s so far away—he
has time for people like us?”
His—obviously— Bengali cousin, “It’s
so vast, so infinite, then—and we’re so
tiny and so finite, He’s so far away—He
has any time or inclination for people like
us?” And Guru Maharaj just immediately responded,
without thinking about this, his natural response
was—he said, “Can you show me somewhere
where He isn’t?” That’s what he said,
“He may be far away, but can you show me
somewhere where He’s not.” So, this is
Veda, Upanishad, shastra-chakshu, seeing through
the eyes of scripture. The Ishopanishad mantram
says, we learned in the very beginning:
tad ejati tan naijati
tad dūre tad v antike
tad antar asya sarvasya
tad u sarvasyāsya bāhyataḥ
(Īśopaniṣad, mantra 5)
He’s very far away: tad dūre. Tad vantike:
but He’s very near, as well. I find it humorous:
sometimes it’s mentioned that Nrisimhadev
or Vishnu in so-called “fear” of Hiranyakashipu
He was hiding in the one place he’d never
look: his heart. He’s searching everywhere
for the enemy “of my brother, who killed
my brother”, scrutinizing, but Vishnu thought,
“I’ll hide in the one place he’ll never
think of looking: his heart.” It says something:
that’s the one place where we’re not thinking
to look.
īśvaraḥ sarva-bhūtānāṁ
hṛd-deśe ’rjuna tiṣṭhati …
(Bhagavad-gītā, 18.61)
Krishna tells this to Arjuna in Bhagavad-gita.
… tene brahma hṛdā …
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 1.1.1)
It’s a heart-to-heart transaction, it’s
not data transfer, it’s not the transfer
of information. It’s not, you know, prioritizing
hits on a Google search: “Which one will
be best for me?” Tene brahma hṛdā—from
the heart of Krishna into the heart of Brahma.
And then what is the heart?—I like the poet
[William Butler] Yeats, and he says, “Deep
in the heart’s core.” In his famous song
about Innisfree: “I’ll live in the bee-loud
glade”, where, we can say by inference,
this divine vibration, it’ll be resonating
deep in the heart’s core, “the deep heart’s
core.” Because there might also be superficial
levels of heart, we can do that, go that far.
Srila Guru Maharaj saying there’s gradation
everywhere and in everything, then there should
be gradations of heart also—why not? “Union
in separation”—one of Guru Maharaja’s
sutras—‘union in separation’: where
does the heart achieve its greatest depth,
its greatest capacity to give its most vital
substance?—In separation.
… bа̄hye viṣа-jvа̄lа̄ haya, bhitare
а̄nanda-maya
kṛṣṇа-premа̄ra adbhuta carita
(Śrī Caitanya-caritāmṛta, Madhya-līlā,
2.50)
This is the adbhuta carita, the wonderfully
astonishing characteristic of Krishna-prema,
that—in separation from Krishna. What does
that mean: “in separation”? If we know
in this world—literature, songs… What
is that Guru Maharaj liked to quote, the poet…
Wordsworth, Percy Bysshe Shelley where he
says, “Our sweetest songs are those that
tell the saddest thought”, right. So, the
heartbreaking love story—heart breaking.
Cracks the heart open as if to allow it to
release some extraordinary substance. Krishna-prem,
so, if you can feel heartbreak being separated
from the beloved in this world, can crack
the heart open, then what to speak of the
supreme Beloved?
Kṛṣṇа-premа̄ra adbhuta carita. Bа̄hye
viṣa-jvālā haya. Viṣa means like poison:
as if one has been poisoned. The famous writer
who died recently Gabriel García Márquez,
one of his famous works “Love in the time
of cholera”, comparing love and separation—that
they can’t distinguish: is this person’s
suffering from some kind of terminal illness
or it’s the heartbreak of separation. And
there’s a mysterious opening there, this
is the focal point of the pastimes of Mahaprabhu
is union in separation. Krishna who knows
everything about the joy, joys of union:
… kandarpa-koṭi-kamanīya-viśeṣa-śobhaṁ
…
(Śrī Brahma-saṁhitā, 5.30)
… lakṣmī-sahasra-śata-sambhrama-sevyamа̄naṁ
…
(Śrī Brahma-saṁhitā, 5.29)
That Krishna with unlimited opportunities
for enjoyment as the focal point of his pastimes
and the descent of Mahaprabhu,
guru-rūpa-hariṁ gauraṁ rādhā-ruci-rucāvṛtam
…
(Śrī Śrī Prapanna-jīvanāmṛtam, 1.3)
Guru Maharaj writes in his Prapanna-jivanamritam.
Those introductory shlokas. His deities:
śrī-guru-gaura-gа̄ndharvа̄-, govindа̄ṅghrīn
gaṇaiḥ saha
vande prasа̄dato yeṣа̄ṁ, sarvа̄rambhа̄ḥ
śubhaṅkarа̄ḥ
(Śrī Śrī Prapanna-jīvanāmṛtam, 1.1)
gа̄ndharvа̄-govinda-sundara
Why Gandharva, Gandharvika?—Explains: Srimati
Radharani’s as the enchantress of the heart
of Govinda, Govinda Mohini: by Her singing,
self-giving, self-offering, singing and dancing—divine
movement enhanced with ultimate beauty—attracting
Krishna. So, Srila Guru Maharaj, he says that
in his case, he’s saying, he was not so
much attracted to Krishna in the beginning.
Why? He said, “Because Krishna is enjoyer,
not “an” enjoyer, the supreme Enjoyer,
His pastimes of enjoy.” He said, “I was
rather attracted to the self-givers, self-sacrifice.”
Even his very name given at birth—Ramendra
Chandra Bhattacharya. His mother wanting to
protect him, fearing some dangers, complications
of pregnancy, praying to Ramachandra for some
divine blessings, protection.
So, upon his successful birth he’s given
the name Ramendra Chandra and family name
Bhattacharya. So, Guru family: they’re natural-born
instructors. So, when he comes to the Gaudiya
Math or even before that: he told when he
was in college he goes one morning to brush
his teeth and the boy next to him—he was
brushing his teeth—starts talking about
his house where he lives, his home. And he
refers to his father, he says, “That gentleman’s
house that I live in, was saying the other
day… something.” And Guru Maharaj is surprised
at this type of talk: to speak about one’s
father that way. So he says, “You shouldn’t
be referring to your father as ‘That gentleman’s
house I live in’—he’s your father, after
all, you know, should speak with some more
familiarity, affection.” And he said, that
boy said, “Yes, actually you’re right,
that’s true,” he said, “But isn’t
it also true from another point of view, if
we factor in Vedic understanding.”
jalajā nava-lakṣāṇi sthāvarā lakṣa-viṁśati
…
(Viṣṇu Purāṇa)
Eight million four hundred thousand different
species of life, the soul and its evolution
going from aquatic species lower, evolving
to higher, to higher, to higher, at last achieving
human life. And then being born into a particular
family according to karmic destiny. So real
and this happening so many times.
janame janame sabe pitā mātā pāya
kṛṣṇa guru nahi mile bhaja hari ei
Birth after birth, janame janame pitā mātā
pāya, you get mother and father, but it’s
very rare to meet Krishna’s agent, Sri Guru,
and engage in the worship of Hari, Sri Hari,
Krishna. So, when he responded that way, Guru
Maharaj said, those words, struck his heart
like lightning, and he thought, “I can’t
deny that what he’s saying is true. Yes,
we’re wandering through this mayic samsar.”
brahmāṇḍa-bhramite kona bhāgyavān jīva
guru-kṛṣṇa-prasāde pāya bhakti-latā-bīja
(Śrī Caitanya-caritāmṛta, Madhya-līlā,
19.151)
When Guru Maharaj returned to his village
Hapaniya after so many years being gone, Achyutananda
Maharaj was with him at the time, and, again,
a family member was charmed to see him accompanied
by some boy from New York City, you know,
this doesn’t happen every day in a Bengali
village, you show up with a boy from New York
city. And so, they’re, sort of, delightfully
charmed and puzzled at this. So someone said,
“How… We’re from this land, the land
of Mahaprabhu, and we don’t have so much
appreciation, but you’re from New York City
and you’re appreciating. How is that possible?”
And Achyutananda answer by saying,
brahmāṇḍa bhramite kona bhāgyavān jīva
guru-kṛṣṇa-prasāde pāya bhakti-latā-bīja
(Śrī Caitanya-caritāmṛta, Madhya-līlā,
19.151)
It is not a question of GPS or mundane location,
someone in a particular mundane location will
come in connection with this, but bhāgyavān
jīva: it is divine good fortune that one
may get this connection.
And Guru Maharaj like to quote the poet Magha
who wrote this book Shishupal-badha, “The
death of Shishupal”, where he says, “Your
present position has some indication of the
past as well as the future.” So, if there
is some present connection with Krishna consciousness,
appreciation—that is indicative of some
past brush with the nirguna plane. And it’s
also indicative of a bright future.
… muktir hitvānyathā-rūpaṁ svarūpeṇa
vyavasthitiḥ
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 2.10.6)
The fate, the happy future of all of those
in connection substantially with the agent
of Krishna, through the Krishna consciousness
movement, a life of love with Krishna.
jīvera ‘svarūpa’ haya—kṛṣṇera
‘nitya-dāsa’ …
(Śrī Caitanya-caritāmṛta, Madhya-līlā,
20.108)
Eternal servitude in a loving relationship
with Krishna. So, Guru Maharaj, that chance:
meeting with that fellow student, again and
what did he say appreciated about him?—Some
self-giving tendency, the self-sacrifice,
the dharmic nature of Ramachandra, also the
atmanivedanam to the extreme of Srimati Radharani.
That Her very name Aradhita indicates that,
one who worships Krishna by offering Herself
fully to Him and His divine will. These things
attracted him.
And when he heard the pastimes of Gauranga
Mahaprabhu, he said, he devoured them like
nectar and that set him on search for the
lotus feet of Srila Bhakti Siddhanta Saraswati
Thakur whom Srila Guru Maharaj recognized
as Mahaprabhu’s agent. The other verse in
the beginning of Prapanna-jivanamritam:
gaura-vāg-vigrahaṁ vande gaurāṅgaṁ
gaura-vaibhavam
gaura-saṅkīrtanonmattaṁ gaura-kāruṇya-sundaram
(Śrī Śrī Prapanna-jīvanāmṛtam, 1.2)
Gaura-vāg-vigrahaṁ: really, the personification
of the teachings of Sri Chaitanyadeva realized
in Srila Bhakti Siddhanta Saraswati Thakur.
We’re told, before, when it was announced
to Saraswati Thakur: Guru Maharaj is seeking
his connection—that he quoted the verse
from Bhagavad-gita:
yad yad а̄carati śreṣṭhas …
(Bhagavad-gītā, 3.21)
“What the great men do, they’re like mahajans,
showing the way for others.” So, he’s
saying, “If someone like this, referring
to Srila Guru Maharaj’s high status and
brahmanical culture, Bhattacharya—saying—if
someone like this joins our mission it will
lend prestige to the institution.” And so
even Saraswati Thakur is recognizing that
in him and also the ability to represent him.
When Srila Saraswati Thakur would give a talk
it was so high and so deep, and refined that
even though his disciples were qualified by
birth and culture—still it was beyond their
grasp. So, after hearing that they would approach
Srila Guru Maharaj after the lecture to explain
to them what he said. So that indicates another
position on him being able to properly and
fully, comprehensively represent Srila Saraswati
Thakur.
And with a certificate no less than from Srila
Saraswati Thakur himself: when he read Guru
Maharaj’s composition the Bhaktivinoda-viraha
Dashakam, particularly the shloka where he
says:
śrī-gaurānumataṁ svarūpa-viditaṁ rūpāgrajenādṛtaṁ
rūpādyaiḥ pariveśitaṁ raghu-gaṇair
āsvāditaṁ sevitam
jīvādyair abhirakṣitaṁ śuka-śiva-brahmādi-sammānitaṁ
śrī-rādhā-pada-sevanāmṛtam aho tad
dātum īśo bhavān
(Śrīmad Bhakti Vinoda-viraha Daśakam, 9)
And we’re told when Srila Saraswati Thakur—he
is seeing all the verses, but when he saw
this particular one, he said, “Who has written
this?” And someone said, “Oh, Sridhar
Maharaj.” And he said, “No, Sridhar Maharaj
has not written this, Bhakti Vinod Thakur
has written this through him.” He considered
it that perfect: it was as if it was from
the pen of Bhakti Vinod Thakur himself. And
what was he identifying but what is the Krishna
consciousness movement substantially and what
is the gift of Bhakti Vinod Thakur to the
world in the form of the Krishna consciousness
movement. What Srila Swami Maharaj Prabhupada
took around the world in pursuance of the
order of Srila Saraswati Thakur to fulfill
the divine vision of Bhakti Vinod, here very
beautifully very perfectly encapsulated.
śrī-gaurānumataṁ svarūpa-viditaṁ …
(Śrīmad Bhakti Vinoda-viraha Daśakam, 9)
The real reason for the appearance of Mahaprabhu
in this world—that’s only understood fully
by Swarup Damodar. As we hear in the Chaitanya-charitamritam—how
is Swarup Damodar described as?
… mahа̄prabhura [haya iṅha] dvitīya
kalevara …
(Śrī Caitanya-caritāmṛta, Madhya-līlā,
11.76)
Mahaprabhu the second or His other self. When
Krishna Das Kaviraj Gosvami is providing the
foundation for Sri Chaitanya-charitamritam,
he says that, “Really what I’m giving
here, all of this I got from Raghunath Das
Gosvami, the prayojan-tattva acharya of the
Rupanuga line. But that Raghunath Das Goswami,
what he got was from the notes and personal
sharing and instructions of Swarup Damodar.”
So really when Mahaprabhu tells in that Gundicha
pastime, “You are Gaudiya”—that’s
really a high compliment. Everyone in this
line or aspiring for a service connection
with this line—it will all go to Swarup
Damodar—who we know from the indications
of Mahaprabhu’s parishads, like Kavi Karnapur,
is none other than Lalita Sakhi. So Radharani’s
right hand personal attendant right. So Guru
Maharaj says here in the beginning, śrī-gaurānumataṁ
svarūpa-viditaṁ, the full reason and understanding
for the descent of Mahaprabhu is known only
to Swarup Damodar—that’s why Kaviraj Goswami
is quoting him and that Swarup Damodar is
also appreciating the position of Rupa Goswami.
So,
śrī-gaurānumataṁ svarūpa-viditaṁ rūpāgrajenādṛtaṁ
…
(Śrīmad Bhakti Vinoda-viraha Daśakam, 9)
And Sanatan Goswami here taken to be the elder
brother of Rupa Gosvami and given some prominence
here. This substance of the internal reason
for the descent of Mahaprabhu, His ecstatic
emotional interior this is ādṛtaṁ—worshipped
by Sanatan Goswami Prabhu.
… rūpāgrajenādṛtaṁ rūpādyaiḥ
pariveśitaṁ …
(Śrīmad Bhakti Vinoda-viraha Daśakam, 9)
And Rupa Goswami, as we heard recently in
Charitamritam after the Ratha-yatra festival
in Vrindavan pastimes, when Mahaprabhu is
introducing Rupa Goswami to all of his followers,
He’s indicating that he is the person qualified
to carry on substantially what is Mahaprabhu’s
line so much so that it becomes known as—those
in the line— as Rupanugas. So Mahaprabhu
asked there in that assembly for Rupa Goswami
to reveal the ishta-devata of the book he
is writing, the work. And of course, it’s
Mahaprabhu. He says:
anarpita-carīṁ cirāt karuṇayāvatīrṇaḥ
kalau
samarpayitum unnatojjvala-rasāṁ sva-bhakti-śriyam
…
(Śrī Caitanya-caritāmṛta, Ādi-līlā,
1.4; 3.4; Antya-līlā, 1.132)
Saying: Shachi Nandana, Shachi Nandan Gauranga
Mahaprabhu or, as Guru Maharaj told in the
beginning, guru-rūpa-hariṁ gauraṁ rādhā-ruci-rucāvṛtam.
Now when Krishna has taken the Guru-rupa—
… rādhā-bhāva-dyuti-suvalitaṁ naumi
kṛṣṇa-svarūpam
(Śrī Caitanya-caritāmṛta, Ādi-līlā,
1.5; 4.55)
He’s enveloped in the heart and halo of
Srimati Radharani. From that position he’s
disseminating Krishna consciousness. So, Rupa
Goswami in his books is revealing his ishta
devata, his worshipable deity, is none other
than Gauranga Mahaprabhu, rādhā-bhāva-dyuti-suvalitaṁ,
who is Krishna enveloped in the heart and
halo of Srimati Radharani and then that gives
some indication of from which perspective
his work is going to be presented.
… rūpādyaiḥ pariveśitaṁ raghu-gaṇair
āsvāditaṁ sevitam …
(Śrīmad Bhakti Vinoda-viraha Daśakam, 9)
So, and Raghunath Das Goswami who also considers
himself a Rupanuga, he is the prayojan-tattva
of the Gaudiya line. And what are his works?
The Vilapa-kusumanjali, a very favorite work
of Srila Guru Maharaj. Particularly, he liked
to quote a shloka from there:
dа̄syа̄ya te mama raso ’stu raso ’stu
satyam
sakhyа̄ya te mama namo ’stu namo ’stu
nityaṁ …
(Śrīla Raghunāth Dās Goswāmī. Śrī
Vilāpa-kusumāñjali, 16)
Where Raghunath Das Goswami’s saying, as
the prayojan-tattva Acharya, who’s ultimately
indicating what is the focal point of everyone
in this line, he’s saying, “If there is
no superior servitor there, I don’t crave
intimacy. I don’t crave the intimacy, intimate
service, if there is no superior servitor
there—what would I be doing there?” He’s
saying—so rather,
… dа̄syа̄ya te mama raso ’stu raso
’stu satyam
(Śrīla Raghunāth Dās Goswāmī. Śrī
Vilāpa-kusumāñjali, 16)
“I’m trying for the least aspect of seva.”
And that sort of thing is echoed in the sentiments
of Rupa Gosvami and praise of Lalita—another
favorite shloka of Guru Maharaj:
rādhā-mukunda-pada-sambhava-gharma-bindu-
nirmañcanopakaraṇī-kṛta-deha-lakṣām
uttuṅga-sauhṛda-viśeṣa-vaśāt pragalbhāṁ
devīṁ guṇaiḥ sulalitāṁ lalitāṁ
namāmi
(Śrīla Rūpa Goswāmī. Śrī Lalita Aṣṭakam,
1)
That Lalita Sakhi is focused on the least
aspect of seva, to not allow any disturbance
to go into the upper world. Again, it’s
echoing the sentiments expressed in the song
of Srila Saraswati Thakur. When they transferred
the deities of Gandharvika-Giridhari from
the Gaudiya Math, their hired house in Ulta
Danga, to their new flagship math in Bhag
Bazaar, what did he write?—
pūjala rāga-patha gaurava-bhaṅge
mа̄tala harijana viṣaya raṅge…
(Śrīla Bhakti Siddhānta Sarasvatī Ṭhākur)
That the path of raga-marg—that shall always
be kept in a higher position, one level above,
consistent with his indication of Govardhan
being the ultimate aspiration for those in
this line, in his line. Why? He’s saying,
“From Govardhan the servitors go to Kusum-sarovar
to collect flowers to serve the superior Guru-varga
in Radha-kunda and return to Govardhan”.
Guru Maharaj is telling when they’re building
one of the residences in the math, in one
of the maths in Mayapur, when Saraswati Thakur
said his residence would be on the ground
floor, Guru Maharaj and the other devotees
thought, “Well, then who could live above
him?”—You know, that wouldn’t be good,
right? So they’re thinking, “If you’re
going to be on the ground floor, then who
will be above you?” And Saraswati Thakur
said, “Oh, that’s for our Guru-varga.
They’ll be staying there. We’re always
in a lower position, one level removed.”
All of these things are connected, his sannyas.
Sannyas—the highest position in varnashrama,
but bowing to the paramahamsa babajis. As
when one babaji in Vrindavan was contesting
Saraswati Thakur’s giving brahmanical initiation
irrespective of class, cast. Keshava Maharaj
and Guru Maharaj were speaking with that gentleman.
Keshava Maharaj ultimately said, “What do
you consider higher: the brahmin thread or
the kaupin of the babaji?” And he said,
“The kaupin of the babajis!”—“But
that you’re giving irrespective of cast.”
And then Guru Maharaj told him, “Actually,
we worship the babajis as higher, they’re
worshipable to us.” And he said as he began
speaking in that way the man was like [showing
proud expression]. But at the conclusion Guru
Maharaj said, “But we don’t consider you
that, so don’t mind.”
But he told, “They’re actually pujala
raga-path, the raga-marg, the path of spontaneous
devotion, the gopi-bhav, that’s worshipable
to us, in the higher plane. We don’t bring
that down here for fear of polluting it.”
… jīvādyair abhirakṣitaṁ …
(Śrīmad Bhakti Vinoda-viraha Daśakam, 9)
Next line. And Jiva Goswami, Baladev Vidiyabhushan,
they’re protecting this divine substance
from adulteration, from modification or from
those who would challenge its legitimacy—that’s
the seva of Jiva Goswami. And Guru Maharaj
points out in one of his shloka to Saraswati
Thakur:
sri-jiva-tejas-tatih
With the type of fervor and fire of Jiva Gosvami
Saraswati Thakur was defending the line of
Bhakti Vinod Thakur and the Rupanuga line—in
a similar way. So, they’re like Rakshak,
Bhakti Rakshak. I once suggested this can
be rendered as ‘Guardian of devotion’
and Guru Maharaj and Gurudev—they happily
accepted that. The “Rakshak”, “the guardian”,
Bhakti Rakshak, “the guardian of devotion”—in
the same way: to protect it from modification,
adulteration or from those who would challenge
its legitimacy. When someone tried to, with
Srila Guru Maharaj himself, challenged the
legitimacy of Saraswati Thakur’s preaching
saying what he is giving—it is not Vedic.
He tried this approach, saying it’s contradicting
what is given in Veda or it’s not Vedic
in its foundation. Guru Maharaj responded
by saying, “What are the Vedas and what
is their target?”
The Vedas—when we speak about the rishis—they’re
the recorded statements of the rishis: they’ve
recorded their observations of the truth and
that’s what they’re presenting. And what
is it primarily, [of] these categories—Brahma,
Paramatma, Bhagavan?—It’s primarily Brahma
with some Paramatma and a hint of Bhagavan—this
is their presentation. It’s like
... а̄rya-pathaṁ ca hitvа̄ …
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 10.47.61)
Uddhava is saying, “The Braja-gopis—they
have rejected that, they’ve crossed over
that. So, a hint of Bhagavan they’re giving.
But our Guru Maharaja and Bhakti Vinod Thakur—what
are they giving?—Mahaprabhu’s full-fledged
theistic Krishna conception. Something needs
attention. Hare Krishna. Don’t want an explosion.
Hare Krishna. Anyway, so Srila Guru Maharaj
in a very short way he demonstrated that,
actually, what Bhakti Siddhanta Saraswati
Thakur is giving and Bhakti Vinod Thakur are
giving to the world surpasses what was given
by the Vedic rishis. So, defeating this type
of challenge. So,
… jīvādyair abhirakṣitaṁ …
(Śrīmad Bhakti Vinoda-viraha Daśakam, 9)
Why?—Shuka, Shiva, Brahma, they’re aspiring
for a drop of this substance, even higher—Uddhava.
āsām aho caraṇa-reṇu-juṣām ahaṁ
syāṁ
vṛndāvane kim api gulma-latauṣadhīnām
yā dustyajaṁ sva-janam ārya-pathaṁ ca
hitvā
bhejur mukunda-padavīṁ śrutibhir vimṛgyām
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 10.47.61)
When a pandit from South India who knew the
entire Shrimad-Bhagavatam met with Srila Guru
Maharaj and Guru Maharaj said, “And you
know all… committed to memory all eighteen
thousand shlokas of the Bhagavatam. In your
estimation, who are the greatest devotees?”
And he said, “The four Kumaras”.
tasyāravinda-nayanasya padāravinda-
kiñjalka-miśra-tulasī-makaranda-vāyuḥ
antar-gataḥ sva-vivareṇa cakāra teṣāṁ
saṅkṣobham akṣara-juṣām api citta-tanvoḥ
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 3.15.43)
How
they were transformed by the aroma of the
Tulasi and the lotus feet of the Lord. So,
the Kumaras—they’re in the highest position,
they’re the greatest sages. What do you
say? And Guru Maharaj he said, “They’re
in the lowest position.”— “What?!”
And with two shlokas he demonstrated who’s
holding the highest position. Bhakti Vinod
talks about barabahi and sarahgrahi. Barabahi
means like an ass, a pack animal, saying,
all these books, all this literature, if you’re
a great scholar and not a sarahgrahi, one
who can extract the essence—you’re carrying
around like a burden. It’s the weight of
scholastic academic understanding. So, eighteen
thousand shlokas he’s carrying with him,
but can’t discern who are the supreme devotees.
So, with two shlokas the sarahgrahi, the one
who can extract the essence, Guru Maharaj
says, “First—from the mouth of Krishna.
We must agree: the Bhagavat Purana, Shrimad-Bhagavatam:
śrīmad-bhа̄gavataṁ pramа̄ṇam-amalaṁ
…
(Śrīla Viśvanāth Cakravarti Ṭhākur)
If Krishna’s speaking there there’s no
greater authority than Krishna it’s the
book of Krishna or as Prabhupad said, “Krishna
book.” So, if Krishna says this is the greatest
devotee—that has to be accepted. What does
Krishna say?
na tathā me priyatama
ātma-yonir na śaṅkaraḥ
na ca saṅkarṣaṇo na śrīr
naivātmā ca yathā bhavān
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 11.14.15)
From no less than the mouth of Krishna, He
says: not ātma-bhu, Brahma, who you hear
so much in the Bhagavatam, Brahma-stuti. What
does he said? He said in that shloka:
… kiṁ bahūktyā …
jānanta eva jānantu …
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 10.14.38)
That Brahma is saying.—Not him.
Na ca saṅkarṣaṇo, na śrīr—not Lakshmi,
the goddess of fortune; said, in fact, naivātmā
ca yathā bhavān, “My own self I’m not
as dear to me as my devotee, as Uddhava—as
you, Uddhava.” So here He establishes the
primacy of the position of Uddhava. And then
what?—Second shloka. So, from the mouth
of Krishna He indicates Uddhava. And then
we say, “Oh, Uddhava! Krishna says, you’re
the highest devotee, you’re the best. Not
even Himself is as dear to Himself as you.”
And what do you say, Uddhava? Uddhava:
āsām aho caraṇa-reṇu-juṣām ahaṁ
syāṁ
vṛndāvane kim api gulma-latauṣadhīnām
…
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 10.47.61)
“Having seen Radharani and the Braja-gopis,
I am aspiring for an atomic presence in the
soil of Vrindavan, so that some of the dust
from their lotus feet may come upon my head
thereby consecrating my existence.” So,
with two shlokas from Krishna to Uddhava,
from Uddhava to the Braja-gopis. And what
does Guru Maharaj say in one shloka, his own?
yadamiya-mahimā-śrī-bhāgavatyāḥ kathāyāṁ
pratipadam anubhūtaṁ chāpy alabdhābhidheyā
tad akhila-rasa-mūrti-śyāma-līlāvalambaṁ
madhura-rasa-dhi-rādhā-pādapadmaṁ prapadye
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj)
Although Her name is not mentioned, at every
step, every shloka, every indication along
the way is to take one in the direction of
the holy lotus feet of Srimati Radharani.
That’s Guru Maharaj’s shloka saying. And
these eighteen thousand shlokas—what are
you supposed to understand from that—Radha-dasyam,
that the only thing in life, worth aspiring
for, is service to the lotus feet of Radharani.
She controls Krishna. She has the copyright,
trademark, registered owner of Krishna. Go
to Her and then you’ll get Krishna automatically.
Don’t waste your time trying to go directly
to Krishna, He’s crooked.
… [śyа̄mam]̇tri-bhaṅga-lalitaṁ niyata-prakа̄śaṁ
…
(Śrī Brahma-saṁhitā, 5.31)
That’s some indication of his ways.
aher iva gatiḥ premṇaḥ svabhа̄va-kuṭilа̄
bhavet …
(Śrī Caitanya-caritāmṛta, Madhya-līlā,
8.111 and 14.163)
Autocrat, despot and liar—Krishna. Like
the master chef: you’ve got your little…
your ingredients—gives that to the master
chef and they’ll turn it into some inconceivably
nectarine substance. That’s our system:
whatever, however, on whatever level this
resonates in your heart, you have some serving
energy, some serving capacity—give that,
that little energy, whatever it is—give
that, offer it to the lotus feet of Sri Guru.
So Uddhava aspires for it. Then this big buildup,
what is it?—He’s saying, “Mahaprabhu
came down here to distribute something, but
Swarup Damodar only really knows fully what
it is, Sanatan Goswami is worshiping it, Rupa
Goswami is distributing it, Raghunath Das—and
Krishna Das by extension—they’re tasting
it and instead of it becoming less tasteful
by their tasting it, it’s becoming increasingly
tasteful.”
… śuka-mukhа̄d amṛtа-drava-saṁyutam
…
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 1.1.3)
It’s becoming even more pleasing. So, what
is it? And he says,
… śrī-rādhā-pada-sevanāmṛtam aho
tad dātum īśo bhavān
(Śrīmad Bhakti Vinoda-viraha Daśakam, 9)
Bhakti Vinod Thakur’s gift to the world
is this prospect, this possibility: he’s
bringing us, giving us the opportunity to
come in connection with the service of the
holy lotus feet of Srimati Radharani and that’s
why Mahaprabhu descended.
yadi gaura nā hoita, tabe ki hoita,
kemone dharitām de
rādhāra mahimā, prema-rasa-sīmā
jagate jānāta ke
(Śrīla Vāsudev Ghoṣ)
The great associates of Mahaprabhu—they’re
saying the same thing. Just it’s so beautiful
that they can say it in a fresh and new, and
palpable, tasteful, meaningful way. That’s
why:
… śuka-mukhа̄d amṛtа-drava-saṁyutam
…
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 1.1.3)
It is becoming more relishable. When Guru
Maharaj expresses these things it becomes
more relishable and it’s relishable by us,
he’s extending the capacity to relish this
substance. That’s what is the
… tad dātum īśo … aho!
(Śrīmad Bhakti Vinoda-viraha Daśakam, 9)
It’s the Sanskrit like for ‘ooh!’—that’s
how you express astonishment and it’s in
Sanskrit ‘aho!’— “Ooh, Bhakti Vinod,
this is your gift to the world, this is what
has come to us in the form of the Krishna
consciousness movement. This is unthinkable,
unthinkable of unthinkable things. The, you
know, impossible of impossible things. This
is your gift to the world.” That’s why
Saraswati Thakur said, “Who wrote this?
Who wrote this?” They go, “Sridhar Maharaj.”—
“No, Sridhar Maharaj has not written this,
Bhakti Vinod Thakur has written this through
him.” It’s that perfect, the representation,
and very beautifully as Srila Keshava Maharaj
said, reading Guru Maharaj’s writing—he
said, “The perfect combination of ontological
substance and poetic beauty.” Someone can
put ontology there, but it’s not sweet.
Someone can write some sweet rhyming words,
but there’s no substance, it’s sentiment.
Here we’re finding the highest philosophical
expression of the divine reality and sweetly
expressed.
Brahma, Brahma-samhita—what did he said?
… kandarpa-koṭi-kamanīya-viśeṣa-śobhaṁ
…
(Śrī Brahma-saṁhitā, 5.30)
How beautiful is Krishna? Shobhana Krishna,
Krishna-shobha. 10 million cupids personified
as one—that type of, it scares us, that
thing. We think, “One cupid is more than
we can handle”—for this world, pivoting
on the erotic principle. Here—10 million
cupids combined into one! Like the ladies
in Mathura when they see Krishna: lāvaṇya-sāram—
gopyas tapaḥ [kim acaran yad amuṣya rūpaṁ]
lāvaṇya-sāram asamordhvam ananya-siddham
dṛgbhiḥ pibanty anusavābhinavaṁ durāpam
ekānta-dhāma yaśasaḥ śriya aiśvarasya
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 10.44.14)
gopyas tapaḥ kim acaran yad amuṣya rūpaṁ
…
The first thing they think, “Krishna’s
so beautiful!”—this is how devotees think.
They think, “What do the gopis do that they
get to see Him all the time?” They’ve
just seen Krishna for the first time, we can
say—immediately they’re saying, “What
do the gopis do—they get to see Him all
the time? Did they do some special... is it
a special mantra? Then give me that mantra.
Or it’s like… You have to fast a certain
way or at a certain time, or stand on one
foot, you know… —Just tell me what it
is, I want to get that! I want…” Krishna
is inconceivably beautiful:
… lāvaṇya-sāram asamordhvam ananya-siddham
…
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 10.44.14)
Inconceivably beautiful, lāvaṇya-sāram
means like “beauty cream”, the cream of
all beautiful substance. Saying, “So, please,
tell me, what did they do? What did they do?”
No, it’s not some particular austerity,
they do things like that superficially. What
is it? They gave their hearts to Krishna,
themselves heart and soul. That’s why Guru
Maharaj said, “When I think of Radharani
I lose meself. So, when I think of Her level
of self-giving and self-sacrifice, everything
else becomes trash.” He can say that, we
can’t really say that. As Guru Maharaj also
said, “Our problem is this world, you know—we
like it or we think we do, or we think we’re
going to find some way to adjust it, fine-tune
it in our favor. And we’re incessantly seduced
by this prospect: that material happiness
is just around the corner, you know. Coming
soon and… and we have to deal with that.”
What can break that?
jāta-śraddho mat-kathāsu
nirviṇṇaḥ sarva-karmasu
veda duḥkhātmakān kāmān
parityāge ’py anīśvaraḥ
(Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, 11.20.27)
“Liking this”—you don’t have to understand
it, fortunately. It’s beyond human comprehension.
So sometimes Guru Maharaj said, “We’re
mad men having a mad talk.” Mahaprabhu says
that:
а̄mi—eka bа̄tula tumi—dvitīya bа̄tula
…
(Śrī Caitanya-caritāmṛta, Madhya-līlā,
8.291)
“I’m the crazy number one, you’re crazy
number two for listening to Me.” That’s
what he’s saying but:
yā niśā sarva-bhūtānāṁ
tasyāṁ jāgarti saṁyamī …
(Bhagavad-gītā, 2.69)
Actually, like what is, people may think what
Einstein and Niels Bohr, what they’re talking—that’s
crazy. These Einstein and his friends, Einstein
and friends, you know— they’re crazy if
you hear them talk. Or—is it: they’re
not so crazy, they’re talking about something,
that’s actually very meaningful, very refined,
very real, very much real, not a mad fantasy.
That’s the secret to that talk, yet the
people in general may think that it’s madness
or be unable to penetrate. So much so that
Kaviraj Goswami said, “Actually these things
should not be revealed. So why am I doing
it?” Gurudev said to Guru Maharaj about
the Brahma Gayatri explanation, “Maharaj,
why are you revealing this? Not to. Maybe,
better not to.” And Guru Maharaj said, “If
I don’t—who will?” And also, as Kaviraj
Goswami says, “If you’re not qualified
to appreciate this, you’ll just think, it’s
madness,” he said, “so even though it
shouldn’t be spoken, I couldn’t be happier
than knowing that only qualified people will
be able to appreciate it.”
That’s what Srila Saraswati Thakur recognized
in Srila Guru Maharaj: the quality for this
sort of depth of appreciation. The same thing
when Mahaprabhu sees the shloka of Rupa Goswami,
the parallel shloka. Mahaprabhu before Jagannath
at the Ratha-yatra is singing the equivalent
of a mundane song. I mean, to put in a modern
context, imagine: we’re at Ratha-yatra and
then someone starts singing some mundane song
everybody knows from the radio.—And seems
to be very moved by the whole thing. That
would be a test of faith. Those devotees,
because they’re so qualified, they don’t
think anything of it. They can’t explain
it, but it doesn’t bother them, they’re
lost in their own divine madness, we can say.
But Swarup Damodar knows, svarūpa viditaṁ.
And then Mahaprabhu finds the shloka written
on a bamboo, you’ve seen the way they etch,
that’s how the books—they still have them,
here you can find them, with a pen—what
do you call it— a stylus, etching into the
bamboo skin. Mahaprabhu sees the shloka. And
it’s revealing, unlocking all the mystery
of what He’s singing before Jagannath. And
he shows it to Swarup Damodar and say, “How
can Rupa know this?” And Swarup Damodar—because
they know, only the two of them know—Swarup
Damodar says, “Oh, well, how can anybody
know anything about Krishna consciousness?
You must have revealed it to them, it must
have Your divine backing.” And this is the
point: the same way Rupa Goswami’s saying…
“Oh, well we’ll never have that…”—No,
everyone connected in this line, particularly,
by the grace of Srila Guru Maharaj, [he] is
getting access to those things. But how? If
there’s any appreciation, the same answer
is there, “You must have given it to them”.
And that’s why Guru Maharaj, as exalted
as he was, amazingly revered everyone newly
connected to Krishna consciousness.
This was not a posing on his part, he would
say, “We shall revere the person newly connected.”
We think, “But wait, you’re the epitome,
Krishna consciousness personified.” And
what is he saying at 92, “I am a student
and I shall forever remain a student.” He
is our leader and he’s saying, “I am a
student.” The professor, the perfect professor
saying, “I’m a student and I shall ever
remain a student.” Quoting Saraswati Thakur
in Madras when teacher withdraws from the
class one of the advanced students becomes
the monitor. That was his example, he’s
a perfect teacher, Guru Maharaj is saying,
“I didn’t like to hear that example, I
don’t think of him that way.” But he’s
presenting himself that way. Guru Maharaj
he’s saying at 92, “I’m a student. I
shall forever remain a student.” The finite
is going to meet the infinite. Vrindavan Das:
“according to the capacity”—a bird flying
in infinite sky—how high can you go? Or
diving into an infinite ocean. When Mahaprabhu
is going to explain Bhakti-rasamrita-sindhu
to Rupa Goswami, He is saying, “Rupa, the
length and breadth of this divine ocean is
unlimited but I will take one drop and explain
that to you. And that’s also unlimited:
a drop of the infinite is also infinite.”
So Srila Guru Maharaj said, “We shall revere
even a new person because now they have a
connection with this divine substance. And
maybe, we’re stagnating or not going, making
so much progress, and the new person will
surpass me.” He said, “And if I properly
revere them and their connection with this
divine substance, I’ll be in a position
to receive grace from them in the future.”
So, this sort of insight, we can only think
of Mahaprabhu’s saying, “What is the unbearable
suffering in this world?” You think: separation
from the devotee. Interestingly, there he
doesn’t say “Krishna”—says “the
devotee,” but because it’s to include:
without the devotee there is no Krishna. That’s
the long and short of it. Only a mirage of
Krishna, a superficial representation of Krishna.
Without the devotee we have no Krishna. And
that’s Guru Maharaj’s one of his other
favorites and that of Saraswati Thakur—from
the Vilapa-kusumanjali of Raghunath Das Goswami.
āśā-bharair-amṛta-sindhu-mayaiḥ kathāṛchit
kālo mayāti gamitaḥ kila sāmprataṁ
hi
tvaṁ cet kṛpamayi vidhāsyasi naiva kiṁ
me
prāṇair vrajena ca varoru bakarināpi
(Śrīla Raghunāth Dās Goswāmī. Śrī
Vilāpa-kusumāñjali, 102)
This exclusive devotion to Srimati Radharani
and Her extended self-surrogate Sri Guru.
[He is] saying, “My life is an aspiration
to serve Your holy lotus feet, without which
of what value is my life?” This is how the
servitor gauges the meaningfulness of their
existence. “My life is an aspiration to
serve You. If that’s not possible then what
would I do with life?” And you say, “Oh,
well you can go to Vrindavan.” [He] says,
“But without you, Guru, Sri Guru, what good
is Vrindavan to me? And to ratchet it up further:
“And Krishna Himself is of no use to me
without you.” So really the connection all
of us have with Krishna consciousness is through
the devotees of Krishna. And it’s all—as
Guru Maharaj explains in his Gayatri:
… bhargo vai vṛṣabhānu-jātma-
vibhavaikārādhanā-śrīpuram …
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj)
“The whole spiritual world is a construct
of the heart of Srimati Radharani to serve
Krishna.” So, it always comes back to this.
It’s what Guru Maharaj impressed upon us
from the first meeting, from day one meeting
with him to the end, until now. That this
is the thing worth dedicating ourselves to
in life and if we get that chance, that opportunity,
as it is been given to us from his divine
grace and his eternal associates Srila Bhakti
Sundar Govinda Dev-Goswami Maharaj, Srila
Bhaktivedanta Swami Prabhupad, who we revere
as our Guru-varga. Then on this day by the
pull of affection Srila Guru Maharaj in his
beautiful susiddhanta, irresistibly beautiful
Krishna conception, but particularly through
Mahaprabhu—and just to close with this.
So, he said, “Brahma:
… kandarpa-koṭi-kamanīya-viśeṣa-śobhaṁ
…
(Śrī Brahma-saṁhitā, 5.30)
That Krishna, Reality the Beautiful. But that
Krishna under the influence and the heart
and halo of Srimati Radharani. What did Guru
Maharaj say?—
svarṇa-koṭi-darpaṇābha-deha-varṇa-gauravaṁ
padma-pārijāta-gandha-vanditāṅga-saurabham
koṭi-kāma-mūrchitāṅghri-rūpa-rāsa-raṅgaraṁ
prema-dhāma-devam eva naumi gaura-sundaram
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj.
Śrī Śrī Prema-dhāma-deva-stotram, 2)
Guru Maharaj is so much in love with Mahaprabhu—he
blushes when he talks about Mahaprabhu. The
way someone…If you realize that someone—like
when you discover somebody is in love with
someone and they start blushing, you mention
their name, they can’t, they’re trying,
they don’t want anybody to know, but they
can’t hide it. They blush. Guru Maharaj
would blush like a pink lotus at the mention
of Mahaprabhu Gauranga Sundar. He can’t
contain that.
And here what did he say:
… svarṇa-koṭi-darpaṇābha-deha …
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj.
Śrī Śrī Prema-dhāma-deva-stotram, 2)
How Gaura is Gauranga? How golden is Gauranga?
And the beauty of Radharani’s heart when
he’s enveloped—he said, svarṇa-koṭi-darpaṇābha-deha-varṇa-gauravaṁ,
like 10 million brilliant mirrors of gold.
If you had 10 million brilliant, you know,
shining mirrors of gold—that’s like that.
If that could be made into one—that’s
how radiant is Gauranga Mahaprabhu, the heart
and halo of Radharani:
... rа̄dhа̄-ruci-rucа̄vṛtam …
(Śrī Śrī Prapanna-jīvanāmṛtam, 1.3)
… padma-pārijāta-gandha-vanditāṅga[-saurabham]
koṭi-kāma-mūrcitāṅghri-rūpa-rāsa-raṅgaraṁ
…
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj.
Śrī Śrī Prema-dhāma-deva-stotram, 2)
And what does he say here? “10 million Cupids
would faint to see the beauty of Mahaprabhu.”
Rupa Goswami said:
rasoddа̄mа̄ kа̄mа̄rbuda-madhura-dhа̄mojjvala-tanur,
yatīnа̄m uttaṁsas [taraṇikara-]vidyoti-vasanaḥ
…
(Śrīla Rūpa Goswāmī. Śrī Caitanyāṣṭakam,
4)
Even the garments of Mahaprabhu are glowing—so
much radiance’s coming from Him. He said—his
cupids, 10 million cupids in full-blown rasidic
cupidity.
rasoddа̄mа̄ kа̄mа̄rbuda-madhura-dhа̄mo
…
(Śrīla Rūpa Goswāmī. Śrī Caitanyāṣṭakam,
4)
How sweet and irresistible is the form of
Mahaprabhu. But what is Guru Maharaj saying?—“And
those 10 million cupids—they’ll faint
to see the beauty, how beautiful is Mahaprabhu.”
So, in this realm of these concepts—he’s
always living there. Going on with this internal
dialogue every day, churning the nectar ocean
and some new stream of nectarine concept coming
from him. So, it’s our good fortune, Srila
Bhakti Sundar Govinda Dev-Goswami Maharaj
is giving everyone, even till now, the opportunity
to serve the lotus feet of Srila Guru Maharaj—that
is his idea of what this mission is. To, like
Lalita Sakhi, not allow anything, anything
of disturbance or distraction to enter that
plane of seva. So, for us, we have, when the
beep-beep-beep-beep thing goes then someone
can get up and go tend to that. There’s
always some… Bhakti Vinod Thakur says, “the
apparent inconvenience of service necessity
or that burden—he says—that’s the labor
of love.” He’s very happy to have that—the
call of seva. Gurudev, as soon as he identifies
something as being the service to the lotus
feet of Guru Maharaj—he’s eager for that,
to be first in line for that service opportunity.
That’s Das Goswami’s
… dа̄syа̄ya te mama raso ’stu raso
’stu satyam
(Śrīla Raghunāth Dās Goswāmī. Śrī
Vilāpa-kusumāñjali, 16)
Always ready for even the least seva. Hare
Krishna. Srila Avadhut Maharaj, he has that
type of serving tendency and capacity and
he’s giving all of us serving opportunities.
That we need. You cannot maintain Krishna
consciousness without service connection—it’s
impossible, really—or at best you’ll have
a mirage, a fictitious representation of it.
There has to be a service connection.
… sevonmukhe …
… sevonmukhata …
… sevonmukhe hi jihvа̄dau svayam eva sphuraty
[adaḥ]
(Śrī Bhakti-rasāmṛta-sindhu, 1.2.234)
Then these other things that we do are meaningful,
but there has to be service connection. And
thanks the Lord for Srila Avadhut Maharaj
giving us unlimited service connection. And
answering that call I’ll be trying to go
there and represent Guru Maharaj’s…If
I get some opportunity to represent Srila
Guru Maharaj then I think I’m doing something
valuable with my time and energy, my life.
And I advise the same for everybody here.
Hare Krishna.
Jai Srila Bhakti Rakshak Sridhar Dev-Goswami
tirobhav maha-mahotsava tithi ki jai!
Jai Om Vishnupad Paramahamsa Parivrajakacharya
Ashtottara-shata-sri Srimad Bhakti Rakshak
Sridhar Dev-Goswami Maharaj ki jai!
Srila Guru Maharaj tirobhav maha-mahotsav
tithi ki jai!
Jai Om Vishnupad Srila Bhakti Sundar Govinda
Dev-Goswami Maharaj ki jai!
Bhagavan Srila Bhakti Siddhanta Saraswati
Thakur ki jai!
Sri Chaitanya Saraswat Math ki jai!
Sri Chaitanya Saraswat Math bhakta-vrinda
ki jai!
śrīmac-caitanya-sа̄rasvata-maṭhavara-udgīta-kīrtir
jaya-śrīm …
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj)
Guru Maharaj—what is the Chaitanya Saraswat
Math started by him, founded by him?—Well,
the conceptual architecture has been encapsulated
and encrypted in the Math’s pranam-mantram:
śrī-caitanya-sа̄rasvata-maṭhavara-udgīta-kīrtir
jaya-śrīm …
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj)
What first and foremost—he put a flag. Like
we have so much bamboo here, Guru Maharaj
would have liked that, but he would have wanted
to say the biggest bamboo, we have, the tallest
bamboo we have—and there put the flag, announcing:
this is Radharani’s place—it’s for Her
service, promote ‘jaya śrī’ means ‘Radharani.’
… udgīta-kīrtir jaya-śrīm …
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj)
The kīrti, the glorification of ‘jaya śrī,’
of Radharani: to loudly broadcast out, profoundly
broadcast the glories of Radharani, Her position.
That’s why Mahaprabhu descended, that’s
what the members of this Math shall do. What
is its GPS conceptually speaking?
… bibhrat sambhа̄ti gaṅgа̄-taṭа-
...
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj)
On the banks of the Ganga and sprung out from
that soil of Navadwip Dham, kolа̄dri-rа̄je,
where Kolerdanga, Gupta Govardhan. That’s
its location: the hidden Govardhan of Navadwip.
… yatra śrī-gaura-sа̄rasvata-mata-niratа̄-gaura-gа̄thа̄-gṛṇanti
…
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj)
What do they do? Glorifying Mahaprabhu, Radharani,
Sri Guru-Gauranga and Krishna. As Guru Maharaj
said, “Recently I’ve developed some attraction
for Krishna.” And even that he said, “Because
I know, if you’re aspiring for service in
Radharani’s group, of course, you have to
like Krishna.”
… gaura-gа̄thа̄-gṛṇanti …
… nityaṁ-rūpānuga śrī-kṛtamati-guru-gaurа̄ṅga-rа̄dhа̄-jitа̄śа̄
(Śrīla Bhakti Rakṣak Śrīdhar Dev-Goswāmī
Mahārāj)
Aspiring for that service, Śrī Rādhikā-mādhavāśām,
like Das Goswami’s prayer—all very perfectly
expressed. That was Maharaj’s, Gurudev’s
happiness. Srila Govinda Maharaj is saying,
“We know, our Guru, Srila Guru Maharaj is
perfect in every way and we’re happy offering
ourselves and everything in service to his
holy lotus feet.” Hare Krishna!