Without controlled senses
there’s no question of spontaneous love.
[Lust vs. Love]
If someone’s senses,
dhīra …
There’s a śloka that says,
vikrīḍitaṁ vraja-vadhūbhir idaṁ ca viṣṇoḥ
śraddhānvito ’nuśṛṇuyād atha varṇayed yaḥ
bhaktiṁ parāṁ bhagavati pratilabhya kāmaṁ
hṛd-rogam āśv apahinoty achireṇa dhīraḥ
[SB: 10.33.39]
So hṛd-rogam means ‘heart-disease’,
expressed in uncontrolled senses.
So, without the senses
being relatively controlled
that one is going
to express rāga-bhakti,
that means ‘spontaneous love’,
here; ‘rāga-mārg’.
Now we’re back to
Saraswatī Ṭhākur’s cautions, saying,
“If this is not there
at the basis,
then they may be telling
that it’s spontaneous love,
but it is mundane, because
the senses are not controlled.”
So they’re taking
divine things
and making them,
in his words, ‘vulture food’,
saying the senses
are like vultures.
So, if the senses
are under the control of lust,
then there’s no question
of expressing spontaneous love,
which means here
‘rāga-bhakti’, ‘rāga-mārg’.
So, there’s viddhi-mārg;
they have to gradually
come under control.
Then, from that position,
dhīra;
undisturbed,
no sense disturbance,
Then, when they hear
the divine pastimes
of Rādhārāṇī, Kṛṣṇa,
and Vraja-gopīs,
that will awaken spontaneous
loving sentiments within them.
Otherwise we’ll project that our
experience of mundane love,
we’ll project that as being …
we’ll impose that idea
on spontaneous love of rāga-bhaktas,
and that’s an offense
against divinity—
to think these pastimes
are mundane,
like the mundane affairs
between men and women.