Guru Mahārāj says
‘artha’ translates as ‘meaning’,
‘anartha’ means,
from another perspective,
‘misconception’,
the wrong idea.
[Cleansing Consciousness]
So we have the wrong idea
about what Kṛṣṇa consciousness is,
or what is Guru, what is a devotee,
what is Deity.
Everything has to be reconceived.
Reconceptualization.
As Guru Mahārāj says,
“Acquiring the proper angle of vision.”
That’s a lifelong project
for a spiritual practitioner.
It’s not saying,
“Oh, I did that”. No.
It’s, we aspire to that —
cheto-darpaṇa-mārjanaḿ,
how are you going to clearly
reflect upon things
unless a certain amount of cleansing
has taken place?
Cleansing of the consciousness.
Remember, even, interestingly,
when they are doing Gītā promotion
and they quote Thoreau, Emerson,
and all these different people
who appreciated it …
What did Thoreau say,
the American transcendentalist?
Or Emerson, one of the two,
I think it’s Thoreau, he said,
“In the morning I bathe my mind
in the stupendous
cosmogonal glory of Bhagavad-gītā,
in comparison with which
our modern literature
seems puny and trivial.”
So he’s saying, “Every morning I bathe
my intellect with the Bhagavad-gītā.”
It’s a daily cleansing process.
What did Saraswatī Ṭhākur say?
“Beat your mind with a broom
when you wake up.”
And Guru Mahārāj,
the way he said it
—and actually his voice was
practically quivering—he said,
“What have I done?”
(talking about the day before),
“Wasting my life,
wasting my time.
Please, today
let me do something
of value in service
to Guru and Vaiṣṇava.”
So Saraswatī Ṭhākur’s saying,
“Beat the mind with a broom
a hundred times upon rising,”
and that’s when he said,
“and then do what?
Sing Āmāra jīvana.”
… sadā pāpe rata,
nāhiko punyera leṣa …
Bhakti Vinod, the confessional song,
“This is my life,
there’s no sinful activity I haven’t committed
thousands of times.”
These are the sort of expression
that come out of Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur
when he’s taking our position.
So Saraswatī Ṭhākur is saying,
“That’s when you sing that.
When you wake up,
sing that, and say,
‘Let me not waste another day
where there’s no Vaiṣṇava sevā,
Hari-kathā, dedication.’”
Gurudev said, “You can do
spiritual practices anywhere,
but you don’t get sevā anywhere.”
So when sevā comes to you,
you fight for that
and fight to keep that.
Once he was saying if there was
a fight over his succession
to the point of blood,
to the point of death,
he said,
“It’s worth fighting for.”
Yes, it’s worth it.