When we were making
Golden Volcano,
[Pizza-Love | Heart Disease]
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj said …
First he kept saying,
“Golden volcano—divine lava.”
And then he would say,
“Is lava love?”
Like that,
And then he would go on
describing a little more,
“Golden volcano—divine lava.
Is lava love?” And so he asked me,
“Are there any connections
between the word ‘love’ and ‘lava’?”
So, this is pre‒Internet,
pre‒digital,
when there were these things
called libraries,
you’ve probably read about them
on Wikipedia.
[Laughing]
We lived next to a major university
with a pretty large library,
so I went there
and I thought,
“I’m going to consult
what they call ‘OED’”—
the Oxford English Dictionary—
it’s huge, like
each giant book volume
for a letter, like ‘A’, ‘B’ …
So I thought,
“I’ll look up ‘love’
because I couldn’t find any connection
with that and ‘lava’”.
So I find in the book,
‘L’—‘Love’,
and it’s this book you read with
a magnifying glass, the type is very small,
and seeing …
going up and down the page,
and at last it said,
“Sanskrit, from the Sanskrit
lobha, lobhyati,
which means ‘desire’,
like, ‘passionate desire’”.
Like, we know,
if you associate with Americans
for any particular length of time,
you’re likely to hear them
say something like,
“I love pizza!”
So I can say, “Is that love?
Pizza-love—is that love
or are we back to hankering?”
Mundane hankering—
desire to consume something.
When it’s pizza
we can smile and laugh about it;
when it’s another person,
it’s not so funny,
if you’re the one
being consumed or devoured
by somebody’s lust or desire
in the name of love; an attachment.
They’re so attached
to this consuming tendency
that Guru Mahārāj says
is identified in the pages
of the Bhāgavatam
as hṛd-rogam—‘heart disease’.
As he told that man,
“What is the root cause
of suffering?
What is this heart disease?”
This ‘I want’—thinking
if I can acquire something
and devour that, consume that …
We’re called consumers
all over the world;
‘Consumer Protection.’
We’re consumers—
if I can consume something,
I’ll find happiness
and satisfaction, and fulfilment.
And it’s really on the basis
of remembering
the very high śloka,
vikrīḍitaṁ vraja-vadhūbhir idaṁ ca viṣṇoḥ
śraddhānvito ’nuśṛṇuyād atha varṇayed yaḥ
bhaktiṁ parāṁ bhagavati pratilabhya kāmaṁ
[SB: 10.33.39]
It’s so extraordinary
that in this practical dealing and situation
that Guru Mahārāj
would recall this śloka
from the rāsa-līlā section,
but use it
in practical application
by saying
and factoring in reincarnation,
“When I was
in the body of an elephant,
I ate a jungle,
and that hunger wasn’t satisfied;
and when I was in the body
of a stool-eating pig,
I ate a hill of stool,
and it was not satisfied.”
And interestingly, when Guru Mahārāj
preached to this man like that,
the man started to cry
because he was a little embarrassed
by what he had said before that,
like, “What is the benefit
of establishing some place,
just talking about Kṛṣṇa?
Why don’t we help people?”
And Guru Mahārāj said,
“You’ll not help them that way.
Only by re‒purposing attachment
will you help them.”
So the man started to cry,
and then he said,
“Swamiji, I believe in God”,
and Guru Mahārāj said,
“Your eyes
are the evidence of that.”
Hare Kṛṣṇa.