tapa, tapasyā means
to voluntarily inconvenience yourself
for the sake of spiritual realisation.
[Flowering Fragrance of Devotion]
But now, some taste has come
for those very things
that someone
was performing previously
out of a sense of following
the order of the Guru or obligation,
spirutual obligations.
Now they have a taste—
they like hearing about Kṛṣṇa,
they like hearing
about Mahāprabhu.
ruci then āsakti.
How much do they like it?
—You can’t take it
away from them.
Now they’re attached to it
the way that someone
becomes attached to anything,
they’re attached now to this.
When someone says,
“Oh, I have no taste
for hearing
the Bhāgavatam, the Gītā,
this, that, the other thing …”
“Guru Mahārāj said,
“Then stop hearing the Bhāgavatam!”
The person, “No,
I don’t want to do that.”
—“Then you do
have some appreciation.”
āsakti, then bhāva.
What does that mean here?
this bhāva, that the seed
of bhakti-latā bij,
sprouted, it blossomed,
now it’s produced a flower.
That flower has a fragrance.
It means that devotion
of that particular servitor has a fragrance
that Kṛṣṇa finds as charming
as a sweet smelling flower.
He wants to enhail that more and more.
It’s giving some joy to Kṛṣṇa.
The sort of devotional sentiments
that are manifesting in their hearts.
And when that intesifies
then it expresses as prem,
Kṛṣṇa prem.
Then what?
sneha, man, prāṇaiḥ, rāga, anurāga,
bhāva, mahābhāva.
But still this is so valuable.
You can say,
“Well, what if someone ...
they only had a brush with this
for a brief time.”
—Still, it’s the best thing.
sv-alpam apy asya dharmasya
trāyate mahato bhayāt
[Bg: 2.40]
Kṛṣṇa says, “Even a small
connection with this will …
trāyate mahato bhayāt
mahato bhayāt—it will save you
from the greatest fear.”
Which can be interpreted variously.
One place Prabhupād says,
“Resending in the animal species.”
But Guru Mahārāj  said
in another place
for a devotee the greatest fear is that
their service is not being accepted.”
It’s very different.
That’s the fear of a devotee
nārāyaṇa-parāḥ sarve
na kutaścana bibhyati
svargāpavarga-narakeṣv
api tulyārtha-darśinaḥ
[SB: 6.17.28]
Citraketu said,
“I only think …
I’m afraid of it’s
not having any seva.
Doesn’t matter where I’m—
in Heaven or Hell,
I want to service connection.”
That’s what’s important
to a devotee.
When Śrīla Gurudev came out
of the hospital in Sokvel
after his operation,
and he thought
he might leave the world.
He came back in
a very devastated physical condition
and it was also depressing to him.
But someone came forward
for hāriṇam,
and he began to smile.
In the midst of all this pain,
and suffering and misery,
he began to smile,
and he said,
“Oh, they’re still accepting
service from me.
They want more service from me.”
That’s how he interpreted it.
That made him happy.
That cancelled all the misery
of the body, mind, etc.
But we will still conclude
the way what Nārada’s told Vyās,
and what is the line
of Śrīla Saraswatī 􏰅Ṭhākur and his followers,
and what Kṛṣṇa reiterates
in Bhagavad-gītā that
sv-alpam apy asya dharmasya
trāyate mahato bhayāt [Bg: 2.40]
“Even slight connection with this
is ultimately benefitial for one.”
You can compare it to education,
as Guru Mahārāj once did,
“By pursuing education, there is no guarantee
that you’ll become Einstein,
but that’s not an argument
against education.
Still, you’ll become educated
as far as possible.
And you’ll benefit from that.
Same thing with spiritual education.