So I knew some devotees,
they thought
that you
put on headphones,
listen to Kṛṣṇa-nām,
or the Bhāgavatam,
and then wake up
enlightened.
[Spirit Over Matter]
It’s not a question  of having ­‘muzak’.
We have Kṛṣṇa conscious ‘muzak’,
and then wallpaper,
and just
surrounding yourself
with external paraphernalia
that that will induce
some sort
of spiritual awakening.
bhaktyā sañjātayā bhaktyā
[SB: 11.3.31]:
only devotion
can ignite devotion in another.
There’s no formula,
no method,
no step and
repeat procedure,
that will generate
spiritual substance.
So, Guru Mahārāj’s point
was that
no amount of finite
can generate the infinite.
Matter
cannot generate spirit,
but spirit
can manipulate matter.
Spirit can
express itself through,
but not that
by reconfiguring the mundane
we can achieve
the spiritual.
In the Prayers of
the Personified Veda,
the 87th chapter
of the 10th Canto,
this question occurs:
that if we’re using
the fleshy tongue,
and the voice box, and the body,
to vibrate sound
—Vedas are supposed
to be spiritual sound—
how can we vibrate
spiritual sound
if we’re using
mundane elements?
And this has to do
with the nature
of what is
genuinely spiritual.
Guru Mahārāj
liked to quote
Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur
in Śaraṇāgati,
where it says,
“When the heart
is under the influence
of Kṛṣṇa conception,
the power of the influence
of that conception
comes outwards from the heart
and expresses itself as sound.”
Not that we make a sound,
we say “Hare Kṛṣṇa”,
listen to that sound,
and then it purifies our hearts.
Rather, the heart
under the influence
of Sādhu, Śāstra,
Guru, Vaiṣṇava,
expresses spiritual sound.