The general strategy is
to invite the Lord’s mercy
towards someone who would be
a very good example
for redemption.
[“Redeem Me!”]
So sometimes the devotees are saying,
“If You want to test Your mercy
and its purifying capacity,
there’s no better specimen
than myself, as a fallen soul.”
And it is a genuine feeling.
I said to Śrīla Guru Mahārāj once that,
“If Kaviraj Goswami …”
He says, you know,
“Jagāi mādhāi haite muñi se pāpiṣṭha
purīṣera kīṭa haite muñi se laghiṣṭha:
‘I’m more sinful than Jagāi and Mādhāi.
If you hear my name,
you’ll lose your pious credits.
If you chant my name,
you’ll fall down.
I’m lower than the worm
in a stool’ [Cc: 1.5.205].”
Saying so many …
venting so much negativity.
So I said to Guru Mahārāj,
“It’s one thing that Kavirāj Goswāmī
is saying this,”
I said,
“but what if you actually are
more sinful
than Jagāi and Mādhāi?”
And Guru Mahārāj said “Oh!
Then perhaps this plenary power
is descending in you.”
Meaning:
Kavirāj Goswāmī doesn’t think he’s speaking
cleverly, poetically, euphemistically;
it’s a sincere expression
from his heart,
on account of the depth of his positive
penetration into Kṛṣṇa conception
—‘dive deep into Reality’—
that he can vent such negativity.
So it’s not a posing; it’s a sincere,
heartfelt expression.