It’s family life
with Kṛṣṇa at the centre.
So, for devotees—devotee families,
their life will be a happy one
if Kṛṣṇa is at the centre
of everything.
[Married Ashram]
And this is something
very extraordinary,
but if they will see one another
as eternal servitors of Kṛṣṇa,
superficially—husband, wife, child,
daughter, son—these things,
but on a deeper … and that’s there,
it’s undeniable and there,
but with the devotional eye awakened,
they’re able to see
that who’s my child—
is a superior devotee than I.
My child has more devotion
to Kṛṣṇa than I do.
That’s possible.
The husband of the wife;
the wife of the husband.
They can see, as servitors,
their servitor identity.
Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur says
in one of his songs,
“When this sort of genuine vision
is awakened,
then caring for that family and other
necessities is also Kṛṣṇa bhakti—devotion,
because you’re serving devotees.”
‘If’, I say ‘if’ that …
we want it to be real.
All these things are predicated.
Sometimes Śrīla Guru Mahārāj presented
many, one of many things; he would say,
“I suppose you want to know,
how far is it real,
how far is it true?”
We could say anything.
We can make any statement;
we can take any statement from the scriptures
and apply it to anything,
but how far is it true, how far is it real?
That we want to know.
But the possibility gives us some optimism,
and encouragement, and inspiration.