“Die to live” according to
Guru Mahārāj means:
you’ll have to die as you are
to live, get life
in a higher plane.
[Self Generation]
Yagya, the fire sacrifice,
what was the idea? Is that …
the self is thrown into the fire.
That old self is disintegrated,
and a new self appears.
The old self
characterized by exploiting tendencies
is disintegrated,
and a new self
characterized by dedicating tendency
is generated
or, we can say,
that dedicating tendency
generates a new self.
Guru Mahārāj mentioned the conclusion
of perhaps Kalyāṇa-kalpataru,
but where there’s Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur
talking about the nāma haṭṭa—
the market of the Holy Name,
and Nityānanda Prabhu.
This beautiful metaphor
for distribution of Kṛṣṇa-nām.
And Bhakti Vinod 􏰅Ṭhākur describes himself
in that market of the Holy Name …
There’s Nityānanda Prabhu,
the market of the Holy Name …
He said, “And this Bhakti Vinod
is a sweeper.”
That’s his position there,
he’s a sweeper.
What is he sweeping out?
—Undesirable things.
And Saraswatī Ṭhākur said,
“If that plane is so high,
that in that plane
Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur is a sweeper,
then I’m one of the straws
in his broom.”
And Śrīla Guru Mahārāj said,
“If we take it that
what he’s expressing
is a sincere
heartfelt expression,
then you can understand
the unitive construction of the svarūp.”
This type of humility
and dedicating tendency
is the unit of construction
of the svarūp—
of the spiritual form,
identity, personality.
So, however we can acquire
dedicating tendency
and association with our
godbrothers and godsisters
under the guidance of guru
and Vaiṣṇav,
that ‘die to live’ principle
can be employed.
The old self will disintegrate,
the golden dedicating self will manifest.