Visa granting officer—
Nityānanda Prabhu.
[Visa Granting Officer of the Spiritual World]
heno nitāi bine bhāi,
rādhā-kṛṣṇa pāite nāi
nitāiyer koruṇā habe,
braje rādhā-kṛṣṇa pābe
[Manaḥ-Śikṣā
by Śrīla Narottam Dās Ṭhākur]
Visa granting officer, Governer;
visa granting office,
Dhameshvar Nabadwīp,
Nityānanda Prabhu.
yatha yatha gaura-padaravinde
vindeta bhaktim krta punya-rasih
tatha tathot-sarpati hrdya-kasmad
radha-padambhoja-sudhambu rasih
[Ccd: 88]
“Yes!”, Prabodhānanda says,
“Give all your attention
those who are sukritivan,
sumedhasaḥ,
they will take the suggestion,
feel the compulsion
to offer themselves exclusivly
to the lotus feet
of Guru and Gaurāṅga.”
Where?
Nitāi, nitāi-pada-kamala,
koṭi-candra-suśītala
We have to—as Dās Goswāmī did,
as Kṛṣṇadās Goswāmī did—
get the shelter of the lotus feet
of Nityānanda Prabhu.
Guru Maharāj, “Doyal Nitāi,
Doyal Nitāi, Doyal Nitāi …”
Take shelter of the lotus feet
of Nityānanda,
and Nityānanda will give
the connection with Gaurāṅga.
bhaja gaurāńga kaha gaurāńga
laha gaurāńgera nām
[song by Kṛṣṇadās Kavirāj Gosvāmī]
Mahāprabhu told them,
yāre dekha, tāre kaha
‘kṛṣṇa’-upadeśa—
[Cc: 2.7.128]
“Tell everyone about Kṛṣṇa.”
And Nityānanda’s saying,
“Not enough time!
Bhaja Gaurāṅga,
worship Gaurāṅga,
chant the name of Gaurāṅga!
gaura-gatha grnanti
as do the members
of Śrī Chaitanya Sāraswat Maṭh.
Their preoccupation, occupation,
preoccupation
is singing the glories
of Mahāprabhu.
That means Rādhārāṇī.
yadi gaura na haita, tabe ki haita,
kemane dharitām de
rādhāra mahimā, prema-rasa-sīmā
jagate jānāta ke?
Vāsu Ghoṣ said, “This is why
Kṛṣṇa descended as Mahāprabhu—
to proclaim the glories of Rādhārāṇī
to everyone.
And the glories of Her supreme love,
Her kṛṣṇa-prema.”
This is the foundation
of the Kṛṣṇa consciousness movement.