How to go on
in the absence of Kṛṣṇa.
[Devotee of the Devotee of Krisha]
And interestingly this is the very,
very high subject matter
of the depths of separation,
expressed there,
in the conclusion of Śikṣāṣṭaka,
the conclusion of Caitanya-caritāmṛta,
very very high and deep things.
But miraculously, mysteriously
it’s also relevant to those
in the aspiring position—adarśan.
Adarśanān marma-hatāṁ karotu vā
[CC: 3.20.47]—how to go on,
how to pursue Kṛṣṇa consciousness
in the apparent absence of Kṛṣṇa,
in the apparent absence
of Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
It’s the critical point.
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
[is] saying that
if you can honestly, candidly
acknowledge and admit,
that you are not Kṛṣṇa conscious,
you have no Kṛṣṇa consciousness,
or as the great devotees
sometimes, they’ll say,
“I’m going
in the opposite direction.”
That’s also in these verses.
Rādhārāṇī and Vraja-gopīs—
they’re sometimes saying,
“They were better off before
they’ve met Kṛṣṇa.”
[Laughing]
So devotees’s thinking like that.
And Guru Mahārāj said,
“So if you can think like that—
honestly, candidly, assess yourself,
and say, ‘I appear to be untouched
by Kṛṣṇa consciousness.’”
He said,
“But, at the same time …
but I have no other shelter.
I have no other Lord than Kṛṣṇa,
and no other interest
than this association,
and service of His devotees.”
He said,
“Then you might be a devotee.”
And there’s nothing greater, better than
being a devotee of a devotee of Kṛṣṇa.
gopī-bhartuḥ pada-kamalayor
dāsa-dāsānudāsaḥ [Cc: 2.13.80]—
that’s also from Mahāprabhu.