Devotees in the Rupanuga line understand
quite comprehensively, clearly,
thoroughly, with clarity,
that you don’t get any more Kṛṣṇa
than in the presence of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī.
[Maximum Krishna]
Just like within this world there are
not only famous people,
but maybe particularly them,
like ‘aiśvaryasya samagrasya vīryasya
yaśasaḥ śriyaḥ’ (Vp: 6.5.47),
who can take it; Bhagavān.
But people will say,
“I can’t really be myself
with these people or that person.
I’m looking for someone
where I can totally be myself.”
That’s what they hanker for.
Sometimes Guru Mahārāj will say,
almost humorously, that
“Kṛṣṇa likes to surround Himself
with ignorant people.”
Wait, I thought you said, “Tathā
paramahaṁsānāṁ munīnām amalātmanām
bhakti-yoga-vidhānārthaṁ kathaṁ
paśyema hi striyaḥ”;
only the highest section of liberated souls
(SB 1.8.20).
Now you’re saying that Kṛṣṇa likes to
surround Himself with ignorant people?
What does he mean?
Jñāna-śūnya-bhaktas.
Those who can suppress
Kṛṣṇa's majestic aspect
back to the aprākṛta region where,
as Guru Mahārāj said,
say a king wants to just dress casually.
It doesn't mean he doesn't have a crown
and a sceptre and all these things,
but he just prefers sometimes
to dress in an ordinary way.
Is he still a king?
Of course. He doesn't have to have …
For some people though,
maybe he needs to have the crown,
the sceptre, and the throne
and everything,
for them to think of him that way.
Here, we have the inverse.
These devotees,
they are so much in love
with Kṛṣṇa, personally,
with His personality, His character traits,
tendencies, etc.
that His majestic divine aspect
is so much eclipsed
by their love and affection,
that it’s sent to the background
and is practically non-existent.
So, that Kṛṣṇa.
We're told Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī's name.
This is mentioned, quoted,
of particular interest,
in the fourth chapter of Ādi-līlā,
where Kavirāj Goswāmī’s laying the ground
for what is Chaitanya-charitāmṛta.
She is known as Kṛṣṇamayī.
How much Kṛṣṇa is in Her?
Guru Mahārāj said, “It is not that
She’s just full of Kṛṣṇa,
but it is as if anywhere
She casts Her glance,
Kṛṣṇa is manifest.”
So he will say,
“You don‘t get any more Kṛṣṇa,
quality Kṛṣṇa, and quantity Kṛṣṇa,
than Kṛṣṇa at the right hand
of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī.”
If you go to Kṛṣṇa direct, even direct,
He won’t fully be Himself in your presence.
He’s only fully Svayam Bhagavān Kṛṣṇa,
to the extreme.
Reality the beautiful. Sweetness.
Love, beauty, charm, sweetness personified.
kandarpa-koṭi-kamanīya-viśeṣa-śobhaṁ
(Śrī Brahma-saṁhitā. 5.30)
Kṛṣṇa, at the right hand of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī.
The way Kṛṣṇa appears with Her
is super-extraordinary
even by Kṛṣṇa's own standards.
Hare Kṛṣṇa.