We shouldn’t think that
voice of Guru, the order of Guru,
the mantra of Guru,
the instruction of Guru,
is some sort of a static thing—
“Oh, I was initiated twenty years ago,
thirty years ago,
forty years ago, any years ago”—
[Dynamic Faith]
but rather, Guru Mahārāj says,
“Vilasatu hrdi nityam bhakti”,
it’s eternally vibrating in our hearts—
the words, the message,
the order of Śrīla Saraswatī Ṭhākur.
That’s what got Śrīla Prabhupād
to leave Vṛndāvan.
I just spoke to Yudhamanyu Prabhu,
he was saying,
“How old was Prabhupād?”
And we know he was something like
69 years old when he boarded
the Jaladuta ship
to go from India to America,
and these things cannot be accidental
or coincidental.
But Kṛṣṇa arranges things,
he’s even kind to atheists,
so if you want to disbelieve,
He’s not going to disturb
your disbelief;
He’ll give you all sorts of reasons,
statistical analysis, to disbelieve.
But faith cultures another thing too.
So, Prabhupad …
What is the name of the ship?
The Jaladuta, which means
‘the water messenger’.
And the diary they give—
they have a few; it’s a cargo ship
and they give a few diaries to the passengers,
it’s only a few passengers
and you have a little diary
you can keep on the ship—
and Prabhupād would write things in it,
and at the top,
the running head of each page says,
“We carry India’s message
of peace and good will.”
So the ship called the Jaladuta,
the water messenger,
niṣṭhā śanti parāyaṇa, is carrying Prabhupād
over the ocean to America
to begin the world-wide inundation
of Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
Hare Kṛṣṇa.