It is interesting to note
when you deal with, let’s say, art.
They are called ‘recording artists’,
and there’s other type of artists.
[Art Without Ego]
When someone is supposed
to be really purely inspired
most often
they will describe the experience
as if something came down
and used them as an instrument for expression.
“I don’t know
where that came from.
Just it all came to me in a flash
all of a sudden.”
Or critics of art, they will say,
“We see in this artwork—
there is no trace of ego.”
The artists themselves
may have had a very big ego.
We read books.
People were shocked to find out.
They are like study ‘10 great artists’,
and they will say,
“This guy was a total jerk.
He had a huge ego.
He was mean to people.”
And people
[demonstrating astonishment]
But he produced such beautiful artwork.
What they mean, by application, is:
those moments were inspired
as if some higher power
came down
and used this person
as an instrument for expression.
They’ll start using adjectives or words,
that’s saying like, “It was divine”
or “Almost divine.”
Like they don’t want to give you the impression
that they believe in God.
So they’ll say,
“It was like that.”
What people describe
about spiritual experience?
“It was like that.”
[Laughing]
But if an artist and hero
are speaking in a generous sense,
if someone who is an artist
can speak of being inspired
and offering themselves
as an instrument for revelation,
then why not spiritually speaking?
The only question will be …
In principle we can’t object to the method,
the delivery mechanism.
All we can really question is:
whether or not it’s real.
The method of delivery
is irrelevant here.
What our interest will be
is: is it real?
Does it really have a touch
of the divine?
Is it really under divine influence
or is it something else?
We don’t need to argue
about how it came.
What substance is there?
Is it really
divine descended substance
or is it something else?
And to make that
judgement or assessment
then we’ll have to take
these things seriously
and study them carefully
under the guidance of experts.