You have
to become acquainted
to measure the value
of any substance.
You have to know the qualities,
characteristics of that substance.
[Spiritual Litmus Test]
Or be in connection with
someone who does.
So I’ve mentioned this
in regard with
jewels, gold,
and other things.
Why do you think
in the scientific world
that they have so many tests?
And the test, not only test,
it’s not like anyone,
“Do this test at home.”
There are some things like that.
But other things …
even to perform the test
requires an expert.
There’re so many variables,
so many subtle things
to factor in and consider
that it requires an expert
to conduct the test.
There’re many examples of that
in Vedic literature as well,
and in the pastimes
of Mahāprabhu.
So parīkṣā, parīkṣit
means to examine.
So to examine something
you have to be acquainted
with the absolute standard by which
it can be measured against,
and then you can
determine its relative value.
So minimally we hear
asat-saṅga-tyāga,—ei vaiṣṇava-ācāra
[Cc: 2.22.87]
asat-saṅga means
bad association,
but asat—
that which is no permanent value.
That’s why Śukadev
tells Parīkṣit Maharaj
varīyān eṣa te praśnaḥ
kṛto loka-hitaṁ nṛpa
ātmavit-sammataḥ puṁsāṁ
śrotavyādiṣu yaḥ paraḥ
[SB: 2.1.1]
But your question,
my dear king, is very good.
There’s a thousand questions
you can ask about anything.
The temporary persons, places,
and things of this world.
But you’re asking a question
that’s beneficial for everybody,
because it transcends the temporality
of mundane existence.
So, everyone will benefit by hearing
the answer to this question.
asat—that which is temporal,
temporary is not the focal point
of people who are serious
about spiritual culture.
They are focused on sat,
that which is permanent,
eternal, spiritual in nature.
Hare Kṛṣṇa.