Those who tell us about Kṛṣṇa,
they’re really giving you something.
Now we can understand something
about that.
[Life-saving Talks]
Who brings you the news
about Kṛṣṇa,
there’s no more better messenger
in the world,
a greater philanthropist,
there’s nothing better you can do
for somebody
other than introduce them to Kṛṣṇa.
Agreed?
Show of hands.
We’re having these programs
at this devotee …
we’re staying in his sister’s room
or something,
and she’s kind of like
going on with everything.
But she sees night after night
we’re talking about Kṛṣṇa,
Mahāprabhu, this, that,
and she was saying, like,
“Why don’t you …
If you really want to help people
why don’t you go outside
and distribute some food or something?
Every night you sit here
talking about Kṛṣṇa.”
So I could understand,
she didn’t understand
the value of Hari-kathā,
that it’s tava kathāmṛtaḿ
tapta-jīvanaḿ—
[SB: 10.31.9]
life-giving, life-saving, nectar.
Just to eat some more food
and go on with the death march
in the land of mortality
is not a glorious activity.