Strong foundation is necessary.
So that what is built
upon the foundation will last,
be something
lasting and substantial.
[Modest Natural Growth]
I’ve told
when I saw the gate
under construction
at Govinda Kuṇḍa,
and saw they’re digging
so deep into the ground,
I asked Śrīla Āchārya Mahārāj,
“Why are they digging so deep?”
He said, “So, it’ll have
a strong foundation.”
And then the gate
will last forever.
So, there is a tendency
for new recruits or neophyte devotees
to try to go too far,
too soon, too fast.
We’ve seen the mangoes
on the trees outside the studio.
And it’s so tempting
to pick one.
But a month goes by,
another month goes by,
and they’re just approaching
the ripe stage.
But it’s so tempting to pull it,
pluck it prematurely.
That’s the conundrum,
one of the difficulties
experienced by the neophyte,
whereas Guru Mahārāj
advises us,
‘modest natural growth’.
They do this thing in India,
they artificially
ripen mangoes with carbide,
because people
are so eager for the mangoes.
They can’t wait for them
to come to market at the natural time.
So, they put this artificial,
this horrible chemical in them somehow,
and it artificially ripens them.
And if you’ve ever had one,
it tastes horrible actually.
If you get one by mistake
you’ll know.
So …
Modest natural growth.
Sometimes Guru Mahārāj
would quote this thing,
“Deserve, then desire”,
or Śrīla Prabhupād’s
famous statement:
“Work now—samādhi later!”
[Laughing]
Saraswatī Ṭhākur,
Guru Mahārāj said,
he would say
to this one devotee,
“I’ve got my eye on you.
I am aware
of everything you’re doing,
all the sevā you’re doing.
And the time will come
in the future,
when you’re older”,
he said,
“I’ll give you one assistant,
you’ll be taking Kṛṣṇa-nām
going deeper,
but now continue as you are.
But don’t think I am not seeing you,
unaware of what your position is.”
That sort of faith
we have to have also.
śraddhānvito ’nuśṛṇuyād atha varṇayed yaḥ
[SB: 10.33.39]
That as Guru Mahārāj would say,
“Our guardians are real!”
Under the ever-watchful
eye of Yoga-māyā.
She knows who needs what,
which servitors need
any particular thing,
and that’s being arranged.
If it’s out of a genuine
service necessity,
the paraphernalia for sevā
will come to that person.
That’s a guarantee.
When Śrīla Saraswatī Ṭhākur
was wondering about
getting the inspiration
to start Gaudiya Math,
and all those activities
that would ensue,
and wondering,
“Where will the funding come?”
Then, we’re told,
that he had a vision
of the Pañcha Tattva.
And they’re reassuring him
not to worry about these things—
that all the resources necessary
for sevā will be supplied.
That faith we must have.
But for it to be real and substantial
it has to be sevā.
Actually sevā … That means for Kṛṣṇa’s
enjoyment satisfaction.