Through sevā we will achieve focus.
It has to be about sevā.
We’re trying to serve the Holy Name,
not to have the Holy Name serve us.
[Devotees of the Invisible]
That’s a big difference.
It may sound the same;
the syllables may sound the same,
but the intention is different.
Anyābhilāṣitā-śūnyaḿ
jñāna-karmādy-anāvṛtam;
ulterior motive is the difference
(Brs: 1.1.11).
We’re told—again, by
Rūpa Goswāmī (Cc 2.17.136),
“Ataḥ śrī-kṛṣṇa-nāmādi
na bhaved grāhyam indriyaiḥ.”
The Nāma-ādi means
Nāma-rūpa-guṇa-līlā;
the Name of Kṛṣna,
the Form of Kṛṣna,
the Qualities of Kṛṣna,
the Pastimes of Kṛṣṇa,
are beyond the grasp
of our mind and intellect.
Then what?
Then what are we doing?
Once, Guru Mahārāj said,
“We’re devotees of the invisible.”
Everyone says, “Bunch of foolish people!
Not one of them has seen Kṛṣṇa.”
Gurudev, even, once asked Guru Mahārāj,
“All this talk about Kṛṣṇa-nām,
has anyone actually got that?”
It’s a Gurudev-type question.
Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur says,
“We were in the presence
of Jagannāth Dās Bābājī on Ekādaśī.
He was taking Kṛṣṇ-nām,
hair standing on end, shivering
and trembling in the body”,
just as we’ve seen described
in the scriptures,
described by Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur—
that out of the sound of Kṛṣṇa-nām,
when it's real, what is the effect?
Read what Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur says.
You can read it in Search for Śrī Kṛṣṇa,
the chapter called Nectar of the Holy Name.
You need to understand what it is really.
He said, “Sometimes I’m taking Kṛṣṇa-nām
and some mysterious form and colour
appears from the sound.
Mysterious form: Kṛṣṇa.
Mysterious colour: Śyāmasundar.
Śyāmasundar Kṛṣṇa appears
out of the sound
of Bhakti Vinoda Ṭhākur’s
Kṛṣṇa-nām.
He said, “And then He takes me.”
And so many other things …
and he’s describing intense ecstatic states.
So then we’ll have to say,
“Well that’s not our position.
What are we doing?”
Previously, people would say something like,
“Oh, today I really chanted good rounds.”
I mean I think the really good rounds
are when Kṛṣṇa comes out of the sound
and reveals His Form and His Qualities,
and takes you into His Pastimes,
according to Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur.
Again, we’re saying, “What are we doing?
We’re following the order
of Guru and Vaiṣṇava.
You take this Kṛṣṇa-nām—Mahaprabhu also—
you take this Kṛṣṇa-nām
under the guidance of a Vaiṣṇava,
and engage in service and association.”
And one day the steel frame in which
our hearts are encased will melt.
One day.