And there’s nothing
we can do about this.
We have to live
with that somehow.
But …
What for do I know
that this is like this?
What for?
What do I get from this?
You think that I think
that I am all this?
[Everybody Wants Happiness]
But where is “me” at all?
Where is “me” in all of this?
Who are you?
What are you?
The unexamined life
is not a life worth living.
That’s Socrates’ opinion.
Meaning ātmā‒samīkṣā,
self analysis—
to try and understand:
who I am,
where I’ve come from,
what is my purpose.
We have good and evil
principles in us.
If we will just live through
with our good principles
without unwrapping them,
then it’s clear
we have failed our goal.
But if we only keep them,
without developing,
then apparently there is no goal
or purpose of [such] existence.
But to end the life
on some higher level
than you started from,
that can be the only purpose
of the human life.
Everyone only thinks
about what to eat,
what food is good,
what bad,
what doctor to consult,
what spa to go to.
Everyone is only thinking
“how” to live,
but “why”—
nobody wants to think.
Everybody wants happiness.
No one can deny
that they want to be happy.
They want love, affection,
a loving affectionate
happy relationship.
Atheist, theist, agnostic—
alike.