Nietzsche once said
facetiously,
“If I were to believe in God,
He would have to be a good dancer!”
[Reality is Dancing]
I recall visiting with Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
in the afternoon one day,
and he’s sitting in his chair,
like that, [tapping]
as he would do sometimes,
he’d go like this, and
when he was very happy …
I gave my daṇḍavats
and sat there, and he said,
“I say, the Ultimate Reality
must be dancing.
What do you say?”
[Laughing]
I thought, “The Ultimate Reality
must be dancing,
what do I say?
[Laughing]
He said, “I say, the Ultimate Reality
must be dancing,
what do you say?”
[Laughing]
Of course,
it was a rhetorical question.
And Guru Mahārāj explaining …
And it’s actually on the basis
of Prema Dhāma Deva Stotram,
but it shows us a few things.
One is that Guru Mahārāj,
until the end of his life,
was generating
fresh Kṛṣṇa conscious substance.
He wasn’t merely repeating
what he had realised in 1941
or 195…
Time is there irrelevant.
He’s in a dynamic process,
in an inner dialogue
that was consistently, constantly,
revealing new substance.
This is how
Guru Mahārāj’s meditation for 50,
70, 80, 90 years
keeps yielding nectarine substance.
So now,
pūrṇam means ‘fulfilled’.
Well, as he would express,
when someone is really feeling satisfied
or fulfilled to the nth degree—
here, the Greek
comes to our aid:
ekstasis, ecstasy, means actually
‘outside of yourself’;
you’re so happy
that you’ve become ecstatic;
you go …
you’re outside of yourself.
And what Guru Mahārāj
is saying here,
“When you’re satisfied
to the nth degree,
and the joy cannot be contained
within yourself,
it expresses itself
outwards as ecstatic dance.”
So, on the basis of this,
he’s saying,
“The Ultimate Reality
must be dancing!”
Reality must be dancing,
but not in some monotonal;
Scientific … they say, “All the atoms
and particles are all moving,
it’s like a dance.”
They’re just talking
about movement.
But now we’re back
to the original point.
Guru Mahārāj would say,
“Movement enhanced with beauty is dance!”
Just movement is not dance per se,
but when it’s enhanced with beauty,
it’s dance.
Speech … When the element of beauty
is added to speech, it becomes song.
So the better writers,
even the better prose writers …
Literary critics and observers,
they will say,
“Oh, at this point in his writing,
it approaches poetry.”
They mean it has
a musical element to it;
even though it’s prose,
it’s so perfectly written,
it’s now as if it’s being sung.
What is the world … In that perfect world,
where we’re told,
kathā gānaḿ nāṭyaḿ gamanam—
[Bs: 5.56]
“Where what they speak is like song.”
That’s what it means.
Not that they just sing
everything they say.
What is being said,
because it’s saturated
with Reality the Beautiful—
it’s song,
and movement is dance.
Why?
Because they’re under the influence
of the Ultimate Beauty,
Who’s also dancing.
His ecstasy is not something
that He strives to achieve,
like to move from the unhappy position
to a happy position—
that’s not Kṛṣṇa!
He’s ecstasy personified.
He’s already ātmārāma.
So, then the question comes up—
Viśvanāth and others deal with it—
then why does He seem to enjoy
His pastimes with the Vraja–gopīs?
What is He approaching them for?
He’s already ecstasy personified.
He’s ātmārāma.
Various descriptions
are given there:
like a child playing
with its reflection,
one point is told, but also,
that being ecstasy personified,
His movements are ecstatic.
He doesn’t move
to achieve ecstasy;
He’s already
in an ecstatic condition,
but He’s extending
or expanding that to others,
particularly in Gaura-līḷā,
Nāma-saṅkīrtan,
and many other things.
All of it is divine movement.
So I thought, as Guru Mahārāj is giving
so much sukṛti to Hegel,
if Nietzsche met Guru Mahārāj,
Guru Mahārāj could give him
a concept of God that he could believe in,
that the Ultimate Reality
must be dancing.