[Possibility of Impossible Love]
Well, first of all
we should wonder
why is it that we’re repeatedly
expressing these things.
In songs, in poetry, in novels,
in motion picture, movie … everything.
we revisit these subject matters
repeatedly.
People find themselves
in a position
where they’re expressing
eternal love to someone,
when we know statistically,
objectively speaking it’s not true.
And mostly as time goes on
it’s more and more not true.
We’re not sure how much
it was true before,
but at least now that we keep records
on all this stuff,
we know the potential
for these eternal relationships to dissolve.
“I love you forever,
or until you’re 40.” [Laughing]
Śrīla Avadhūt Mahārāj,
“Or untill you fat.” [Laughing]
There are many
different objective criteria
that somehow destroy,
dissolve that love,
and we’re still hankering
for this eternal love scenario.
So then we think:
then what are we doing?
You yourself are saying
it’s not a thing of this world.
But stop for a second.
We didn’t say it’s impossible
to connect with.
We’re saying it’s not a thing
of this objective world.
What is expressed in those stories,
that eternal love
that’s in the song, the story,
the movie, etc.
is not really a thing
of this world.
They say,
“No, that’s just in the movies!”
Right.
But does that mean
there’s not a plane where …
it doesn’t exist anywhere.
Not even in the movies?
No. So we understand—
we’re hardwired to seek this;
to seek something that
we’re trying to address
through objective culture
in the objective …
So it’s a purely subjective thing
that we’re trying to feed objects to.