Now Freud tells us
everyone in this world
is bewildered
by the erotic principle.
That’s what’s driving
all of existence.
[Erotic Principle]
And in this sense
he’s stumbled upon
a very essential principle.
He’s saying the sexual principle
is driving everything;
it’s driving the ants,
it’s driving the human beings,
love makes the world
go ’round.
It’s the force
that’s behind everything.
And he has his system
of interpretation for that.
But see,
what he’s expressing
is a perverted reflection
of the truth.
The erotic principle, expressed
in unalloyed devotion
in the spiritual world,
that’s the source
of everything.
The loving relationship
between Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa
is the source
of everything,
and this world is
a perverted reflection of that.
So Freud was right
in identifying:
this is what’s driving everything
in the world, is the erotic principle.
And what the spiritual experts
are saying,
in its unalloyed unconditional
pure expression,
it’s what’s driving everything
in the spiritual world.
So naturally what he’s saying
is true here,
because in the Supreme Reality,
it’s the source, it’s the origin,
it’s driving everything.
And in the place where it’s perverted,
similarly,
but, in the words Saraswatī Ṭhākur uses
sometimes, it’s “vitiated”.
Rather than it being wholesome
and pure and nourishing,
it’s degrading.
So Freud identified:
everyone in the world
is under the influence of
Cupid, Madan.
Madan Mohan means
the seductive charm,
attraction, sweetness,
of Kṛṣṇa,
is capable of bewildering Cupid.
Everyone here bewildered by Cupid,
Cupid bewildered by Kṛṣṇa.
But by extension,
what it means is
everyone who’s bewildered by Cupid
can overcome that bewilderment,
illusion,
by redirecting this innate
intrinsic principle towards Kṛṣṇā.
Kṛṣṇa can fulfil—
if we take that principle
to its highest level
of fulfilment and expression—
he alone can fulfil that.
Kṛṣṇa.