Here the body is the biological
expression of the soul’s delusion.
[Delightful Lunatics]
That’s why there is jalajā nava-lakṣāṇi
sthāvarā lakṣa-viṁśati …
Padma-purāṇa is saying:
8 400 000 species.
Don’t trip out on the numbers …
If you take three colors: RGB
or red, yellow, blue,
whichever three
you want to deal with,
and start combining them,
you get how many variations?
Millions.
So, taking these three:
tama, raja, sattva—
millions of variations.
That’s what
they’re telling you.
The body’s the biological expression
of the soul’s delusion—
it’s the outcome
of exploiting tendency.
ahaṅkāraḥ,
bhūmir āpo ’nalo vāyuḥ
khaṁ mano buddhir eva ca
ahaṅkāra itīyaṁ me
bhinnā prakṛtir aṣṭadhā
[Bg: 7.4]
Bhagavad-gītā is saying:
these elements,
these mundane elements
form a body,
the gross body
that is built
upon a subtle body,
which is based upon ego—
ahaṅkāra.
So, it’s all … And what is that,
that ego tendency?
kartāham iti manyate
[Bg: 3.27]
another Gita śloka,
what does it say?
prakṛti …
kāraṇaṁ guṇa-saṅgo ’sya
sad-asad-yoni-janmasu
[Bg: 13.22]
prakṛteḥ kriyamāṇāni
guṇaiḥ karmāṇi sarvaśaḥ
ahaṅkāra-vimūḍhātmā
kartāham iti manyate
[Bg: 3.27]
It’s saying again:
ahaṅkāra, ego.
The ego of exploitation,
exploiting tendency
hṛd-rogam—the heart infused
with consumer tendency
expressing that,
the exploiting tendency—
body is generated from there.
But there’s another world …
paras tasmāt tu bhāvo’nyo
[Bg: 8.20]
jiva bhuta sanātanaḥ
[Bg: 15.7]
But beyond this world
there’s another world,
where the body is based upon
dedicating tendency.
So, Guru Mahārāj said, “In that plane
form and substance are one.”
And I was just remembering,
when I first went to the temple,
the Śrī Śrī Rādhā-Kṛṣṇa Temple
in Haight-Ashbury in 1969,
December of ’69,
the devotees …
and I say this with affection,
Trivrikam Mahārāj,
he gets some joy when I say.
He would say,
“What was it like?”
And I said, “I thought
they were delightful lunatics.”
The group.
But I remember they
were always telling me this:
they’d point to the sky and say,
“You see that sky?” And I’d go, “Yeah.”
They’d say, “Beyond that sky
there’s another sky
called the spiritual sky
full of planets.”
And I’m like,
“Wow man, far out!”
But they’re quoting
Bhagavad-gītā.
paras tasmāt tu bhāvo ’nyo …
[Bg: 8.20]
beyond this sky, Kṛṣṇa is saying,
there’s another sky.
So, that world, which is the world
of our aspiration.