One lady got initiated,
and she said,
“What should I do
for my morning sādhana?”
And I said,
“What are you doing now?”
She said,
“Oh, I chant …
My daughter and I,
we chant the Nārāyaṇ kavacha.”
[Don’t Miss the Point]
I said,
“Why did you do that?”
She said, “Well, we’ve read in the book.“
It says, “It’s so auspicious,
and it should be done,
and everyone should …”
But interestingly,
even in Prabhupād’s lifetime
one of his disciples,
leading disciples,
reported to him
that he was doing that.
And Prabhupad said,
“Why are you doing this?”
He said,
“It’s you wrote in your book,
one should do this
and how important it is,
and you’ll get this,
and you …”
So, you read in a purport
something that to him
it seemed like Prabhupād
was giving a resounding,
wholesale, full recommendation
to do this.
But when
he talked to him personally,
he told, “I never told you to do that.
I’m not asking you to do that.”
But he said,
“Well, in the book …”
That’s another thing.
There are so many things.
They’ll say,
“One who hears this,
one who does that,
one should …
is advised
to do this.”
But that’s why
we have guru—
sādhu, sāstra,
guru, Vaiṣṇav.
We have the scriptures
and then the living scriptures.