The one who is
most dear to Kṛṣṇa.
Still, we could say,
“Well, that’s a general thing.
It’s not filling in the blank.”
[Guru | Closer Examination]
And as connotation increases,
denotation decreases.
—Oh, so we are being told here
the general principle,
that we’ll think of our guru
as being most dear to Kṛṣṇa.
The Vaiṣṇava‒sresta—
the best of the Vaiṣṇavas,
we’ve approached
to take shelter of as guru,
and it is
we will think of
our guru is the one
who’s most dear to Kṛṣṇa,
as indicated by
Raghunāth Dās Goswāmī,
echoed by
Viśvanāth Cakravartī Ṭhākur.
He says
kintu prabhor yaḥ priya eva tasya
vande guroḥ śrī-caraṇāravindam
where in the beginning
of that śloka, and it says
sākṣād‒hari‒tvena samasta‒śāstrair
uktas tathā bhāvyata eva sadbhiḥ
The scriptures are telling us—
see guru is Kṛṣṇa.
‘kintu’ means here,
but upon closer examination
‘su–samīkṣā’—
greater scrutiny.
If we are following that thread
of Kṛṣṇa conception, of guru as Kṛṣṇa,
he’s saying,
“If we look deeper,
we’ll see—
kintu prabhor priya.
Guru is really
prabhor priya,
the one who is
most dear to Kṛṣṇa.
So, if guru is seen …
we say—
see Kṛṣṇa with greater,
a more refined way of seeing,
and you’ll see prabhor priya—
the one who is most dear to Kṛṣṇa.
Of all of those
who are most dear to Kṛṣṇa
that means Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī.
What did Saraswatī Ṭhākur
say at the conclusion
of the Caitanya-caritāmṛta’s purport?
—If I look deeply,
with greater depth of vision,
depth of field,
infinite depth of field
at Bhakti Vinod 􏰅Ṭhākur,
and Gaurakiśor dās Bābājī Mahārāj,
I see Gadādhar Paṇḍit,
and Svarūp Dāmodar,
or ultimately—
Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī.
I see my guru as
Hare Kṛṣṇa.