Maharaj, you're always describing such a deep topics,
and it can be deeper and deeper,
and you've also just told us, you can start from Guru Maharaj's conception
and go from there, and it is also very deep,
and just now you've mentioned that mind cannot understand all of this stuff,
but also we feel that we need some foundation like firm basics,
especially newcomers.
So, is it the proper approach that you just dive deep into those deep conceptions?
No, what I've just said, your heart is hankering for something.
Your heart is hankering. Who can fulfil that?
That's foundational.
Who can address what you heart is seeking?
A person, place or thing in this world.
You're searching for beauty. Krishna is Beauty personified.
That is simple and direct.
You're searching for happiness. Krishna is Happiness personified.
Oh, how? Want to understand more?
So, people are not searching for something superficial actually.
By default they are, but that will not make them happy.
Searching for superficial things.
You know, the husk is not the rice.
The shell is absent the substance.
These are foundational things.
To understand that you're the spiritually conscious being
in a body generated by karmic circumstance
and you're searching for fulfilment.
That's foundational.
So what will fulfil you?
Any amount of the mundane or quality of mundane or
on account of your subjective nature must it be something located in the subjective world.
I'm not here to hammer over somebody's head day after day:
"You are not the body. You are the soul. Read the second chapter of Bhagavad Gita."
Sometimes. But I'm not going to speak every day this theme.
I did that. For 10 years.
So 10 years of hammering this on people's heads.
You look in the Chaitanya Charitamrita and see how much of that type of hammering is there.
So we are devotees of Mahaprabhu.
So you can't just... We are discussing Mahaprabhu and talking about him. And you say:
"It's all too high! You know, people just need to know what are they gonna do tomorrow morning when they wake up."
Oh, alright. But then we have to go all the way back to that.
"These things are so high!" and then we go back.
Can the infinite make itself known to the finite?
Do you accept this principle?
The infinite can make itself known to the finite.
And someone says: "No, I don't accept that."
And someone says: "Yes, I accept that."
Right. Then we need to accept the principle of Revealed Truth.
Here's this one level of Revealed Truth: in the Bible or the Quran or the Torah.
Then another level of Revealed Truth: in the Vedas, the Upanishads, the Puranas.
Another level of Revealed Truth: in the Mahapurana, the Bhagavatam.
How serious are you to know these things?
Or just always wanna go back to ABC?
2 + 2 = 4
We need addition, subtraction, you know...
Gonna go back to grade one and go "ABCD", learn the ABCs.
How does the song go?
No, I know, how it goes.
So it has the place, but [we] can't stay forever.
And say: "Wow, grade three, they're discussing things that..." Yes.
You're dealing with the Ultimate Reality and say: "Well, it's pretty deep!"
I guess it should be, shouldn't it?
It's the Ultimate Reality. From which everything has come.
So, how much... How earnest, serious is someone to become acquainted with these things?
And we're saying: "Yes, so then..."
Read the Bhagavad Gita, read the second chapter of Bhagavad Gita about ātmajnāna,
understand the difference between the body, the gross body, the subtle body, etc.
That's general.
Aham Brahmasmi ─
that's not, in this sense, a Vaishnava aphorism.
That's for everyone.
"I am Spirit."
The mayavadis say that, the vaishavas say, everyone says that.
That's general.
And someone says: "No, I don't accept that."
Then they're not gonna go very far.
And it's a waste of time to argue with them.
They say: "No, i don't believe in God or Spirit." Okay. That's your choice.
For those who do, there is a way to systematically study these things.
We are primarily Gaudia-vaishnavas.
That means we study the teachings of Sri Chaitanya Mahaprabhu.
His teachings about Krishna-bhakti, devotion to Krishna.
So, that's our primary emphasis.
But we understand, in another context, someone...
they need, they want to...
What would be appropriate for them is to hear ātmajnāna ─
the analogy about the soul, the spirit ─ it's in the second chapter of Bhagavad Gita and other places.
We believe that, we preach it all the time.
But here, I mean, the context of answering questions about Mahaprabhu,
that would be to go backwards.
Talking about the differences between Mahaprabhu's, you know, Puri pastimes and His Nabadwip pastimes.
So, the question by its nature is a deep one.
Then there must be some understanding about what is Nabadwip, what is Puri,
who is Chaitanya Mahaprabhu, what is Vrindavan, Krishna, Jagannath, Dvaraka.
All of these things.
Which are the heart of the matter of the discussion of Gaudiya-vaishnavas,
the followers of Mahaprabhu.
They delight in having these discussions.
What's the first sloka of Prema Dhama Stotram?
Do you know?
deva-siddha-mukta-yukta-bhakta-vrnda-vanditam
papa-tapa-dava-daha-dagdha duhkha-khanditam
krsna-nama-sidhu-dhama-dhanya-dana-sagaram
prema-dhama-devam eva naumi gaura-sundaram
Talking about Mahaprabhu.
"The Devas, the Siddhas, the Muktas, the Yuktas, the Bhakta vrinda,
they are all singing His praise.
So then someone asks, you know, what is a Deva, what is a Siddha, what is a Mukta, what are Bhaktas.
─ "Well, it's very deep!" ─ It is.
It's, you know, endless ocean deep.
That's what we're interested in.
Still, we are talking to someone who knows absolutely nothing about these things.
Why should we conceal Krishna?
It may be the only opportunity they have in their live they hear something about Krishna.
So, we may not want to say something so general.
We want them to here about Krishna.
Even if only for a moment it would be the crowning glory of their lifetime is to hear the sound of the name of Krishna.
Once in their life.
Even you say: "Krishna says in the Bhagavad Gita:
For the soul there is neither birth nor death."
na jāyate mriyate vā kadācin
Maybe more then hearing the slokas, they've heard "Krishna says".
So, it's all good.
But we are inclined to discuss the pastimes of Sri Chaitanya Mahaprabhu.
Especially in the association of devotees.
If we are going to some public program and we are dealing with people have no knowledge or exposure,
we may take another route.
We're talking about these things all the time, a hundred times, a thousand times.
Matchmaker.com ─ it that too deep?
Is that something people have never heard of?
Or can't relate to?
If I'm talking about matchmaker.com, finding your soulmate,
and segway from there to a little talk about God, Divinity, the Personality of Godhead.
So depends on who the audience is.
And our audience is... we're here right now... is primarily devotees.
And those aspiring to go deeper, to have a deeper understanding of these things.
Which was... Our Guru Maharaj, what did he say?
He prefers to speak on higher things in a small circle then general things, lower things in a large circle.
That's who my Guru is.
That's his preference. That's how he spoke.
I'm trying to reiterate, reproduce things that I've heard from him.
These are the things he talked about. They are very deep. That's right.
They are.
Swami Maharaj himself said: "He has deep realizations of Krishna. If you would have heard them, you will faint."
That's my interest. I'm interested in those things.
So I told ─
when Govinda Maharaj told Guru Maharaj, he said: "Goswami Maharaj wants you to tell him something that will make him faint."
That's my interest.
But if someone earnestly wants to discuss other things, we are ready for that too.
We'll discuss it again.
I don't mean to indirectly make less of the ātmajnāna, atma-tattva, that's within the pages of Bhagavad Gita.
I repeatedly read those slokas, relish them.
But what is it saying there?
āścarya-vat paśyati kaścid enam [Bg: 2.29]
"If you have a glimpse of your soul, you'll be astonished."
So, that's what Krishna says.
And again, I've been this point,
all the things He's saying there, we can repeat them with great confidence,
considering who it is that speaking.
So, someone's hearing that,
it may touch them in a particular way,
when they hear those things.
And they want to hear more.
To go further, to go deeper.
But we should not forget that Krishna Consciousness ─ it's...
there is nothing deeper then this.
So, if in discussing it we say, from time to time, high things or deep things, that's going to happen.
By virtue of what we're talking about.
We are talking about the Ultimate Reality.
And as revealed in the pastimes of Mahaprabhu.
So it's very deep. Someone hearing those things...
As I told, once a lady, a journalist, was interviewing me in San Jose,
discussing many things that I didn't care to discuss. It was a very awkward conversation.
And while I'm talking to her, Mahayogi Maharaj knocked on the door and he said:
"There are some professors visiting from the school in the Midwest."
I was thinking of showing them an excerpt of a video of Guru Maharaj.
"Do you have any recommendations?" and I said:
"Oh, show, you know, number... this one."
And he goes: "Which one?"
I'm saying: "The one where Mahaprabhu is saying — if I have a drop of love for Krishna, I would have died a long ago."
He goes: "Oh, yes, yes, that's a great one." And he leaves. And he's gonna go show them this excerpt of talk of Guru Maharaj.
And that newspaper reporter who had no interest in Krishna Consciousness other then
finding out some, you know, ugly things or awkward things.
This is the sole purpose of this meeting.
And I'm somehow reluctantly participating in this.
And then, now we gonna go back to this talk and she said:
"Can I ask you a question?" And I'm saying: "Yeah, lady, go ahead."
And she goes: "Why did that person say 'if I had a drop of love for Krishna, I would have died a long time ago'?"
That was interesting to her.
Not some talk about consciousness.
That picked her imagination.
And I said: "Well... I'm glad you asked.
I thought you'd never ask."
Then I told her, as best I could, something.
And I'm not saying: "So then we should just randomly shoot fragments of high things out into the environment."
I'm not saying that. That's just how that happened at that time.
Yes, generally we do start with the elementary position. That's correct.
Atma-tattva, ātmajnāna in the second chapter of Bhagavad Gita and other parts of Gita.
And there're talks similar to that in the Bhagavatam.
That is the way we begin.
But there's also... you look at how Mahaprabhu teaches Rupa Goswami, rupa śikṣā, that structure.
Wandering to the length and breath of the universe in different lifeforms,
if they fortunate they get connection with Guru,
and get the bhakti-lata-bija, the seed of devotion.
That's how Mahaprabhu begins in His talk to Rupa.
Then He talks about karmis, jnanis, yogis and devotees.
In terms of gradation.
Then he's talking about the seed of devotion growing and developing.
That's for someone who is interested
in devotion.
Knowing about what Krishna Consciousness is.
So, still generally we will start that way and then...
As I told once, in a conference with reporters they ask Prabhupad, they're sitting there with their... :
"What is the purpose of life?"
And we were all thinking, because we're trained to say like:
"The purpose of the human form of life is to engage in self-realization or God-realization
or to realize your love of God." There's this wrote recitation of answers we're trained to say in general.
So we were thinking he'll probably say one of these things.
Wonder which one he's gonna say.
So they go: "Swami, what is the purpose of life?" And he says: "Enjoyment."
And they all go: "Oh, really?"
And then he said: "Problem is, at present, no one is enjoying."
And then he gave a little talk about that.
About suffering.
That's more in the theme of the second chapter of Bhagavad Gita.
So, we worship that. And we'll forever preach that.
But when we are with our group who except these things, embrace them,
then we're pursuing what is exclusively Gaudiya.
Guru Maharaj is saying: "As connotation increases, denotation decreases."
They used to make a poster showing how everyone in the world loves Bhagavad Gita.
Not just us.
So, Emerson, Thoreau... Thoreau, you know:
"In the morning I bathe my intellect in the cosmogonal and stupendous glory of the Bhagavad Gita;
in comparison with which our modern literature seem trivial and puny."
And Nitzsche and this one, everyone loves.
Juan Mascaro, Christopher Isherwood, Annie Besant, Hitler.
Everybody loves the Bhagavad Gita.
As connotation increases, denotation decreases.
We say that we have the Gita...
And mayavadis...
You know, Gaudiya-vaishnavas, Sri-vaishnavas, Madhavas, Mayavadis...
We say: "No, but Bhagavad Gita must be understood in terms of the light of Srimad Bhagavatam."
Then not the mayavadis, others... Now it's the Vaishnavas:
Madhava line, Sri-vaishnavas Ramanuja line, Gaudiya line.
And if we say: "And Bhagavatam should be understood through Mahaprabhu and His, you know, Rupanuga line."
Then you're with Gaudiya-vaishnavas.
Still, Guru Maharaj would say —
because, as you pointed, we do from time to time discuss things that are very high —
"So I take the name of Nityananda — Dayal Nitai, Dayal Nitai, Dayal Nitai —
to restore myself to my former position, 'cause maybe in discussing these high things I said something wrong,
I made a mistake or I commited an offence.
So I take the name of Nityananda to humbly resume my natural aspirational humble position."