What we’re searching for?
What everyone is searching for?
Actual love, affection which,
when that general concept is refined
and expressed purely,
it’s prem or Kṛṣṇa-prem.
It’s not a thing of this world.
[Love Is not a Thing of This World]
Love means prem,
means Kṛṣṇa-prem,
they’re synonymous.
There’s not one love here,
and Kṛṣṇa-prem is another love.
Love means Kṛṣṇa-prem.
Accept no substitute.
When Śrīla Prabhupād put it this way
in one of his purports in Bhagavad-gītā,
he said, “When our natural propensity
for love, meaning this Kṛṣṇa-prem,
when it’s perverted,
it’s expressed
as lust towards matter.”
Which is similar to a statement
in Caitanya-caritāmṛta , as
kāma andha-tamaḥ, prema nirmala bhāskara
[Cc: 1.4.171]
Kām, which is the word for ‘lust’.
Andha-tamaḥ means
‘the dense dark ignorance’.
Prem nirmala bhāskar—
it’s like pure sunshine.
Or Guru Mahārāj said once,
“Dense light …
dense darkness—dense light.”
kāma andha-tamaḥ, prema nirmala bhāskara
Guru Mahārāj compared
to North Pole and South Pole,
meaning—on a superficial glance,
observation
we notice that they look similar—
North Pole, South Pole.
Saying, but he’s invoking this
(try to whisper)
he’s invoking this metaphor
to tell us: but they’re worlds apart
like night and day—
North Pole, South Pole.
So, appear to be similar,
but are worlds apart.
So, the love, the so-called love
of this world
it appears to be similar to divine love,
but they’re worlds apart.
ātmendriya-prīti-vāñchā—tāre bali ‘kāma’
kṛṣṇendriya-prīti-icchā dhare ‘prema’ nāma
[Cc: 1.4.165]
Again, it’s mentioned
in Caitanya-caritāmṛta :
ātmendriya—that trying
to have everything egocentric,
when our goal is the satisfaction
of our own senses,
seeing an egocentric world
that everything is meant
for our pleasure, satisfaction,
that we’re taking ourselves
to be the centre of all existence—
that’s called kām.
kṛṣṇendriya-prīti-icchā dhare ‘prema’ nāma
[Cc: 1.4.165]
But reconfiguring oneself,
redirecting oneself
towards the Absolute centre,
hṛṣīkeṇa hṛṣīkeśa-sevanaṁ bhaktir ucyate
[Nārada-pañcarātra]
of dedicating ourselves
and our acquired energy
in the service
the senses of Kṛṣṇa,
saying, this caused
by the name of prem.