Bhāgavatam
in the beginning says,
tasyaiva hetoḥ prayateta kovido
na labhyate yad bhramatām upary adhaḥ
[SB: 1.5.18]
Direct yourself towards that
acquiring that,
which you can’t achieve
in wandering the length
and breadth of this Universe.
[The Naked Truth | Don’t Sell Yourself Short]
What does that mean?
That in all species of life
there’s sensual activities:
āhāra-nidrā-bhaya-maithunaṁ cha—
eating, sleeping,
sex, defense
is not something exclusive
to human civilization.
So the Bhāgavatam śloka here
is one of the ten verses
given by Nārada to Vedavyāsa.
He’s saying,
“Use your energy now
for something that’s exclusive
to human society.
If all these other possibilities
are there in other species,
don’t waste
your time on that.”
Prabhupād used to be blunt
about it quoting Ṛṣabhadev
from the 5th Canto,
nāyaṁ deho deha-bhājāṁ nṛloke
kaṣṭān kāmān arhate viḍ-bhujāṁ ye
[SB: 5.5.1]
The naked truth,
blunt and brutal.
Ṛṣabhadev says,
“Why try
for the same pleasures
that are available
to the stool-eating pigs?”
Saying,
“As a human being,
is this how you should
direct your energy?”
We once were
in Vṛndāvan,
and Śrīla Prabhupād
was giving a lecture.
And, ah … [Laughing]
He is talking
about this verse,
tapo divyaṁ putrakā yena sattvaṁ
śuddhyed yasmād brahma-saukhyaṁ tv anantam
[SB: 5.5.1]
Ṛṣabhadev telling his sons,
“My dear boys,
don’t waste your time
on the same sort
of pleasures
that are available to the animals,
stool-eating pigs.
Do tapasyā, means
to voluntarily inconvenience yourself
for the sake
of spiritual realization.
You have to suffer
one way or another,
so this sort of voluntarily …
voluntary suffering
will help you make progress
in the spiritual path.”
Anyway,
brahma-saukhyaṁ tv anantam—
instead of this temporary pleasure,
yan maithunādi-gṛhamedhi-sukhaṁ hi tucchaṁ—
[SB: 7.9.45]
same thing from Prahlād,
[Ṛṣabhadev] is saying,
brahma-saukhyaṁ tv anantam—
try for brahma-saukh,
spiritual pleasure,
which is anantam,
it’s unlimited.
Don’t sell yourself short.
Anyway, explaining this śloka
he was talking about
the so‒called “stool-eating pigs”,
and Prabhupād said …
[Laughing]
said, “Not only …”
I mean he was shocked
as he travelled around the world,
flying on airplanes,
visiting different countries.
He said, “Not only if they’re trying
for the same pleasures
as the stool-eating pigs,
but they’re
also eating them.
I have seen,
on the airplane.”
[Laughing]
And he said, “What is this called,
pig’s intestine?”
And one devotee,
way in the back from England,
smart, he goes, “Sausage.”
And Prabhupād goes,
“Just see, immediate answer.”
[Laughing]
Like, Prabhupād couldn’t for the life
of him think of what this was.
But that … he went,
“Sausage.”
—Just see,
immediate answer.
Like, you know
what I am talking about.
As gross as this is,
you know what I’m talking about.
From first hand experience.
Said, “Not only theу’re trying
for the same pleasures, but …
dot, dot, dot …”
Try to get that thing
that’s only available
in human society—
that’s the point.
What is that that’s
exclusive to human beings.
athāto brahma-jijñāsā
[Vedānta-sūtra: 1.1.1]
spiritual inquiry,
beyond the base necessities
of existence,
internal culture.
Love beyond body connection.