As I’ve mentioned many times,
Rukmiṇī says
śrutvā guṇān bhuvana-sundara śṛṇvatāṁ te
[SB: 10.52.37]
Hearing about You …
She hasn’t met Kṛṣṇa yet.
By hearing about Him though,
she has.
[ Sound Reveals Form ]
Some conception
has come to her
about the form of Kṛṣṇa,
His quality … everything.
Her we take in a big way.
We say, “Oh! It’s Rukmiṇī,
she’d knew Him before.
It’s not like that.
She had not met Him.
The wives of the yajñic brahmins,
the vipra-patnīs
they hadn’t met Kṛṣṇa.
They’d only heard about Him
from fruit sellers.
And others in Vrindavan
they heard about Him,
by hearing about Him, they got …
See, you could have a general idea,
but if you’ve realized
at a particular advanced stage
of devotion, by hearing
they are getting a very precise
conception of the form.
So it’s mysterious,
acintya-bhedābheda—
having not met,
but through hearing
they’re meeting,
but it’s creating
a hunger to meet.
So that’s why we’re advised
to culture separation.
And we say, “Well, if we haven’t met
how we can culture separation?”
By hearing.
The mystery is
that by hearing about Kṛṣṇa
some conception comes to you.
Whether vague, or more refined,
or substantial.
And gradually,
some hunger develops.
Like, I mean
a cheap example would be
that in this world …
babies …
they are hungry
before they’ve eaten.
And than they’re fed.
So this is a mysterious thing.
You say, “Well, how can
you have the hunger?”
Well, you can.
You can awaken in you
by hearing about Kṛṣṇa
can awaken a hunger,
and a sense of loss.
So beautiful,
and what’s been lost to me?
Now it’s compelling.
So, hunger in this sense
hunger precedes tasting
and is a necessary component
for taste is hunger.
So separation is the necessary component
for relishing union.