These descriptions,
they’re not ordinary descriptions.
That’s why whenever
we repeat them
we should try to do so
with the greatest accuracy.
[Different Tastes of Truth]
Or, if Kṛṣṇa’s pastimes
are being told to children,
they should be accurate;
we shouldn’t make things up,
they should accurately follow
the story.
Because here’s a child
offering themselves to hear these things,
they need to get it right
so that they’ll get
the maximum benefit for it,
because they’re perfectly constructed,
and in the future,
when they recall hearing these things
in their childhood,
they may have a tendency
to reproduce them accurately.
Bhakti Vinoda Ṭhākur,
placing emphasis on the pastimes of Kṛṣṇa,
the childhood pastimes of Kṛṣṇa
in Śrīmad Bhāgavatam,
and the pastimes of
Chaitanya Mahāprabhu.
So in one sense,
the whole idea is total immersion,
and we have a glimpse
of that when we hear
from the higher devotees.
And interestingly,
even the same pastimes
can be described accurately
by great devotees
but still have a different taste
and quality to the rendering.
As we find, in the beginning of
the Bṛhad-bhāgavatāmṛtam,
Mahārāj Janamejay
is speaking with Jaimini Ṛṣi,
and he’d just finished
a Mahābhārata recitation,
and Janamejay says, “I heard this previously
from Vaiśampāyana Ṛṣi”—
this story,
the Mahābhārata divine story.
He’s saying, “Essentially you’ve told
the same things,
but the way you’ve told it,
it has a particular
madhura, sweetness,
quality to it,
and your recitation
has awakened in me
a desire for more of
this madhura sweetness.”
And it’s in response to that,
that Jaimini Ṛṣi begins telling
the Bṛhad-bhāgavatāmṛtam.
So it shows it’s not merely
the transfer of information
or story, "Oh, I heard that story”,
but how it is told,
the way Vṛndāvan Dās Ṭhākur
is telling some pastimes,
and similar pastimes
are being told by Kavirāj Goswāmī.
Out of fear of committing
maryādā-vyatikram,
impertinently surpassing
the predecessor,
Kavirāj Goswāmī would say,
“What Vṛndāvan Dās has described,
it would be an aparādh
to describe the same thing,
but if there’s some aspect
that was not described,
I’ll describe that.”
He says that humbly,
but we know from Śrīla Guru Mahārāj,
Vṛndāvan Dās Ṭhākur,
when we worship Chaitanya Bhāgavat,
is from the perspective of
a cowherd boy—sakhya rasa;
Chaitanya-charitāmṛtam is an exclusively
madhura-rasa literature.
Just like in my first actual meeting with
Śrīla Guru Mahārāj,
where Kṛṣṇadās Bābājī Mahārāj
took myself
and Bhakti Abhay Nārāyaṇ Mahārāj up to
the lotus feet of Guru Mahārāj,
at one point,
Bhakti Abhay Nārāyaṇ Mahārāj
said to him, “I find I’m more attracted
to Chaitanya-charitāmṛtam
than Śrīmad Bhāgavatam.”
Like, a bold statement.
But Guru Mahārāj
just responded very matter-of-factly,
saying, “Of course,” he said,
“because Śrīmad Bhāgavatam
presents rasa—takes us from
the plane of ontology to rasa—
but in gradual development,
culminating in madhura-rasa in the 10th canto,
whereas Chaitanya-charitāmṛtam
is an exclusively
madhura-rasa literature,
so naturally that is
your preference.”
And I was saying,
“It is?”