bhaktyā sañjātayā bhaktyā
[SB: 11.3.31]
You can only get devotion
from someone who has it.
[Instructions in the Womb]
So Prahlāda Mahārāj
responds by saying,
matir na kṛṣṇe parataḥ svato vā
mitho ’bhipadyeta gṛha-vratānām
adānta-gobhir viśatāṁ tamisraṁ
punaḥ punaś carvita-carvaṇānām
[SB: 7.5.30]
matir na kṛṣṇe parataḥ svato vā—
you can’t get Krishna consciousness;
this what I have,
you can’t get this
on your own.
Guru Maharāj would say,
“You have to connect
with the power supply,
the source.”
And not only
can you not get it yourself
by your own endeavors,
even if you combine with others,
you still won’t get it;
you won’t get it
as a group endeavor;
through democracy.
In other words,
it’s not ascending pluralistic democracy,
but descending exclusive theocracy.
Gṛha-vrat—those who have vowed,
pledged allegiance
to the mundane,
adānta-gobhir viśatāṁ tamisraṁ—
then those,
whose idea of freedom
is for the senses,
not from the senses,
they are entering
into deeper and deeper
levels of darkness.
punaḥ punaś carvita-carvaṇānām
Doing what?
Like ‘chewing the chewed’—
over and over again.
Whatever little bit
of apparent taste
may have been there
in the beginning,
has vanished long ago.
He says,
na te viduḥ svārtha-gatiṁ hi viṣṇum
durāśayā ye bahir-artha-māninaḥ
[SB: 7.5.31]
They are thinking
that what the heart wants—
how to find fulfillment,
love, affection—
that you’ll find
in the superficial,
the external aspect
of a thing,
not realizing
that it is internal culture.
svārtha-gatiṁ hi viṣṇum
durāśayā ye bahir-artha-māninaḥ
andhā yathāndhair upanīyamānās
te ’pīśa-tantryām uru-dāmni baddhāḥ
[SB: 7.5.31]
He said, so it’s like
what is this world—
it’s the blind
leading the blind.
What Śukadeva tells
in the beginning of Bhāgavatam,
apaśyatām ātma-tattvaṁ—
[SB: 2.1.2]
those who cannot see
the self, the soul.
For what Guru Maharāj said,
“Socrates had to die for”
talking about the existence of ...
Who can have no ability
to self-see, to see the self—
it’s like the blind leading the blind.
What will be the end result?
And what is the solution?
naiṣāṁ matis tāvad urukramāṅghriṁ
spṛśaty anarthāpagamo yad-arthaḥ
mahīyasāṁ pāda-rajo-’bhiṣekaṁ
niṣkiñcanānāṁ na vṛṇīta yāvat
[SB: 7.5.32]
Prahlad Maharāj says,
“You have to be bathed
in the dust of the lotus feet
of a devotee.”
mahīyasāṁ pāda-rajo-’bhiṣekaṁ
—an abhiṣeka of pāda-rajaḥ
Then you can have this.
He is trying to think,
“Where did he get that?”
Then we hear when Kayādhu
was taken to the ashram of Nāradā
that there even though
Prahlād was in the womb, in utero,
he’s hearing all the instructions
of Nārada Muni.