Sometimes you’ll say,
“What should be
the first preaching point?”
[Heartfelt Heartshare]
Well, you could have
a discussion about that,
you could analyse—
these are the kind of things
generally people should hear first.
ātmā‒jñāna to paramātmā-jñāna …
there’s a sequence of how
to present these things.
We appreciate that.
but at the same time
I like to suggest that
whatever it is you’ve appreciated—
share that.
Because that would be said
in a more heartfelt way.
It’s one thing—the rote recitation
of perceived siddhānta,
but another thing when someone,
“What do you like about it?”
And you say,
“Well, this is what I like.”
Like Guru Mahārāj
always repeated about
this one lady said,
disciple of Prabhupād,
when she’s visiting the Math.
She said what she liked about
Kṛṣṇa consciousness—
is we’re being given a chance
to have a family life with Kṛṣṇa.
Guru Mahārāj
quoted that for 20 years.
You can listen in …
regularly this comes up in his talks.
He was that impressed.
He liked that so much
that she got it.
Although she was
a relatively new devotee,
and from a foreign country,
but that appealing to her.
When Bhakti Madhur Bon Mahārāj
met with Guru Mahārāj,
and he was introduced,
and he mentioned to Guru Mahārāj
he’d read the Bhagavad-gītā.
So, Guru Mahārāj
said to him,
“Of what you read,
what did you like?”
And he said, and this scored
a lot of points for him;
he said, “I liked the part
where Kṛṣṇa says,
‘Give up everything
and surrender to me’.”
And Guru Mahārāj
started to smile.
[Laughing]
So, it reminds me also of
once a newspaper reporter
came to interview me.
And it was the particular time where
the Kṛṣṇa consciousness movement
was not getting good press,
we could say.
And so I was really not happy
about having to do this interview also.
Knowing that embarrassing sort
of awkard questions were going to be asked.
But somehow I had to do it.
And so, we’re talking
and while we’re doing this
Mahayogi Maharaj came into the room
and some scholars
were visiting from a university.
And he wanted
to show them
a particular tape
of Guru Mahārāj  speaking.
And I knew these tapes
very well
and where it would be,
like which one it was.
I said, “Oh, show them this one.”
And he went.
And he goes, “Which one is that?”
I go, “It’s the one where is said,
‘If I had a drop of love for Kṛṣṇa
I would’ve died a long time.’”
And he goes, “Oh, oh, yeah
that one, yeah, right, OK.
Right, that will be in.”
And so, he goes out and then
I turn to this woman,
and she is like:
“now we have to go back
to this stuff.”
And she stops for a second,
and she says,
“Can I ask you a question?”
And I’m saying,
“Yes, lady. What?
What do you want to know?”
And she said,
“Why did that person say,
‘If I had a drop
of love for Kṛṣṇa,
I would’ve died
a long time ago.’”
“Why did he say that?”
So, you wouldn’t think
that that would be like
what you would lead with.
But that she found,
hearing that,
it had some mysterious pull
on her heart and consciousness.
She wanted to hear
more about it.
And that’s when I started
preaching to her.
And I was as surprised, maybe
more surprised than her.
Because I had a stereotype
in my mind—
oh, this is reporter
who’s trying to trick me.
And I was in a very poor
state of consciousness, actually.
But by her asking that question,
she opened the door to another zone.
Then I became very happy,
we had a nice discussion ...
everything changed at that point.
And I would’ve never thought
like to begin with that.
But then we can see
Kṛṣṇa had another idea.
So, we want to be open,
as fallen as we are,
as unqualified as we are.
We’ll say, “ Kṛṣṇa …”,
like Prabhupād in his poem,
when he says,
when he reaches America,
I mean,
it’s almost humorous,
but it’s not.
It’s heartbreaking,
but he says,
he’s now in America after ...
and almost dies on the ship
on the way over—heart attack.
And he says,
“You must’ve brought me here
for a reason.”
That’s what he thought.
How humble! How …
I mean, it’s heartbreaking!
Saying “You’ve brought me here
for a reason.”
Must be!
So, he concluded,
he said,
“Then make me dance,
make me dance,
make me dance, oh Lord,
make me dance.”
Like—use me
to do something.
So, that’s the proper mood
always of the devotees.