We may think the position
of guru is one of master.
We say: the spiritual master,
prabhu, the guru.
[Guru: Master and Servant]
He said, but really
the position of the guru
is to be the servant of the disciple,
as much as the pūjārī
who’s preparing the fruit
to be offered to the deity.
What do they have to do?
They take one fruit,
a fruit comes
into their possession.
They are the servant of the fruit,
not the master of the fruit.
The fruit has come to them,
they think this fruit needs to be cleaned,
and then peeled of these things
and then fit.
Then it’ll be fit
to be offered to the deity.
So, the service of the guru is
to cleanse the impurities of the disciple
and then gradually through
proper instruction …
and infused spiritual conception,
those layers: karma and jñāna,
they are peeled away and then
the golden servitor is revealed,
who’s fit to enter the serving group
of the lotus feet of Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa.
That’s the service
that is performed.
And
Śrīla Saraswatī Ṭhākur—we’ve heard
that he was saying, “Dāso ‘smi”.
First of all—calling his disciples
prabhu, which means ‘guru’.
Prabhu, we think,
“Oh, you call everyone ‘prabhu’ …”
No.
It actually …
If you want to understand
what the word means—it means ‘guru’.
Only guru is called ‘prabhu’.
Why we are telling everyone
such-and-such ‘prabhu’?
Because Saraswatī Ṭhākur saw
his disciples as prabhu, as guru.
And he said—and if it ever, if ever
the time comes where I’m chastising them,
like: “I’m the guru and
listen to me for your own benefit!”,
he said, “If that type of mood comes”,
he said, “that is my pralāpa.”
Pralāpa means ‘delirium’. He said,
“Sometimes I become delirious
thinking I’m the master,
and you’re the servant.
But that’s a delirious condition
that should come infrequently.
Normally, I’m seeing myself
as your servant, dāso 'smi.”
And we might think,
“Oh, we are being told this—
these are stories
that are being handed down.
Self–serving stories
that are being handed down.”
Don’t think like that.
The fact is—it’s true.
You think how to readjust and
readjust, and readjust ourselves
to the point, where we can come and
understand—these things are true;
they are not stories,
they are the truth.
The truth
is being extended to us.
And it’s only being
limited by our disbelief,
or causeless
unwillingness to believe.
That expression sometimes
Prabhupāda used to—
‘a causeless unwillingness’.
Where does it come from?
Guru Mahārāj called ‘the anti-Kṛṣṇa
tendencies we have acquired’.
Where do they come from?
It’s so unfortunate.
But our good fortune,
bhāgyavān jīva,
is to come in connection
with the lotus feet of guru and Vaiṣṇava.
That’s all good fortune.
Guru Mahārāja said
then in the end of that
‘Śrī Guru’ preface he said,
“When the gentle hand of Śrī Guru
wipes away all the tears
of the suffering souls
in this world”—
that is why Kṛṣṇa is manifesting
Himself to us as guru.